<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-27310</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and health sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Infectious diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial diseases</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacteremia</subject><subject>Osteomyelitis</subject><subject>Staphylococcal infection</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Healthcare-associated infections</subject><subj-group><subject>Nosocomial infections</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Contribution of the <italic>nos-pdt</italic> Operon to Virulence Phenotypes in Methicillin-Sensitive <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus nos-pdt</italic> Operon</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sapp</surname><given-names>April M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mogen</surname><given-names>Austin B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almand</surname><given-names>Erin A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>Frances E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>Lindsey N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>Anthony R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>Kelly C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Microbiology and Cell Science, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Department of Microbiology, North Carolina State University, Raleigh, North Carolina, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><addr-line>Department of Cell Biology, Microbiology and Molecular Biology, University of South Florida, Tampa, Florida, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><addr-line>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, North Carolina, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freitag</surname><given-names>Nancy E.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Illinois at Chicago College of Medicine, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">kcrice@ufl.edu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: KCR AMS EAA ABM LNS. Performed the experiments: AMS EAA ABM FR ARR KCR. Analyzed the data: AMS ABM FR LNS KCR. Wrote the paper: KCR AMS ABM EAA LNS ARR.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<elocation-id>e108868</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article, free of all copyright, and may be freely reproduced, distributed, transmitted, modified, built upon, or otherwise used by anyone for any lawful purpose. The work is made available under the Creative Commons CC0 public domain dedication.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Nitric oxide (NO) is emerging as an important regulator of bacterial stress resistance, biofilm development, and virulence. One potential source of endogenous NO production in the pathogen <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is its NO-synthase (saNOS) enzyme, encoded by the <italic>nos</italic> gene. Although a role for saNOS in oxidative stress resistance, antibiotic resistance, and virulence has been recently-described, insights into the regulation of <italic>nos</italic> expression and saNOS enzyme activity remain elusive. To this end, transcriptional analysis of the <italic>nos</italic> gene in <italic>S. aureus</italic> strain UAMS-1 was performed, which revealed that <italic>nos</italic> expression increases during low-oxygen growth and is growth-phase dependent. Furthermore, <italic>nos</italic> is co-transcribed with a downstream gene, designated <italic>pdt</italic>, which encodes a prephenate dehydratase (PDT) enzyme involved in phenylalanine biosynthesis. Deletion of <italic>pdt</italic> significantly impaired the ability of UAMS-1 to grow in chemically-defined media lacking phenylalanine, confirming the function of this enzyme. Bioinformatics analysis revealed that the operon organization of <italic>nos-pdt</italic> appears to be unique to the staphylococci. As described for other <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> mutants, inactivation of <italic>nos</italic> in UAMS-1 conferred sensitivity to oxidative stress, while deletion of <italic>pdt</italic> did not affect this phenotype. The <italic>nos</italic> mutant also displayed reduced virulence in a murine sepsis infection model, and increased carotenoid pigmentation when cultured on agar plates, both previously-undescribed <italic>nos</italic> mutant phenotypes. Utilizing the fluorescent stain 4-Amino-5-Methylamino-2',7'-Difluorofluorescein (DAF-FM) diacetate, decreased levels of intracellular NO/reactive nitrogen species (RNS) were detected in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant on agar plates. These results reinforce the important role of saNOS in <italic>S. aureus</italic> physiology and virulence, and have identified an <italic>in vitro</italic> growth condition under which saNOS activity appears to be upregulated. However, the significance of the operon organization of <italic>nos-pdt</italic> and potential relationship between these two enzymes remains to be elucidated.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported in part by the following sources: Air Force Institute of Technology Civilian Institution Program Scholarship (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://m.airforce.com/benefits/air-force-institute-of-technology" xlink:type="simple">http://m.airforce.com/benefits/air-force-institute-of-technology</ext-link>) to EAA, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.niaid.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx" xlink:type="simple">http://www.niaid.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx</ext-link>) 1P01AI083211 sub-award to KCR, Resubmission funding from the University of Florida Emerging Pathogens Institute (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://epi.ufl.edu/news-and-events/epi-seed-funding-and-resubmission-support/" xlink:type="simple">http://epi.ufl.edu/news-and-events/epi-seed-funding-and-resubmission-support/</ext-link>) to KCR, UF Institute of Food and Agricultural Sciences Early Career Award to KCR, National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.niaid.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx" xlink:type="simple">http://www.niaid.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx</ext-link>) grant AI093613 to ARR, and National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.niaid.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx" xlink:type="simple">http://www.niaid.nih.gov/Pages/default.aspx</ext-link>) grant AI080626 to LNS. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Nitric Oxide (NO) is a highly reactive free radical gas that easily and rapidly diffuses across biological membranes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Lancaster1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Toledo1">[2]</xref>. One cellular source of NO production is via the NO synthase enzymes (NOS), whose three isoforms are well-characterized in mammals and are involved in a wide variety of cellular processes, including regulation of blood pressure, nervous system signaling, and protection against pathogens <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Sudhamsu1">[3]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Lipton1">[9]</xref>. All three mammalian NOS enzymes consist of both an oxygenase and reductase domain, which together catalyze a five-electron heme-based oxidation of the guanidine nitrogen of L-arginine to L-citrulline <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Alderton1">[7]</xref>. The power and versatility of NO as a signaling molecule is exemplified by its ability to diffuse several cell diameters away from its site of synthesis in eukaryotes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Lancaster1">[1]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Malinski1">[10]</xref>. NO can react directly or indirectly via formation of reactive nitrogen species (RNS) with a variety of cellular targets, including DNA, lipids, and proteins containing transition metal centers and thiol groups (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Wink1">[11]</xref>).</p>
<p>A number of studies in recent years have revealed that some bacterial species also contain a NOS homologue in their genomes, equivalent in most cases to the oxygenase domain of eukaryotic NOS (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Sudhamsu1">[3]</xref>). The role of bacterial NOS can be quite varied, participating in diverse physiological functions such as biofilm development, biosynthesis of plant phytotoxins, stress resistance and virulence <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Kers1">[12]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov2">[18]</xref>. Although this versatility suggests a specificity of function to individual bacterial species, an increased understanding of the regulation and exact cellular targets of bacterial NOS may help divulge an evolutionary link between prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms. Previous analysis of bacterial genomes has shown that bacterial NOS enzymes are primarily found in Gram-positive species such as <italic>Streptomyces</italic>, <italic>Bacillus</italic>, and the staphylococci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Sudhamsu1">[3]</xref>. A number of biochemical studies have focused on determining the crystal structure and characterizing the enzymatic activity of these bacterial NOS enzymes (reviewed in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Crane1">[4]</xref>). By comparison, much less is understood about the regulation of bacterial NOS enzyme expression, activity, and participation in cell signaling.</p>
<p><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> is a versatile pathogen that is highly transmissible in healthcare settings as well as in the community at-large. Of increasing concern is the fact that many methicillin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MRSA) strains are genetically-resistant to nearly all antibiotics currently used in the clinical setting. In fact, a recent report by the CDC estimates that 80,000 MRSA infections and 11,000 MRSA-associated deaths occur in the US per year <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Centers1">[19]</xref>. These alarming statistics underscore the importance of deciphering new drug targets to expand our arsenal against this devastating pathogen. Bacterial NOS enzymes are an attractive target for drug development, since they have been shown to confer tolerance to oxidative stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Shatalin1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Vaish1">[20]</xref> and antibiotics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov2">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>, promote bacterial survival inside neutrophils <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Vaish1">[20]</xref> and macrophages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Shatalin1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>, and contribute to virulence <italic>in vivo</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Shatalin1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>. A search for small molecule inhibitors of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> NOS has also recently been undertaken and described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Holden1">[22]</xref>. With respect to <italic>S. aureus</italic>, exogenous addition of NO to cultures protects this bacterium from challenge with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and antimicrobials <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov2">[18]</xref>. More recent studies of <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> mutants have revealed that this gene contributes to a number of virulence properties, including protection against oxidative stress <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Vaish1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>, antibiotics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>, antimicrobial peptides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>, and leucocyte-killing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Vaish1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>. A role for saNOS in <italic>S. aureus</italic> virulence was also recently confirmed in a murine abscess model of infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>. Although multiple models infer the importance of bacterial NOS during infection, the exact molecular mechanisms by which NOS elicits its control on bacterial stress resistance and virulence have not been elucidated.</p>
<p>Given the established relevance of saNOS in virulence and as a potential drug development target <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Holden1">[22]</xref>, it is surprising that relatively little attention has been given to the genetics, regulation, and the exact cellular targets of this enzyme. Inspection of the <italic>S. aureus</italic> genome has revealed that the <italic>nos</italic> open reading frame (ORF; SAR2007 of the MRSA252 genome) is separated by only 19 nucleotides from the downstream SAR2008 ORF. No identifiable transcription termination signals appear to be present between <italic>nos</italic> and SAR2008, suggesting that they may comprise an operon. SAR2008 (henceforth referred to as the <italic>pdt</italic> gene) encodes a prephenate dehydratase (saPDT) enzyme, which catalyzes the formation of phenylpyruvate from prephenate during phenylalanine biosynthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Tan1">[23]</xref>. Therefore, this current study was undertaken to probe the potential genetic and functional relationships between saNOS and saPDT in a clinical methicillin-sensitive <italic>S. aureus</italic> strain. These experiments demonstrate that the <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> genes are co-transcribed, and that the expression of this operon is upregulated during low-oxygen growth. Furthermore, a <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant displayed reduced virulence in a murine sepsis model and increased carotenoid pigmentation when cultured on agar plates, both previously-undescribed <italic>nos</italic> mutant phenotypes. An assay to detect intracellular NO/RNS in <italic>S. aureus</italic> was also developed using the fluorescent stain DAF-FM diacetate, and demonstrated decreased levels of intracellular NO/RNS in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant when cultured on agar plates.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title>
<p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains and plasmids used in this study are listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108868-t001">Table 1</xref>. Planktonic <italic>S. aureus</italic> cultures were grown either aerobically (1∶10 volume to flask ratio, 250 RPM) or under low-oxygen conditions (7∶10 volume to flask ratio, 0 RPM), as indicated for each experiment. <italic>S. aureus</italic> was freshly streaked from a frozen stock onto tryptic soy agar (TSA) for 24 hours, followed by overnight aerobic growth in tryptic soy broth (TSB) for each experiment, unless otherwise indicated. As indicated, antibiotics were included in agar plates and broth cultures at the following concentrations: 5 µg/ml or 10 µg/ml chloramphenicol (Cm), 2 µg/ml or 10 µg/ml erythromycin (Erm). <italic>E. coli</italic> was routinely grown under aerobic conditions (1∶10 volume to flask ratio, 250 RPM) in Luria-Bertani (LB) broth with 50 µg/ml ampicillin (Amp) or 50 µg/ml kanamycin (Km), as indicated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108868-t001">Table 1</xref>. Glycerol stock cultures of all strains were maintained at −80°C and were prepared by mixing equal volume of overnight culture with sterile 50% (vol/vol) glycerol in cryogenic tubes.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0108868-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Bacterial strains and plasmid constructs used in this study.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108868-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain or plasmid name</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reference or source</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DH5α</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host strain for construction of recombinant plasmids</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Hanahan1">[68]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RN4220</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Easily transformable restriction deficient strain</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Kreiswirth1">[69]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UAMS-1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Osteomyelitis clinical isolate</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gillaspy1">[70]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KR1010</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UAMS-1 <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> insertion mutant</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KR1013</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UAMS-1 Δ<italic>pdt</italic> deletion mutant</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Plasmids</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pTR27</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> allele-replacement plasmid; Erm<sup>R</sup>/Cm<sup>R</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pKR13</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<italic>pdt</italic> allele-replacement plasmid; Cm<sup>R</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMKnos</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nos</italic> complementation plasmid; Cm<sup>R</sup>/Amp<sup>R</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMKpdt</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pdt</italic> complementation plasmid; Cm<sup>R</sup>/Amp<sup>R</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This work</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCRBlunt</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> cloning plasmid; Km<sup>R</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Invitrogen</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCR2.1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> cloning plasmid; Km<sup>R</sup>/Amp<sup>R</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Invitrogen</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pBSK</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. coli</italic> cloning plasmid; Amp<sup>R</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stratagene</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pBT2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature-sensitive shuttle vector; Cm<sup>R</sup>/Amp<sup>R</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Bruckner1">[25]</xref></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pMK4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shuttle vector; Cm<sup>R</sup>/Amp<sup>R</sup></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Sullivan1">[29]</xref></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Creation of <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> and Δ<italic>pdt</italic> mutant strains</title>
<p>To create a <italic>nos</italic><bold>::</bold><italic>erm</italic> insertion mutant, plasmid pTR27 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108868-t001">Table 1</xref>) was created as follows: The <italic>nos</italic> gene was amplified from <italic>S. aureus</italic> genomic DNA by PCR using the nos1-F and nos1-R primers specified in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108868-t002">Table 2</xref>, followed by Topo-cloning into pCR2.1 (Invitrogen). An internal <bold>BglII</bold> site was introduced into this cloned sequence 232 bp downstream from the saNOS start codon in the sequence 5'-gttaaatgtcattgatgcaagAGATGTtactgacgaagcatcgttcttatc-3', where the capital letters are located, changing the sequence from AGATGT to AGATCT, a <bold>BglII</bold> restriction enzyme cut site. An <italic>Eco</italic>RI fragment harboring this modified allele was moved into the <bold>Eco</bold>RI site of pBluescript SK (pBSK), a vector backbone that does not contain a <bold>Bgl</bold>II site. A 1.1 kb <bold>Bam</bold>HI-digested fragment harboring the <bold><italic>erm</italic></bold> resistance cassette from Tn1545 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Clewell1">[24]</xref> was then cloned into the <bold>Bgl</bold>II site of the <italic>nos</italic> fragment cloned in pBSK. The resulting <italic>nos</italic><bold>::</bold><italic>erm</italic> allele was subsequently ligated into the <bold>Eco</bold>RI site of the temperature sensitive shuttle vector pBT2 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Bruckner1">[25]</xref> to generate pTR27, which was first transformed into strain RN4220 by electroporation, followed by phage transduction into UAMS-1, with growth at 30°C for all steps <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Groicher1">[26]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Schenk1">[28]</xref>. To create strain KR1010 (UAMS-1 <italic>nos</italic><bold>::</bold><italic>erm</italic> mutant), integration of pTR27 into the <italic>nos</italic> gene on the UAMS-1 chromosome was initiated by growth at 43°C on TSA +10 µg/ml Erm (non-permissive temperature for plasmid replication), to promote integration of the plasmid into the chromosome via homologous recombination at the <italic>nos</italic> gene. To induce a second recombination event, a single isolated colony was used to inoculate TSB (no antibiotic) and grown at 30°C for 5 days. Every 24 hours, an aliquot of the culture was diluted 1000-fold into fresh TSB (no antibiotic). On days 3–5, the culture was serially-diluted and spread on TSA +10 µg/ml Erm, and isolated colonies were then screened for Erm-resistant and Cm-sensitive phenotypes by picking and patching onto TSA +2 µg/ml Erm and TSA +5 µg/ml Cm. PCR using the nos1-F and nos1-R primer pair, as well as Southern blotting, were used to screen candidate mutants to confirm that the chromosomal <italic>nos</italic> gene had been correctly replaced by the <italic>nos</italic><bold>::</bold><italic>erm</italic> allele.</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0108868-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>PCR primers used in this study.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0108868-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Primer</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Purpose</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence (5′-3′; lower case letters represent addition of restriction site)</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nos1-F nos1-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant creation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">GTTAGTTACCAAAGCATAATTGCG ATCTGCCACAATGTTGATTGTTCC</named-content></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nos2-F nos2-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nos</italic> complement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cccggatccGTTTCTATTAATTGCGCTTGA cccgaattcTGCTATACCTCTACTAACTTAATGAT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nos3-F nos3-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>nos</italic> promoter</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cccggatccTGTTTCTATTAATTGCGCTTGAA ccccccgggGCTTTATATTATAGTCTAC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nos4-F nos4-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">real-time PCR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">TATGGTGCTAAAATGGCTTG ACGATGCTTCGTCAGTAACA</named-content></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nos5-F pdt5-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">co-transcription PCR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ccccatatgTTATTTAAAGAGGCTCAAGCTTTC cccctcgagATTAAAAGCACCAATCA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pdt1-F pdt1-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Δpdt</italic> mutant creation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">TTTAAAGAGGCTCAAGCTTTCA CAACACCAATCGATGTGTCA</named-content></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pdt2-F pdt2-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Δpdt</italic> mutant creation</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">CAATTAGGTATGTATCGATTTTTCG</named-content> ccctctagaAAACAAAAGTTAGACGAGCTTGG</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pdt3-F pdt3-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>pdt</italic> complement</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ccccccgggCATCATTAAGTTAGTAGAGGTATAGCA cccgaattcACGAGTGGTAACGAAACGTA</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pdt4-F pdt4-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">real-time PCR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">TGGGTTGTTAGCAAGTGTGC GCCTGAACGAAAAATCGATAC</named-content></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sigA-F sigA-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">real-time PCR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">CAAGCAATCACTCGTGCAAT GGTGCTGGATCTCGACCTAA</named-content></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">asp23-F asp23-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">real-time PCR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">ATTGCTGGTATCGCTGCAC TTGTTGCCACTTGAGAATGC</named-content></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">purH-F purH-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">real-time PCR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">CGAAATAAACCGCAGCATTT TCGTCACATCAGGGTTAGCA</named-content></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">crtN-F crtN-R</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">real-time PCR</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><named-content content-type="gene" xlink:type="simple">CAGTGATTGGTGCAGGTGTC CATACGCCCGCCTACATTAT</named-content></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap>
<p>To create a Δ<italic>pdt</italic> deletion mutant, plasmid pKR13 (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108868-t001">Table 1</xref>) was created as follows: PCR was performed with primer pairs pdt1-F/pdt1-R (amplifying the 1.2-kb region upstream of nucleotide 151 of the <italic>pdt</italic> open reading frame), and pdt2-F/pdt2-R (amplifying the 1.0-kb region downstream of nucleotide 672 of the <italic>pdt</italic> ORF) using AccuPrime™ Pfx SuperMix (Invitrogen Life Technologies) and UAMS-1 genomic DNA as template. Each PCR product was cloned into pCRBlunt (Invitrogen Life Technologies) following the manufacturer's protocols for ligation and <italic>E. coli</italic> transformation, followed by Sanger DNA sequencing (ICBR, University of Florida) to verify that no mutations had been introduced. The pdt1 and pdt2 inserts were each excised from pCRBlunt by restriction digestion with HindIII-ClaI and ClaI-XbaI, respectively, followed by gel-purification of each insert (DNA Gel Extraction Kit, Zymo Research). Plasmid pBT2 was digested with HindIII-XbaI, and a “triple” ligation reaction using T4 DNA ligase (New England Biolabs) containing this linearized plasmid, HindIII-ClaI pdt1 and ClaI-XbaI pdt2 was incubated for several hours at room temperature, followed by heat-shock transformation into <italic>E. coli</italic> DH5α. The resulting pKR13 was moved into <italic>S. aureus</italic> RN4220 and UAMS-1 by electroporation and phage transduction, respectively, as described above. Creation of strain KR1013 (UAMS-1 Δ<italic>pdt</italic> mutant) was performed as described above, except that isolated colonies recovered after induction of the second recombination event were screened for chloramphenicol sensitivity by picking and patching onto TSA (no antibiotic) and TSA +5 µg/ml Cm. PCR with primers nos2-F and pdt2-R was used to screen candidate mutants to confirm that 521-bp of the <italic>pdt</italic> gene had been deleted.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Creation of complementation plasmids</title>
<p>To create pMKnos, primer pair nos2-F/nos2-R and Thermalace enzyme (Invitrogen Life Sciences) was used to PCR-amplify a 1.6 kb product (spanning 564 nucleotides upstream of the <italic>nos</italic> ATG start codon through the entire <italic>nos</italic> ORF), using UAMS-1 genomic DNA as template. This PCR product was cloned into pCRBlunt (Invitrogen Life Technologies) according to the manufacturer's protocols for ligation and <italic>E. coli</italic> transformation, followed by Sanger DNA sequencing to verify that no mutations had been introduced. This DNA fragment was excised from pCRBlunt by restriction digestion with BamHI and EcoRI, gel-purified, and ligated to BamHI-EcoRI digested pMK4 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Sullivan1">[29]</xref>. This ligation was transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic>, followed by movement into <italic>S. aureus</italic> RN4220 and KR1010 by electroporation and phage transduction, respectively, as described above. To create pMKpdt, primer pair nos3-F/nos3-R was used to PCR-amplify a product spanning 564 nucleotides upstream of the <italic>nos</italic> ATG start codon, and primer pair pdt3-F/pdt3-R was used to amplify a 0.97 kb product spanning the <italic>pdt</italic> ORF. Each PCR product was cloned into pCRBlunt (Invitrogen Life Technologies) following the manufacturer's protocols for ligation and <italic>E. coli</italic> transformation, followed by Sanger DNA sequencing. The <italic>nos</italic> promoter fragment was excised from pCRBlunt by restriction digestion with BamHI and SmaI, gel-purified, and ligated to BamHI-SmaI digested pMK4 and transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic>. The resulting plasmid was then digested with SmaI and EcoRI, and ligated to the 0.97-kb <italic>pdt</italic> insert that was excised from pCRBlunt by digestion with these same two enzymes. This ligation was then transformed into <italic>E. coli</italic>, followed by movement into <italic>S. aureus</italic> RN4220, KR1010, and KR1013 by electroporation and phage transduction, respectively, as described above. <italic>S. aureus</italic> UAMS-1, KR1010, and KR1013 were also transduced with pMK4 to create vector-only control strains.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Growth experiments and RNA isolation</title>
<p>To measure growth-phase dependent expression of <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic>, overnight cultures of UAMS-1 were diluted to an OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.05 in TSB, and were grown in both aerobic and low-oxygen conditions as described above (n = 3 biological replicates). Culture samples were harvested from each flask at 2, 6, and 12 hours growth. To compare <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> expression between UAMS-1 (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant (pMK4) and <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> complement (pMKnos) strains, cultures of each (n = 3 biological replicates) were grown for 6 hours under low-oxygen conditions. To compare expression of <italic>nos</italic>, <italic>pdt</italic>, and various carotenoid pigment-related genes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108868-t002">Table 2</xref>) between UAMS-1 (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic> complement (<italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant containing pMKnos) and <italic>pdt</italic> complement (<italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant containing pMKpdt) strains, cultures of each (n = 3 biological replicates) were grown for 28 hours on TSA +5 µg/ml Cm. For all experiments, RNA was isolated with the FASTPREP system (Lysing Matrix B, Q-Biogene, Inc.) and Qiagen RNeasy mini kit, using previously-published methods <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Patton1">[30]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) analysis of gene expression</title>
<p>To remove residual genomic contamination, isolated RNA was treated with Turbo DNase using the TURBO DNA-<italic>free</italic>™ kit (Applied Biosystems). A mock qRT-PCR was then performed with primer pair sigA-F/sigA-R and DNAse-treated RNA as template to check for amplification of contaminating genomic DNA. Each RNA sample (0.750 µg) was then converted to cDNA using the iScript Reverse Transcriptase kit (BioRad), which generates total cDNA using a mixture of oligo(dT) and random hexamer primers. Expression of genes of interest (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0108868-t002">Table 2</xref>) was measured in the cDNA from each sample by qRT-PCR using iQ SYBR green supermix (BioRad) and the Eco Real-Time PCR system (Illumina). The Livak method (2<sup>-ΔΔCt</sup>) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Livak1">[31]</xref> was used to calculate the relative fold change between the calibrator (indicated in each figure legend) and test samples. Primers specific to the housekeeping gene sigA (sigA-F/sigA-R) were used to normalize the data. The amplification efficiency of sigA-F/sigA-R was within 5% of all of the other primer pairs used in qRT-PCR. All qRT-PCR reactions were performed on triplicate technical replicates of each RNA isolated from n = 3 biological samples.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Co-transcription PCR</title>
<p>To determine whether the <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> genes are co-transcribed, 0.750 µg of UAMS-1 RNA isolated from 6 hour low-oxygen cultures (n = 3 biological replicates) was converted to cDNA using the iScript select cDNA kit (BioRad) and primer pdt5-R, which anneals to the stop codon region of the <italic>pdt</italic> gene. As a control, these reactions were also performed in the absence of reverse-transcriptase (RT) enzyme, to check for genomic DNA contamination. PCR reactions (30 cycles) were then performed on 0.075 µg of each RT+ and RT- cDNA sample, as well as a UAMS-1 genomic DNA template control and no template control. Primer pair nos5-F/pdt5-R was used to amplify a 1.9-kb product that spans the region between the <italic>nos</italic> start codon and <italic>pdt</italic> stop codon. PCR products were visualized by agarose gel electrophoresis and ethidium bromide staining, and imaged on a Molecular Imager Gel Doc XR+ (BioRad).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Carotenoid pigment assays</title>
<p>The pigment differences in UAMS-1 (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic><bold>::</bold><italic>erm</italic> mutant (pMK4), <bold><italic>nos</italic></bold> complement (<italic>nos</italic><bold>::</bold><italic>erm</italic> mutant containing pMKnos), and <bold><italic>pdt</italic></bold> complement (<italic>nos</italic><bold>::</bold><italic>erm</italic> mutant containing pMKpdt) strains were quantitatively assessed using a modified method from Morikawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Morikawa1">[32]</xref>. In brief, each strain was grown at 37°C on TSA +5 µg/ml Cm. After 48 hours growth, cells were scraped from each plate, suspended in 1 ml dH<sub>2</sub>O, and centrifuged for 3 minutes at 13,000 RPM. The supernatants were removed and cells were washed and centrifuged a second time as described above. Cell pellets were then resuspended in 420 µl methanol, vortexed for 10 seconds, and 20 µl was withdrawn to measure the OD<sub>600</sub> of each suspension. The remaining 400 µl was incubated at 55°C for 5 minutes, and then centrifuged at 13,000 RPM for 2 minutes. Finally, 350 µl supernatant (containing extracted pigments) was withdrawn from each tube, transferred to a cuvette containing 650 µl methanol, and the absorbance of each sample at 465 nm. All samples were standardized by dividing the A<sub>465</sub> reading by the sample's corresponding relative OD<sub>600</sub> value [calculated by dividing the OD<sub>600</sub> of each sample by the average OD<sub>600</sub> of UAMS-1 (pMK4)], to account for slight variations in the amount of cells harvested from the agar plates. This experiment was performed on n = 3 independent experiments per strain.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2h">
<title>Assessment of phenylalanine biosynthesis</title>
<p>To determine if saPDT is required for phenylalanine biosynthesis, UAMS-1 (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant (pMK4), Δ<italic>pdt</italic> mutant (pMK4), and corresponding complement strains were grown in chemically-defined media (CDM) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Lincoln1">[33]</xref> in the presence and absence of phenylalanine. In brief, each strain was cultured overnight in TSB containing 5 µg/ml Cm, followed by centrifugation to harvest cells. Cell pellets were each washed once in CDM lacking phenylalanine, then resuspended in the same media. These washed cell suspensions were then used to inoculate 1 ml of CDM with phenylalanine or CDM lacking phenylalanine to an OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.02. Aliquots (200 µl) of each diluted culture were transferred in triplicate to wells of a 96-well tissue culture plate (Costar 3596), and grown at 37°C. OD<sub>600</sub> readings were measured in a Synergy HT microplate reader (Biotek) every 2 hours over a 24 hour growth period. This experiment was performed on n = 4 biological replicates (acquired in 2 independent experiments) per strain.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2i">
<title>Fluorescent detection of endogenous NO/RNS</title>
<p>To detect intracellular accumulation of NO and RNS in <italic>S. aureus</italic>, a fluorescent assay using the cell-permeable stain 4-Amino-5-Methylamino-2',7'-Difluorofluorescein (DAF-FM) Diacetate (Invitrogen Life Technologies) was developed. To validate the use of this stain as a measure of intracellular NO/RNS in <italic>S. aureus</italic>, strain UAMS-1 was grown overnight in TSB supplemented with 3% (wt/vol) NaCl and 0.5% (wt/vol) glucose (TSB-NaGlc). Overnight cultures were then diluted to an OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.05 in TSB-NaGlc, and 1 ml aliquots were transferred to wells of a 24-well tissue culture plate (Costar 3524; previously coated overnight at 4°C with 20% human plasma) and grown for 7 hours at 37°C. Following growth, the total well (biofilm + supernatant) was harvested, centrifuged and cell pellets were resuspended in 1× Hank's Buffered Salt Solution (HBSS) buffer containing 5 µM DAF-FM diacetate. Cell suspensions were incubated for 1 hour at 37°C, then cells were collected by centrifugation, washed once in HBSS buffer, and resuspended in HBSS alone (“untreated”) or HBSS supplemented with 100 µM Diethylamine (DEA; Sigma) or 100 µM DEA/NO (Cayman Chemicals). Aliquots (200 µl) of each untreated or treated cell suspension were immediately transferred in triplicate to wells of a Costar 3904 96-well plate, which was incubated at 37°C in a Biotek Synergy HT fluorescent plate reader. Fluorescence (EX/EM 485±10/516±10) and OD<sub>600</sub> measurements were recorded after 30 minutes, and data were reported as relative fluorescent units (RFU) per OD<sub>600</sub> of each well. Where indicated, 2-(4-carboxyphenyl)-4,5-dihydro-4,4,5,5-tetramethyl-1H-imidazolyl-1-oxy-3-oxide, monopotassium salt (cPTIO), an NO scavenger, was added to cell suspensions to a concentration of 150 µM during the 1 hour DAF-FM staining step.</p>
<p>To determine the relative levels of endogenous NO/RNS of <italic>S. aureus</italic> when grown on TSA plates, UAMS-1 (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic> complement (<italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant containing pMKnos) and <italic>pdt</italic> complement (<italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant containing pMKpdt) strains were cultured for 26 hours on TSA +5 µg/ml Cm. Cells were harvested from each plate by scraping with a sterile toothpick, and resuspended in 1 ml HBSS. Cell pellets were harvested by centrifugation, washed once in HBSS buffer, and then resuspended in HBSS containing 5 µM DAF-FM. Aliquots (200 µl) of cell suspension were immediately transferred in quadruplicate to wells of a Costar 3904 96-well plate, which was incubated at 37°C in a Synergy HT fluorescent plate reader. Fluorescence and OD<sub>600</sub> measurements were recorded after 90 minutes, and data were reported as RFU per OD<sub>600</sub> of each well.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2j">
<title>Hydrogen peroxide sensitivity assay</title>
<p>The sensitivity of UAMS-1 (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant (pMK4), Δ<italic>pdt</italic> mutant (pMK4), and corresponding complement strains were assessed for sensitivity to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> based on the method reported by Nudler et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov1">[15]</xref>. In brief, each strain was inoculated in LB broth (+ selective antibiotic, as needed), and grown overnight at 37°C and 250 RPM. These cultures were diluted to an OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.05 in 20 ml LB (no antibiotic) in a 250 ml Erlenmeyer flask. After growth for 4.75–5 hours at 37°C and 250 RPM, 1 ml was removed for serial dilution, track plating <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Jett1">[34]</xref> and CFU/ml determination, and the remaining culture was incubated in the presence of 250 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 2 hours. After this 2 hour treatment, 1 ml of culture was removed from each flask for serial dilution and track plating to determine CFU/ml.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2k">
<title>Murine model of sepsis and dissemination</title>
<p>These experiments were conducted as described previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Voyich1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Kolar1">[36]</xref>. Briefly, 6 week old, female CD-1 Swiss mice were purchased from Charles River Laboratories, and housed at the vivarium in the College of Medicine, University of South Florida. Animals were housed in standard metal cages (2 per cage), with <italic>ad libitum</italic> food and water access. For infection purposes, previously-stocked cultures of UAMS-1 and KR1010 were thawed, washed twice in PBS, and diluted in PBS to 1×10<sup>9</sup> CFU/ml. Mice were randomly assorted into two groups (n = 9 mice per strain) and subsequently inoculated by tail vein injection with 100 µl bacterial suspension, giving a final inocula of 1×10<sup>8</sup> CFU/ml. The infection was allowed to proceed for 7 days, or until mice reached a pre-moribund state (used as a measure of mortality). Mice were monitored every 3 hours for the first 24 hours after inoculation, then every 8 hours (up to 72 hours post-inoculation), and twice daily for the remaining infection period. The criteria used for determining the pre-moribund state included development of a hunched posture, labored breathing, decreased activity, immobility, inability to eat or drink, and ruffled fur. Mice were then euthanized with carbon dioxide, and death was verified by the cessation of cardiovascular and respiratory activity. The liver, kidneys, heart, and lungs were collected and stored at −80°C. Any mouse sacrificed before day 7 was recorded for mortality, and their organs were stored for enumerating bacterial burden. Each organ was subsequently homogenized in 3 ml sterile PBS, and the CFU/organ determined via serial dilution and viable count enumeration. This study was performed in strict accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health. The protocol was approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of the University of South Florida (Permit Number: A-4100-01).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2l">
<title>Statistical analyses</title>
<p>All statistical analyses used for the <italic>in vivo</italic> data were performed using SAS software (version 9.2, SAS Institute, Cary, NC). The distribution of data was determined in SAS through tests for normality (<italic>SAS proc univariate</italic>) and equality of variance (<italic>SAS proc ttest</italic>). The statistical significance of bacterial recovery from the murine model of sepsis was evaluated using a Mann-Whitney Test. Mortality was measured using a Log Rank and Chi-square test with 1-degree of freedom. For all <italic>in vivo</italic> statistical analyses the significance level was set at α = 0.05. <italic>In vitro</italic> assays were subjected to statistical analysis using Sigmaplot version 12.5 software (Build 12.5.0.38, Systat Software, Inc.). Data were tested for normality and equal variance, then analyzed with a parametric (if normality and/or equal variance tests passed) or non-parametric (if normality and/or equal variance tests failed) one-way ANOVA, followed by an appropriate multiple-comparison test to detect differences between individual groups.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>The <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> genes comprise a co-transcribed operon</title>
<p>Inspection of the <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> genomic region revealed the presence of an ORF located only 19-bp downstream of the <italic>nos</italic> gene. This ORF (SAR2008 of the MRSA252 genome, herein referred to as <italic>pdt</italic>) encodes a predicted prephenate dehydratase (saPDT) enzyme, which catalyzes the formation of phenylpyruvate from prephenate during phenylalanine biosynthesis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Tan1">[23]</xref>. A conserved domain search <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Hunter1">[37]</xref> of the <italic>S. aureus pdt</italic> ORF revealed the presence of signature catalytic (PDT; IPR001086) and regulatory (ACT; IPR002912) domains present in mono-functional PDT enzymes that are common to Gram-positive bacteria <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Tan1">[23]</xref>. A BLAST search <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Altschul1">[38]</xref> using the <italic>S. aureus</italic> MRSA252 nucleotide sequence spanning the <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> ORFs revealed that this organization is present in all sequenced <italic>S. aureus</italic> genomes, as well as all sequenced coagulase-negative staphylococcal genomes currently available in the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) genome database (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g001">Fig. 1</xref>). As reported previously <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Sudhamsu1">[3]</xref> and verified by our own BLAST search of all sequenced microbial genomes in the NCBI database, numerous other bacterial genomes contain a gene encoding a predicted NO-synthase that is highly homologous to the <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> ORF (&gt;50% amino acid identity). However, inspection of the genomic context of <italic>nos</italic> in these other bacteria revealed that the putative <italic>nos-pdt</italic> operon structure appears to be unique to the staphylococci (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g001">Fig. 1</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0108868-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Genetic arrangement of the <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> genes.</title>
<p>The representative bacterial genera and/or species that contain a <italic>nos</italic> gene are listed below the <italic>S. aureus nos-pdt</italic> operon diagram. The “+” designation under <italic>nos</italic> indicates its presence in each respective genome, whereas the “+/−” designation under <italic>pdt</italic> indicates if this gene is located immediately downstream of <italic>nos</italic> in each respective bacterial genera/species. The predicted molecular weight (kDa) of the <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> ORFs are indicated above each gene, and the size (bp) of each gene is shown below. Gene designations refer to the MRSA252 genome. The site where the <italic>erm</italic> resistance cassette was inserted to create the <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant (KR1010) is indicated by the black block arrow. *denotes that all sequenced strains in NCBI contain the indicated genes.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To gain insight into the growth conditions under which <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> are expressed, quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) was performed on RNA isolated from aerobic and low-oxygen cultures at early-exponential (2 hours growth), late exponential (6 hours growth) and stationary (12 hours growth) growth phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). The expression patterns of <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> were similar, in that RNA levels of each gene were greatly increased under low-oxygen growth compared to aerobic growth. Furthermore, expression of both of these genes was growth-phase dependent, peaking at late exponential growth phase, and declining in stationary phase. Co-transcription of <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> was verified by synthesizing cDNA from UAMS-1 RNA using a primer that anneals to the 3' end of the <italic>pdt</italic> gene, followed by PCR using primers designed to amplify a 1.9 kb product that spans the start codon of <italic>nos</italic> and stop codon of <italic>pdt</italic>. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g003">Fig. 3A</xref>, a distinct 1.9 kb PCR product was amplified using cDNA as template, confirming that <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> are indeed co-transcribed. This amplification only occurred when reverse-transcriptase (RT) enzyme was present in the cDNA synthesis reaction, indicating that this product was not amplified from contaminating genomic DNA. Because the <italic>nos</italic> mutant used in this study was created by inserting an erythromycin resistance gene cassette into the <italic>nos</italic> coding sequence, the effect on <italic>pdt</italic> transcription in this mutant was also assessed using quantitative real-time PCR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). Comparison of <italic>pdt</italic> expression in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant by this method revealed that <italic>pdt</italic> RNA levels were about 3-fold less than the wild-type strain in low-oxygen 6 hour cultures, and <italic>pdt</italic> expression was not restored when the <italic>nos</italic> mutant was complemented with <italic>nos</italic> expression from a plasmid. These results collectively demonstrate that the <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> genes represent a co-transcribed operon, and that the insertion mutagenesis used to create the <italic>nos</italic> mutant has a partial polar effect on <italic>pdt</italic> expression when cultured in TSB.</p>
<fig id="pone-0108868-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Growth-phase dependent <italic>nos</italic> (A) and <italic>pdt</italic> (B) expression.</title>
<p>Total RNA was isolated at the indicated time points from n = 3 biological replicates of UAMS-1 grown under highly aerated (light grey bars; 250 RPM, 1∶10 volume-to-flask ratio) or low-oxygen (dark grey bars; 0 RPM, 7∶10 volume-to-flask ratio) conditions. Quantitative real-time PCR was performed on reverse-transcribed cDNA from each sample using <italic>nos</italic> (A) or <italic>pdt</italic> (B) specific primers. The Livak (2<sup>-ΔΔCt</sup>) method was used to determine relative fold change of <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> expression, using measured <italic>sigA</italic> expression as the reference gene and the 2 hour aerobic sample as the calibrator. Error bars  =  standard error of the mean (SEM). *denotes statistical significance between aerobic and low-oxygen fold-change values at each indicated time point (Two-Tailed T-Test, p&lt;0.01); •denotes statistical significance relative to t = 2 hour low-oxygen time point (Dunnett's Test, p&lt;0.05).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0108868-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Co-transcription of <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> genes.</title>
<p><bold>A:</bold> 0.750 µg of UAMS-1 RNA isolated from 6-hour low-oxygen cultures was converted to cDNA using the iScript select cDNA kit (BioRad) and primer pdt5-R. As a control, these reactions were also performed in the absence of reverse-transcriptase (RT) enzyme, to check for genomic DNA contamination of the RNA. Equal amounts of RT+ and RT- cDNA samples, as well as UAMS-1 genomic DNA and no template control, were used as templates in a PCR reaction containing the primer pair nos5-F/pdt5-R, which amplifies a product spanning the region between the <italic>nos</italic> start codon and <italic>pdt</italic> stop codon. Data are representative of results obtained from RNA isolated from n = 3 biological replicates. <bold>B:</bold> Total RNA was isolated from n = 3 biological replicates each of UAMS-1 (pMK4; wild-type), KR1010 (pMK4; <italic>nos</italic> mutant), and KR1010 (pMKnos; <italic>nos</italic> complement) grown at 37°C for 6 hours under low-oxygen (0 RPM, 7∶10 volume-to-flask ratio) conditions. Quantitative real-time PCR was performed on reverse-transcribed cDNA from each sample using <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic>-specific primers. The Livak (2<sup>-ΔΔCt</sup>) method was used to determine relative fold change of expression of each gene, using measured <italic>sigA</italic> expression as the reference gene and the 2 hour aerobic sample as the calibrator. Error bars  =  SEM. *denotes statistical significance of <italic>nos</italic> expression relative UAMS-1 (Student-Newman-Keuls Test, p&lt;0.05); •denotes statistical significance of <italic>pdt</italic> expression relative UAMS-1 (Student-Newman-Keuls Test, p&lt;0.05).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title><italic>S. aureus</italic> PDT is required for growth in the absence of phenylalanine but does not affect oxidative stress resistance and carotenoid pigmentation</title>
<p>The crystal structure of saPDT has been previously solved and the predicted enzymatic function of this enzyme (conversion of phenylpyruvate to prephenate) has been confirmed <italic>in vitro</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Tan1">[23]</xref>. However, the operon structure of <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> suggest that the functions of each encoded enzyme may be inter-related. Therefore, the ability of wild-type, <italic>nos</italic> mutant, <italic>pdt</italic> mutant, and corresponding complement strains to grow in the presence and absence of phenylalanine was compared using a chemically-defined media (CDM; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g004">Fig. 4</xref>). In complete CDM (containing phenylalanine), all wild-type, mutant, and complement strains displayed similar growth patterns over a 24-hour period, and each achieved a similar OD<sub>600</sub> after 24 hours growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g004">Fig. 4A</xref>). However, in CDM lacking phenylalanine, the <italic>pdt</italic> mutant displayed greatly reduced growth relative to the wild-type strain, and reached an OD<sub>600</sub> that was 83% less than the wild-type strain after 24 hours (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g004">Fig. 4B</xref>). This growth defect was fully complemented by expressing the <italic>pdt</italic> gene in trans on a plasmid in the <italic>pdt</italic> mutant strain, confirming a requirement for this enzyme in <italic>S. aureus</italic> phenylalanine biosynthesis. The pattern of <italic>nos</italic> mutant growth was nearly identical to the wild-type strain in the absence of phenylalanine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g004">Fig. 4C</xref>), even though this mutation had a partial polar effect on <italic>pdt</italic> expression when grown in TSB (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>). Data retrieved from a previously-published RNA-seq experiment performed on <italic>S. aureus</italic> strain USA300 HOU <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Weiss1">[39]</xref> suggests that there may be other potential promoter sites within the <italic>nos</italic>-<italic>pdt</italic> operon capable of driving <italic>pdt</italic> expression (Fig. S1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108868.s001">File S1</xref>). At least two of these regions are located downstream of the inserted <italic>erm</italic> cassette in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant, and may represent a potential reason why growth in the absence of phenylalanine was not impaired in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant. Overall these results suggest that (1) saNOS is not required for growth in the absence of phenylalanine, and (2) there is adequate expression of <italic>pdt</italic> in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant to support phenylalanine biosynthesis when grown in chemically-defined media.</p>
<fig id="pone-0108868-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Effects of <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> on growth in chemically-defined media.</title>
<p>UAMS-1 (pMK4; wild-type), KR1010 (pMK4; <italic>nos</italic> mutant), KR1010 (pMKnos; <italic>nos</italic> complement), KR1013 (pMK4; <italic>pdt</italic> mutant), and KR1013 (pMKpdt; <italic>pdt</italic> complement) were grown in chemically-defined media in the presence (A) or absence (B and C) of phenylalanine. Cultures were inoculated to an OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.02, and grown statically in a 96-well plate for 24 hours at 37°C. OD<sub>600</sub> readings were measured every 2 hours using a microplate reader. Data represents the average of n = 4 biological replicates acquired in 2 independent experiments. Error bars  =  SEM. *statistical significance of <italic>pdt</italic> mutant (pMK4) OD<sub>600</sub> compared to UAMS-1 (pMK4) at t = 24 hours growth (p&lt;0.05, Tukey Test).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>A role for saNOS in resistance to oxidative stress has been established <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov2">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Vaish1">[20]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>, but a similar role for saPDT has not been previously explored. Given that <italic>nos</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Chang1">[40]</xref> and <italic>pdt</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Chang1">[40]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-PalazzoloBallance1">[41]</xref> expression were shown by others to be induced in response to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, it is possible that saPDT may also contribute to oxidative stress resistance, possibly by generating the α-keto acid anion phenylpyruvate that has been proposed to act as an antioxidant by direct chemical interaction with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Perera1">[42]</xref>. To explore this possibility, wild-type, <italic>nos</italic> mutant, <italic>pdt</italic> mutant, and corresponding complement cultures were grown to late-exponential phase, and challenged with 250 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g005">Fig. 5</xref>). As expected, the <italic>nos</italic> mutant displayed a significant (&gt;3-log) reduction in cell viability after H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> challenge compared to the wild-type strain, and this phenotype was fully-restored by supplying the <italic>nos</italic> gene on a plasmid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g005">Fig. 5A</xref>). However, the sensitivity of the <italic>pdt</italic> mutant to oxidative stress was unaffected in this assay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g005">Fig. 5B</xref>), suggesting that, at least in this <italic>in vitro</italic> growth condition, saPDT does not appear to function in an antioxidant capacity.</p>
<fig id="pone-0108868-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Effect of <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> on oxidative stress resistance.</title>
<p><bold>A:</bold> UAMS-1 (pMK4; wild-type), KR1010 (pMK4; <italic>nos</italic> mutant) and KR1010 (pMKnos; <italic>nos</italic> complement) were cultured aerobically for 4.75–5 hours (mid-exponential growth phase) in LB media (“pre-treatment” time point, light grey bars) prior to addition of 250 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Cultures were then grown for 2 more hours to assess the effect of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment cell viability by CFU plating (“post-treatment” time point, dark grey bars). <bold>B:</bold> UAMS-1 (pMK4; wild-type), KR1013 (pMK4; <italic>pdt</italic> mutant), and KR1013 (pMKpdt; <italic>pdt</italic> complement) were analyzed for resistance to 250 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> as described in panel A. All data represent the average of n = 5 independent experiments. Error bars  =  SEM. *statistical significance compared to UAMS-1 (pMK4) (p&lt;0.05, Student-Newman-Keuls Test).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>During routine culturing of the wild-type, <italic>nos</italic> mutant, <italic>pdt</italic> mutant, and complement strains used in these studies, the <italic>nos</italic> mutant consistently appeared to display increased carotenoid (golden-yellow) pigmentation when cultured on TSA agar plates. This observation was verified by measuring the A<sub>465 nm</sub> of methanol-extracted carotenoid pigments from 48-hour TSA plate cultures of wild-type, <italic>nos</italic> mutant, and complement strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>). Consistent with qualitative observations, the <italic>nos</italic> mutant displayed a statistically-significant (p&lt;0.05, Student-Newman-Keuls Test) increase in pigmentation compared to the wild-type strain. Furthermore, pigment was restored to wild-type levels by complementation with a <italic>nos</italic>-expressing plasmid but not with a <italic>pdt</italic>-expressing plasmid, verifying that increased pigmentation of the <italic>nos</italic> mutant is solely due to loss of saNOS function. To determine if increased pigmentation in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant was a result of altered expression of pigment-related genes, qPCR was employed to measure changes in expression of <italic>crtN</italic> (a member of the carotenoid biosynthesis operon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Wieland1">[43]</xref>), <italic>asp23</italic> (alkaline shock protein 23, highly-regulated by alternative sigma factor B <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gertz1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Giachino1">[45]</xref>), and <italic>purH</italic> (purine biosynthesis gene H), as mutation in these genes and/or regulatory circuits have each been shown to greatly alter pigment production <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Wieland1">[43]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Giachino1">[45]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Lan1">[46]</xref>. Surprisingly, <italic>asp23</italic>, <italic>crtN</italic>, and <italic>purH</italic> RNA levels were not significantly different between wild-type, <italic>nos</italic> mutant, and <italic>nos</italic> complement strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>), suggesting that increased pigmentation of the <italic>nos</italic> mutant is not due to altered expression of these genes.</p>
<fig id="pone-0108868-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Effect of <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> mutation on carotenoid pigmentation.</title>
<p><bold>A:</bold> UAMS-1 (pMK4; wild-type), KR1010 (pMK4; <italic>nos</italic> mutant), KR1010 (pMKnos; <italic>nos</italic> complement), and KR1010 (pMKpdt; <italic>nos</italic> mutant containing <italic>pdt</italic> complement plasmid) were grown for 48 hours at 37°C on TSA plates. Pigments from each culture were extracted with methanol, the A<sub>465 nm</sub> of each sample was measured, and standardized by dividing by the sample's corresponding relative OD<sub>600</sub> value (measured prior to methanol extraction step). Results represent the average of n = 3 independent experiments, error bars  =  SEM. *statistical significance compared to UAMS-1 (pMK4) (p&lt;0.05, Student-Newman-Keuls Test). <bold>B:</bold> Total RNA from 28 hour TSA plate cultures of UAMS-1 (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant (pMK4), <italic>nos</italic> complement and <italic>pdt</italic> complement strains (n = 3 biological replicates each) was reversed-transcribed to cDNA, and subjected to quantitative real-time PCR using primers specific for detecting <italic>nos</italic>, <italic>pdt</italic>, <italic>asp23</italic>, <italic>crtN</italic>, and <italic>purH</italic> expression. The Livak (2<sup>-ΔΔCt</sup>) method was used to determine relative fold change expression of each gene, using measured <italic>sigA</italic> expression as the reference gene and the UAMS-1 (pMK4) sample as the calibrator.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Detection of intracellular NO/RNS in <italic>S. aureus</italic> by DAF-FM diacetate</title>
<p>To detect and compare relative levels of intracellular NO in <italic>S. aureus</italic>, an assay using the cell-permeable fluorescent stain DAF-FM diacetate was developed. This compound diffuses into cells and once inside, is cleaved by intracellular esterases to liberate weakly-fluorescent DAF-FM, which in turn becomes highly fluorescent upon reaction with NO or other specific RNS <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Kojima1">[47]</xref>. To validate the use of this stain as an indirect indicator of intracellular NO levels in <italic>S. aureus</italic>, wild-type biofilms grown for 7 hours were subjected to DAF-FM diacetate staining, followed by treatment with HBSS buffer alone, DEA/NO (a short half-life NO donor), DEA alone, cPTIO (an NO scavenger), and DEA/NO + cPTIO (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g007">Figure 7A</xref>). As expected, treatment with DEA/NO resulted in a marked increase in DAF-FM fluorescence in <italic>S. aureus</italic> cells, whereas treatment with DEA alone did not affect fluorescence relative to the untreated condition. Interestingly, treatment of cells with cPTIO alone decreased intracellular DAF-FM fluorescence relative to untreated cells (buffer alone), suggesting that this NO scavenger was able to reduce the level of endogenous NO detectable by intracellular DAF-FM. Furthermore, when cPTIO-treated cells were subsequently exposed to NO donor, the fluorescent signal did not greatly increase compared to the untreated sample. Collectively, these results validate the use of DAF-FM diacetate as a fluorescent tool to indirectly measure intracellular NO levels in <italic>S. aureus</italic>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0108868-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Detection of intracellular NO/RNS with DAF-FM diacetate.</title>
<p><bold>A:</bold> Cells harvested from replicate UAMS-1 7 hour static biofilms were resuspended in HBSS containing 5 µM DAF-FM diacetate. After incubation for 1 hour at 37°C, cells were collected by centrifugation, washed, and resuspended in HBSS alone (“untreated”) or HBSS supplemented with 100 µM DEA or 100 µM DEA/NO. Where indicated, 150 µM cPTIO (NO scavenger) was added to cell suspensions during the 1 hour DAF-FM diacetate staining step. Aliquots (200 µl) of each cell suspension were immediately transferred to a 96-well plate, and incubated at 37°C in a Synergy HT fluorescent plate reader. Fluorescence and OD<sub>600</sub> measurements were recorded after 30 minutes, and data were reported as relative fluorescent units (RFU) per OD<sub>600</sub> of each well. Data represents the average of n = 3 independent experiments, error bars  =  SEM. *statistical significance compared to untreated UAMS-1 (p&lt;0.05, Tukey Test). <bold>B:</bold> UAMS-1 (pMK4; wild-type), KR1010 (pMK4; <italic>nos</italic> mutant), and KR1010 (pMKnos; <italic>nos</italic> complement) were grown on agar plates for 26 hours, followed by harvesting and resuspension in HBSS +5 µM DAF-FM dicaetate. Fluorescence (RFU) and OD<sub>600</sub> readings were recorded after 90 minutes incubation in a microplate reader as described above. Data represents the average of n = 3 independent experiments, error bars  =  SEM. *statistical significance compared to UAMS-1 (pMK4) (p&lt;0.05, Tukey Test).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>DAF-FM diaceate was initially used to measure relative endogenous NO levels in late-exponential phase low-oxygen TSB cultures of the wild-type, <italic>nos</italic> mutant, and complement strains, as <italic>nos</italic> expression was increased at this phase of low-oxygen growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g002">Fig. 2</xref>). However, no detectable differences in DAF-FM fluorescence were observed (Fig. S2 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0108868.s001">File S1</xref>), suggesting that saNOS activity may be minimal or very transient at this phase of growth. Alternatively, its contribution to endogenous NO in this growth condition may be masked relative to other cellular sources of NO/RNS. Since phenotypic changes in pigmentation were observed when these strains were cultured on TSA plates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>), 28-hour TSA plate cultures of wild-type, <italic>nos</italic> mutant, and complement strains were also assessed for endogenous NO levels by staining with DAF-FM diacetate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g007">Fig. 7B</xref>). Intriguingly, DAF-FM fluorescence was significantly (p&lt;0.05, Tukey test) decreased relative to the wild-type and complement strains, suggesting that saNOS enzyme activity and/or expression is increased in <italic>S. aureus</italic> when cultured on TSA plates. Given that the level of DAF-FM fluorescence only decreased by about 35% in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant, it is likely that other cellular sources of endogenous NO and/or RNS are also present that are able to react with DAF-FM in this assay.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Contribution of saNOS to survival in a murine sepsis model</title>
<p>Although the contribution of saNOS to MRSA virulence has been previously-demonstrated in a murine abscess model of infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>, a role for this enzyme in virulence of MSSA has not been reported. Therefore, the virulence of MSSA strain UAMS-1 and its isogenic <italic>nos</italic> mutant was compared using a previously-published murine sepsis model of infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Voyich1">[35]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Kolar1">[36]</xref>. As demonstrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g008">Figs. 8A–8D</xref>, the bacterial load (as measured by CFU/organ) in the lungs, kidneys, and liver were significantly (p&lt;0.05, Mann-Whitney Test) lower in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant-infected mice compared to wild-type infected mice. Although not a statistically significant difference, bacterial counts from the heart were also decreased in <italic>nos</italic> mutant-infected mice relative to the wild-type infected mice. As well, the <italic>nos</italic> mutant-infected mice displayed significantly (p&lt;0.05, Log Rank and Chi Squared Test with 1-degree of freedom) less mortality than the wild-type infected mice in this model of infection, with 8/9 <italic>nos</italic> mutant-infected mice and 6/9 wild-type-infected mice surviving throughout the 7-day infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g008">Fig. 8E</xref>). Given that a partial polar effect on <italic>pdt</italic> expression was observed in the <italic>nos</italic> mutant when grown in low-oxygen TSB cultures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>), it is possible that the <italic>in vivo</italic> effects of the <italic>nos</italic> mutant observed in this study are due, in part, to partial loss of <italic>pdt</italic> expression. These results, combined with previously-published data showing that a MRSA <italic>nos</italic> deletion mutant displayed decreased virulence in an abscess infection model <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>, suggest that saNOS and/or saPDT contribute to <italic>S. aureus</italic> dissemination and survival <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0108868-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Effect of <italic>nos</italic> on <italic>S. aureus</italic> virulence.</title>
<p>1×10<sup>8</sup> CFU/ml of UAMS-1 (wild-type) and KR1010 (<italic>nos</italic> mutant) cultures were each injected into the tail veins of female CD-1 Swiss mice (n = 9 mice per group). The infection proceeded for 7 days, or until mice reached a pre-moribund state (used as a measure of mortality). Mice were then euthanized and organs were collected and stored at −80°C prior to homogenization and determination of recovered CFU/organ. Graphs represent the calculated bacterial burdens for the kidneys (A), heart (B), lungs (C) and liver (D), and the percent survival (E). For A–D, data are graphed as box-whisker plots, indicating the 25<sup>th</sup>, median, and 75<sup>th</sup> percentiles (box lines), the 90<sup>th</sup> and 10<sup>th</sup> percentiles (error bars), and mean (+) of each data-set. *denotes statistically significant difference of mortality (p&lt;0.05, Log Rank and Chi Squared Test with 1-degree of freedom), **denotes statistical significance of bacterial recovery (p&lt;0.05, Mann-Whitney Test).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>An emerging body of evidence has demonstrated that bacterial NOS enzymes act as important regulators of cellular stress resistance and physiology. For example, NO-derived from the NOS of plant-pathogenic <italic>Streptomyces</italic> species is required for the nitration of thaxtomin phytotoxins, a modification that is essential for its phytotoxicity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Kers1">[12]</xref>. The NOS enzymes of <italic>B. subtilis, B. anthracis</italic>, and <italic>S. aureus</italic> have also been shown to promote resistance to oxidative stress imposed by hydrogen peroxide <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Shatalin1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov1">[15]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref> and by certain antibiotics <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov2">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>. This oxidative stress resistance has been proposed to be mediated by several mechanisms, including transient suppression of the enzymatic reduction of intracellular cysteines by NO (and subsequent inhibition of the Fenton reaction) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Shatalin1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov1">[15]</xref>, NO activation of catalase activity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Shatalin1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov1">[15]</xref>, and NO-induced expression and/or increased activity of superoxide dismutase (SOD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov2">[18]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>. Our current results have corroborated the contribution of saNOS to hydrogen peroxide resistance in the MSSA strain UAMS-1, and furthermore, have also illustrated that carotenoid pigmentation is increased in a <italic>nos</italic> mutant when grown on TSA plates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g006">Fig. 6A</xref>), a phenotype that has not been previously described for <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> mutants. Staphyloxanthin, the major carotenoid pigment synthesized by a series of enzymes encoded by the <italic>crt</italic> operon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Wieland1">[43]</xref>, has been shown to be a potent antioxidant defense against hydrogen peroxide and the immune cell respiratory burst <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Clauditz1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Liu2">[49]</xref>, as well as conferring tolerance to host antimicrobial peptides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Mishra1">[50]</xref> and fatty acids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Chamberlain1">[51]</xref> by altering membrane fluidity. Therefore, at first glance, it appears paradoxical that a <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> mutant would be more sensitive to oxidative stress while displaying increased carotenoid pigmentation. However, the hydrogen peroxide challenge assay utilized in this study was performed during mid-exponential growth phase in planktonic cultures, a growth condition under which differences in staphyloxanthin production is unlikely to be observed, since maximal expression of <italic>crtM</italic> has been shown to occur in stationary phase in planktonic culture <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Lan1">[46]</xref>. Although loss of saNOS does not appear to alter expression of the <italic>crt</italic> operon and regulators of <italic>crt</italic> expression when grown on TSA plates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g006">Fig. 6B</xref>), it is possible that NO derived from saNOS may regulate the activity of one or more of the enzymes involved in the synthesis of staphyloxanthin or one of its precursors. Another possibility stems from the fact that the degree of conjugation (increased number of double bonds) in carotenoids tends to correlate to the observed intensity of orange-yellow pigmentation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Walter1">[52]</xref>. Since NO is known to have an affinity for biological membranes <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Griffith1">[53]</xref> and can attack the double bonds of β-carotene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gabr1">[54]</xref>, it is possible that increased pigmentation observed in the <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> mutant is simply a result of loss of NO accumulation in the cell membrane.</p>
<p>In these presented studies, we have also optimized the use of DAF-FM diacetate to monitor relative intracellular NO levels in <italic>S. aureus</italic>. Using this technique, a decrease in intracellular NO/RNS was observed in the <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> mutant when cultured on TSA plates, a growth condition where increased pigmentation of the <italic>nos</italic> mutant was also observed. Although DAF-FM can also react with certain RNS such as nitrosonium ions, the majority of the fluorescent signal has been shown by others to be due to NO <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Kojima2">[55]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Kojima3">[56]</xref>. Since the NO radical itself is relatively unstable and may quickly yield other RNS upon exposure to cellular components, intracellular DAF-FM fluorescence should be considered an indirect measurement of NO levels. In previous studies of <italic>S. aureus</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>, <italic>B. anthracis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Shatalin1">[14]</xref>, and <italic>B. subtilis</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Gusarov3">[57]</xref> NOS activity, a NO-specific copper fluorescein (CuFL) stain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Lim1">[58]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Lim2">[59]</xref> was utilized to detect intracellular NO production in wild-type and <italic>nos</italic> mutants. When used in <italic>S. aureus</italic>, the cells were incubated in a buffer containing arginine prior to CuFL staining <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref> and it was not specified in this study whether excess arginine was necessary to detect NO production. Arginine addition may artificially induce <italic>nos</italic> expression and/or enzyme activity in cells not normally producing <italic>nos</italic>, and may overestimate the actual number of cells that contain high-level saNOS enzyme activity when growing <italic>in vivo</italic>. Furthermore, CuFL specifically interacts with NO to yield high-level fluorescence, but it may be more difficult to detect endogenous NO if it is produced in a short biological window or if it reacts quickly with other cellular targets to yield other RNS. In these cases the use of DAF-FM diacetate may provide a viable alternative method of intracellular fluorescent NO detection.</p>
<p>The protective effects of endogenous NO observed in bacteria <italic>in vitro</italic> likely translate to an important contribution of NOS to the virulence of these Gram-positive pathogens during human infection. For example, a <italic>B. anthracis nos</italic> mutant displayed decreased survival when engulfed by macrophages, and an increased lethal dose (LD<sub>50</sub>) of spores compared to the parental strain in a murine model of systemic infection <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Shatalin1">[14]</xref>. Furthermore, a <italic>nos</italic> mutant generated in a highly virulent community-acquired MRSA (USA300) strain was shown to be more sensitive to killing by neutrophils by both intracellular and extracellular mechanisms, as well as decreased survival in macrophages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>. This MRSA <italic>nos</italic> mutant was also less virulent in a murine subcutaneous model of infection, displaying decreased abscess sizes and decreased recovered CFUs compared to the wild-type strain <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-vanSorge1">[21]</xref>. The UAMS-1 <italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant strain used in our current study was also less virulent than its wild-type counterpart in a murine sepsis model of infection (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g008">Fig. 8</xref>). A partial polar effect on <italic>pdt</italic> expression was observed in this mutant when grown in low-oxygen TSB cultures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g003">Fig. 3B</xref>), therefore it is possible that the <italic>in vivo</italic> effects observed in the sepsis model were due, in part, to partial loss of <italic>pdt</italic> expression. Given the interest in both NOS and PDT as potential drug development targets <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Holden1">[22]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Tan1">[23]</xref>, our future studies will focus on assessing the individual contributions of <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> to <italic>S. aureus</italic> virulence <italic>in vivo</italic> using non-polar deletion mutants.</p>
<p>As discussed above, <italic>S. aureus</italic> NOS clearly contributes to the oxidative stress response and virulence of this deadly pathogen. Considering the interest in this enzyme as a potential drug target, studies aimed at understanding the upstream regulators of both <italic>nos</italic> gene expression and saNOS enzyme activity are surprisingly lacking <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Holden1">[22]</xref>. In the study presented here, we have confirmed that <italic>S. aureus nos</italic> is co-transcribed with the downstream <italic>pdt</italic> gene, encoding a prephenate dehydratase which catalyzes the formation of phenylpyruvate from prephenate in the phenylalanine biosynthesis pathway. Although saNOS contributes to oxidative stress resistance in <italic>S. aureus</italic>, we have demonstrated that expression of <italic>nos-pdt</italic> is upregulated in response to low-oxygen growth and is maximally expressed at late-exponential growth phase. These observations suggest that one or both of these enzymes are required for an as-yet unknown function in the normal physiology of this organism during low-oxygen growth. Although the genetic regulators of <italic>nos-pdt</italic> expression have not yet been identified, a search of the <italic>S. aureus</italic> microarray meta-database (SAMMD) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Nagarajan1">[60]</xref> has revealed that <italic>nos</italic> expression was upregulated in <italic>purH</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Lan1">[46]</xref>, <italic>lytS</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-SharmaKuinkel1">[61]</xref>, and <italic>clpP</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Michel1">[62]</xref> mutants, as well as by challenge with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Chang1">[40]</xref>, and downregulated when challenged with chlorination <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Chang2">[63]</xref>, mupirocin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Reiss1">[64]</xref>, and various antimicrobial peptides <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Pietiainen1">[65]</xref>.</p>
<p>The <italic>S. aureus</italic> PDT enzyme has also been postulated to be a potential drug target since it is involved in phenylalanine synthesis and is highly conserved among the staphylococci <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Tan1">[23]</xref>. As such, the enzymatic activity of purified recombinant <italic>S. aureus</italic> PDT has been demonstrated and the crystal structure of this protein has been solved <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Tan1">[23]</xref>. Although study of this gene in <italic>S. aureus</italic> has not been previously described, the data presented in this manuscript begin to fulfill this knowledge gap by confirming a role for saPDT as being required for growth in the absence of phenylalanine, as well as identifying low-oxygen growth as a signal that stimulates expression of <italic>pdt in vitro</italic>. RNA microarray analysis of <italic>S. aureus</italic> cultures previously revealed that <italic>nos</italic> and <italic>pdt</italic> were upregulated 2.5- and 2.2-fold, respectively, in H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated cultures <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Chang1">[40]</xref>. Given these collective results, we hypothesized that saPDT, like saNOS, may also contribute to oxidative stress resistance, possibly by generating excess phenylpyruvate under these conditions. The α-keto acid anions, such as β-hydroxypyruvate and β-phenylpyruvate, can chemically react with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>, and have been proposed to act as antioxidants by nucleophilic attack of the mono-deprotonated peroxide species at the C-2 carbonyl group carbon center <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Perera1">[42]</xref>. Furthermore, pyruvate, another α-keto acid, is commonly added as an H<sub>2</sub>0<sub>2</sub>-scavenger in certain cell culture media <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Neuman1">[66]</xref>, and exogenous pyruvate is able to protect these cultured cells from H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-induced lysis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-ODonnellTormey1">[67]</xref>. However, our data suggests that saNOS is not required for activity of saPDT when participating in phenylalanine biosynthesis, and saPDT itself does not appear to contribute to hydrogen peroxide resistance under the <italic>in vitro</italic> conditions tested in this study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g004">Figs. 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0108868-g005">5</xref>). Therefore the potential functional and/or biological relationship between these two enzymes remains a mystery and subject of our on-going investigations.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0108868.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0108868.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>File S1</label><caption>
<p>Contains the following files: <bold>Figure S1.</bold> Expression of the <italic>nos-pdt</italic> operon in <italic>S. aureus</italic> USA300 HOU as assessed by RNA-seq analysis. Data depicted in this figure was generated as part of a previously-published RNA-seq study <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0108868-Weiss1">[39]</xref>, whereby RNA from 3 hour TSB cultures of strain USA300 HOU was subjected to Ion Torrent sequencing and resulting reads were aligned to the USA300 FPR genome. Arrows represent potential internal promoters and/or RNA processing sites. <bold>Figure S2.</bold> Detection of intracellular NO/RNS in low-oxygen cultures. UAMS-1 (pMK4), KR1010 (<italic>nos</italic>::<italic>erm</italic> mutant; pMK4), and KR1010 (complement; pMKnos) were grown as low-oxygen TSB cultures for 6.25 hours, followed by harvesting and resuspension in HBSS +5 µM DAF-FM dicaetate as described in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="s2">Materials and Methods</xref>. Fluorescence (RFU) and OD<sub>600</sub> readings were recorded after 90 minutes incubation in a microplate reader. Data represents the average of n = 3 independent experiments, error bars  =  SEM.</p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors gratefully acknowledge Ms. Cydney Godman for technical assistance.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Lancaster1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>JR</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A tutorial on the diffusibility and reactivity of free nitric oxide</article-title>. <source>Nitric Oxide</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Toledo1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Toledo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Augusto</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Connecting the chemical and biological properties of nitric oxide</article-title>. <source>Chem Res Toxicol</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>975</fpage>–<lpage>989</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Sudhamsu1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sudhamsu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Bacterial nitric oxide synthases: what are they good for?</article-title> <source>Trends Microbiol</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>212</fpage>–<lpage>218</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Crane1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sudhamsu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Bacterial nitric oxide synthases</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source> <volume>79</volume>: <fpage>445</fpage>–<lpage>470</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Forstermann1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Forstermann U, Sessa WC (2012) Nitric oxide synthases: regulation and function. Eur Heart J 33: 829–837, 837a–837d.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Crawford1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms for nitric oxide synthesis in plants</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>471</fpage>–<lpage>478</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Alderton1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alderton</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide synthases: structure, function and inhibition</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source> <volume>357</volume>: <fpage>593</fpage>–<lpage>615</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Yun1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Neurobiology of nitric oxide</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Neurobiol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>291</fpage>–<lpage>316</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Lipton1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Lipton SA (2001) Physiology. Nitric oxide and respiration. Nature. England. pp. 118–119, 121.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Malinski1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malinski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Taha</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide release from a single cell measured <italic>in situ</italic> by a porphyrinic-based microsensor</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>358</volume>: <fpage>676</fpage>–<lpage>678</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Wink1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wink</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grisham</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Direct and indirect effects of nitric oxide in chemical reactions relevant to biology</article-title>. <source>Methods Enzymol</source> <volume>268</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>–<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Kers1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kers</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wach</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krasnoff</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Widom</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Nitration of a peptide phytotoxin by bacterial nitric oxide synthase</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>429</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>–<lpage>82</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Wach1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wach</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kers</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krasnoff</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loria</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide synthase inhibitors and nitric oxide donors modulate the biosynthesis of thaxtomin A, a nitrated phytotoxin produced by <italic>Streptomyces</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>Nitric Oxide</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Shatalin1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shatalin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gusarov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Avetissova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shatalina</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McQuade</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title><italic>Bacillus anthracis</italic>-derived nitric oxide is essential for pathogen virulence and survival in macrophages</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>1009</fpage>–<lpage>1013</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Gusarov1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gusarov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nudler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>NO-mediated cytoprotection: instant adaptation to oxidative stress in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>13855</fpage>–<lpage>13860</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Liu1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Heterologous expression of bacterial nitric oxide synthase gene: a potential biological method to control biofilm development in the environment</article-title>. <source>Can J Microbiol</source> <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>336</fpage>–<lpage>344</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Schreiber1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beutler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Enning</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lamprecht-Grandio</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zafra</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The role of nitric-oxide-synthase-derived nitric oxide in multicellular traits of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> 3610: biofilm formation, swarming, and dispersal</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Gusarov2"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gusarov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shatalin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Starodubtseva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nudler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Endogenous nitric oxide protects bacteria against a wide spectrum of antibiotics</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>325</volume>: <fpage>1380</fpage>–<lpage>1384</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Centers1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Centers for Disease Control (2013) Antibiotic Resistance Threats in the United States.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Vaish1"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaish</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Antioxidant Functions of Nitric Oxide Synthase in a Methicillin Sensitive <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Microbiol</source> <volume>2013</volume>: <fpage>312146</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-vanSorge1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Sorge</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beasley</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gusarov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Kockritz-Blickwede</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> bacterial nitric-oxide synthase affects antibiotic sensitivity and skin abscess development</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>288</volume>: <fpage>6417</fpage>–<lpage>6426</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Holden1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Structural and biological studies on bacterial nitric oxide synthase inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> <volume>110</volume>: <fpage>18127</fpage>–<lpage>18131</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Tan1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clancy</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Structures of open (R) and close (T) states of prephenate dehydratase (PDT)–implication of allosteric regulation by L-phenylalanine</article-title>. <source>J Struct Biol</source> <volume>162</volume>: <fpage>94</fpage>–<lpage>107</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Clewell1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clewell</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flannagan</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaworski</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Unconstrained bacterial promiscuity: the Tn916-Tn1545 family of conjugative transposons</article-title>. <source>Trends Microbiol</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>–<lpage>236</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Bruckner1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bruckner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Gene replacement in <italic>Staphylococcus carnosus</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus xylosus</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source> <volume>151</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Groicher1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Groicher</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Firek</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bayles</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Staphylococcus aureus lrgAB</italic> operon modulates murein hydrolase activity and penicillin tolerance</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>182</volume>: <fpage>1794</fpage>–<lpage>1801</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Shafer1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shafer</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iandolo</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Genetics of staphylococcal enterotoxin B in methicillin-resistant isolates of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>902</fpage>–<lpage>911</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Schenk1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laddaga</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Improved method for electroporation of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source> <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>–<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Sullivan1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasbin</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>New shuttle vectors for <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> which allow rapid detection of inserted fragments</article-title>. <source>Gene</source> <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Patton1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bayles</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Staphylococcus aureus cidC</italic> gene encodes a pyruvate oxidase that affects acetate metabolism and cell death in stationary phase</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>1664</fpage>–<lpage>1674</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Livak1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>–<lpage>408</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Morikawa1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inose</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higashide</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Overexpression of sigma factor, sigma(B), urges <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> to thicken the cell wall and to resist beta-lactams</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source> <volume>288</volume>: <fpage>385</fpage>–<lpage>389</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Lincoln1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lincoln</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leigh</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The amino acid requirements of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> isolated from cases of bovine mastitis</article-title>. <source>Vet Microbiol</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>275</fpage>–<lpage>279</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Jett1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jett</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatter</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huycke</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gilmore</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>Simplified agar plate method for quantifying viable bacteria</article-title>. <source>Biotechniques</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>648</fpage>–<lpage>650</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Voyich1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Voyich</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mathema</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braughton</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Is Panton-Valentine leukocidin the major virulence determinant in community-associated methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> disease?</article-title> <source>J Infect Dis</source> <volume>194</volume>: <fpage>1761</fpage>–<lpage>1770</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Kolar1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kolar</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibarra</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rivera</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mootz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Extracellular proteases are key mediators of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> virulence via the global modulation of virulence-determinant stability</article-title>. <source>Microbiologyopen</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Hunter1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Attwood</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>InterPro in 2011: new developments in the family and domain prediction database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source> <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>D306</fpage>–<lpage>312</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Altschul1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>215</volume>: <fpage>403</fpage>–<lpage>410</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Weiss1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ibarra</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paoletti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>The delta subunit of RNA polymerase guides promoter selectivity and virulence in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>1424</fpage>–<lpage>1435</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Chang1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Small</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toghrol</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Global transcriptome analysis of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> response to hydrogen peroxide</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>188</volume>: <fpage>1648</fpage>–<lpage>1659</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-PalazzoloBallance1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Palazzolo-Ballance</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reniere</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braughton</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sturdevant</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Neutrophil microbicides induce a pathogen survival response in community-associated methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> <volume>180</volume>: <fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>509</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Perera1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parkes</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haycock</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>High resolution 1H NMR investigations of the reactivities of alpha-keto acid anions with hydrogen peroxide</article-title>. <source>Free Radic Res</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>–<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Wieland1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gloria-Maercker</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thumm</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lechner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Genetic and biochemical analyses of the biosynthesis of the yellow carotenoid 4,4'-diaponeurosporene of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>176</volume>: <fpage>7719</fpage>–<lpage>7726</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Gertz1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gertz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engelmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohlsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hacker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Regulation of sigmaB-dependent transcription of sigB and asp23 in two different <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source> <volume>261</volume>: <fpage>558</fpage>–<lpage>566</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Giachino1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giachino</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engelmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bischoff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Sigma(B) activity depends on RsbU in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>183</volume>: <fpage>1843</fpage>–<lpage>1852</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Lan1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunman</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Missiakas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Golden pigment production and virulence gene expression are affected by metabolisms in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>192</volume>: <fpage>3068</fpage>–<lpage>3077</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Kojima1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Urano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Fluorescent Indicators for Imaging Nitric Oxide Production</article-title>. <source>Angew Chem Int Ed Engl</source> <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>3209</fpage>–<lpage>3212</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Clauditz1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clauditz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Resch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wieland</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peschel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gotz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Staphyloxanthin plays a role in the fitness of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> and its ability to cope with oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>74</volume>: <fpage>4950</fpage>–<lpage>4953</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Liu2"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Essex</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoffman</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> golden pigment impairs neutrophil killing and promotes virulence through its antioxidant activity</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> <volume>202</volume>: <fpage>209</fpage>–<lpage>215</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Mishra1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>GY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yeaman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nast</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Carotenoid-related alteration of cell membrane fluidity impacts <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> susceptibility to host defense peptides</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>526</fpage>–<lpage>531</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Chamberlain1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mehrtens</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kapral</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boardman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Correlation of carotenoid production, decreased membrane fluidity, and resistance to oleic acid killing in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> 18Z</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>4332</fpage>–<lpage>4337</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Walter1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Carotenoids and their cleavage products: biosynthesis and functions</article-title>. <source>Nat Prod Rep</source> <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>663</fpage>–<lpage>692</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Griffith1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>OW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stuehr</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Nitric oxide synthases: properties and catalytic mechanism</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Physiol</source> <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>707</fpage>–<lpage>736</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Gabr1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gabr</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Symons</surname><given-names>MCR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Novel Reactions of Nitric Oxide in Biological Systems</article-title>. <source>J Chem Soc, Chem Commun</source>: <fpage>915</fpage>–<lpage>916</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Kojima2"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakatsubo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Detection and imaging of nitric oxide with novel fluorescent indicators: diaminofluoresceins</article-title>. <source>Anal Chem</source> <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>2446</fpage>–<lpage>2453</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Kojima3"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sakurai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kikuchi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kirino</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Development of a fluorescent indicator for nitric oxide based on the fluorescein chromophore</article-title>. <source>Chem Pharm Bull (Tokyo)</source> <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>–<lpage>375</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Gusarov3"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gusarov</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Starodubtseva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>ZQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McQuade</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lippard</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Bacterial nitric-oxide synthases operate without a dedicated redox partner</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source> <volume>283</volume>: <fpage>13140</fpage>–<lpage>13147</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Lim1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lippard</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Fluorescent nitric oxide detection by copper complexes bearing anthracenyl and dansyl fluorophore ligands</article-title>. <source>Inorg Chem</source> <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>8980</fpage>–<lpage>8989</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Lim2"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lippard</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Visualization of nitric oxide in living cells by a copper-based fluorescent probe</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>375</fpage>–<lpage>380</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Nagarajan1"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nagarajan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elasri</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>SAMMD: <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> microarray meta-database</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>351</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-SharmaKuinkel1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sharma-Kuinkel</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuechenmeister</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dunman</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> LytSR two-component regulatory system affects biofilm formation</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>191</volume>: <fpage>4767</fpage>–<lpage>4775</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Michel1"><label>62</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Agerer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hauck</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ullrich</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Global regulatory impact of ClpP protease of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> on regulons involved in virulence, oxidative stress response, autolysis, and DNA repair</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source> <volume>188</volume>: <fpage>5783</fpage>–<lpage>5796</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Chang2"><label>63</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toghrol</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bentley</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Toxicogenomic response to chlorination includes induction of major virulence genes in <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Technol</source> <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>7570</fpage>–<lpage>7575</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Reiss1"><label>64</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiss</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pane-Farre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Francois</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liebeke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Global analysis of the <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> response to mupirocin</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source> <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>787</fpage>–<lpage>804</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Pietiainen1"><label>65</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pietiainen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Francois</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyyrylainen</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tangomo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sass</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Transcriptome analysis of the responses of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> to antimicrobial peptides and characterization of the roles of vraDE and vraSR in antimicrobial resistance</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>429</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Neuman1"><label>66</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Neuman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mc</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name> (<year>1958</year>) <article-title>Growth-promoting properties of pyruvate oxal-acetate, and alpha-ketoglutarate for isolated Walker carcinosarcoma 256 cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Soc Exp Biol Med</source> <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>303</fpage>–<lpage>306</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-ODonnellTormey1"><label>67</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>O'Donnell-Tormey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lanks</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>DeBoer</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de la Harpe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Secretion of pyruvate. An antioxidant defense of mammalian cells</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>500</fpage>–<lpage>514</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Hanahan1"><label>68</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanahan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Studies on transformation of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> with plasmids</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source> <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>557</fpage>–<lpage>580</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Kreiswirth1"><label>69</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kreiswirth</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lofdahl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Betley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O'Reilly</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schlievert</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>The toxic shock syndrome exotoxin structural gene is not detectably transmitted by a prophage</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>305</volume>: <fpage>709</fpage>–<lpage>712</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0108868-Gillaspy1"><label>70</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gillaspy</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hickmon</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Role of the accessory gene regulator (<italic>agr</italic>) in pathogenesis of staphylococcal osteomyelitis</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>3373</fpage>–<lpage>3380</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>