<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="EN">
    <front>
        <journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PLoS</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><!--===== Grouping journal title elements =====--><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn><publisher>
                <publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
                <publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc>
            </publisher></journal-meta>
        <article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10-PLME-RA-6004R2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433</article-id><article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                    <subject>Research Article</subject>
                </subj-group>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline">
                    <subject>Evidence-Based Healthcare/Health Services Research and
                        Economics</subject>
                    <subject>Evidence-Based Healthcare/Quality and Safety in Medical
                        Practice</subject>
                    <subject>Public Health and Epidemiology/Health Services Research and
                        Economics</subject>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories><title-group><article-title>Quality of Private and Public Ambulatory Health Care in Low and Middle Income Countries: Systematic Review of Comparative Studies</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Quality of Private Versus Public
                    Care</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Berendes</surname>
                        <given-names>Sima</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Heywood</surname>
                        <given-names>Peter</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
                        <sup>2</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Oliver</surname>
                        <given-names>Sandy</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
                        <sup>3</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
                <contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Garner</surname>
                        <given-names>Paul</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
                        <sup>1</sup>
                    </xref>
                    <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
                        <sup>*</sup>
                    </xref>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
                <label>1</label>
                <addr-line>Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine, Liverpool, United
                    Kingdom</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff2">
                <label>2</label>
                <addr-line>Menzies Center for Health Policy, University of Sydney, Sydney,
                    Australia</addr-line>
            </aff><aff id="aff3">
                <label>3</label>
                <addr-line>Institute of Education, University of London, London, United
                    Kingdom</addr-line>
            </aff><contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
                    <name name-style="western">
                        <surname>Jenkins</surname>
                        <given-names>Rachel</given-names>
                    </name>
                    <role>Academic Editor</role>
                    <xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group><aff id="edit1">King's College London, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes>
                <corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">pgarner@liverpool.ac.uk</email></corresp>
                <fn fn-type="con">
                    <p>ICMJE criteria for authorship read and met: SB PH SO PG. Agree with the
                        manuscript's results and conclusions: SB PH SO PG. Designed the
                        experiments/the study: SB PH SO PG. Analyzed the data: SB PH SO PG.
                        Collected data/did experiments for the study: SB PG. Wrote the first draft
                        of the paper: SB. Contributed to the writing of the paper: PH SO PG.</p>
                </fn>
            <fn fn-type="conflict">
                <p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
            </fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection">
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub">
                <day>12</day>
                <month>4</month>
                <year>2011</year>
            </pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e1000433</elocation-id><history>
                <date date-type="received">
                    <day>19</day>
                    <month>8</month>
                    <year>2010</year>
                </date>
                <date date-type="accepted">
                    <day>3</day>
                    <month>3</month>
                    <year>2011</year>
                </date>
            </history><!--===== Grouping copyright info into permissions =====--><permissions><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Berendes et al</copyright-holder><license><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under
                the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted
                use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and
                source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="RA1" issue="4" page="e1000432" related-article-type="companion" vol="8" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000432" xlink:title="Perspective" xlink:type="simple">
                <article-title>The Quality of Medical Care in Low-Income Countries: From Providers
                    to Markets</article-title>
            </related-article><abstract abstract-type="toc">
                <p>Paul Garner and colleagues conducted a systematic review of 80 studies to compare
                    the quality of private versus public ambulatory health care in low- and
                    middle-income countries.</p>
            </abstract><abstract>
                <sec>
                    <title>Background</title>
                    <p>In developing countries, the private sector provides a substantial proportion
                        of primary health care to low income groups for communicable and
                        non-communicable diseases. These providers are therefore central to
                        improving health outcomes. We need to know how their services compare to
                        those of the public sector to inform policy options.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Methods and Findings</title>
                    <p>We summarised reliable research comparing the quality of formal private
                        versus public ambulatory health care in low and middle income countries. We
                        selected studies against inclusion criteria following a comprehensive
                        search, yielding 80 studies. We compared quality under standard categories,
                        converted values to a linear 100% scale, calculated differences
                        between providers within studies, and summarised median values of the
                        differences across studies. As the results for for-profit and not-for-profit
                        providers were similar, we combined them. Overall, median values indicated
                        that many services, irrespective of whether public or private, scored low on
                        infrastructure, clinical competence, and practice. Overall, the private
                        sector performed better in relation to drug supply, responsiveness, and
                        effort. No difference between provider groups was detected for patient
                        satisfaction or competence. Synthesis of qualitative components indicates
                        the private sector is more client centred.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title>Conclusions</title>
                    <p>Although data are limited, quality in both provider groups seems poor, with
                        the private sector performing better in drug availability and aspects of
                        delivery of care, including responsiveness and effort, and possibly being
                        more client orientated. Strategies seeking to influence quality in both
                        groups are needed to improve care delivery and outcomes for the poor,
                        including managing the increasing burden of non-communicable diseases.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec>
                    <title/>
                    <p>
                        <italic>Please see later in the article for the Editors' Summary</italic>
                    </p>
                </sec>
            </abstract><abstract abstract-type="editor">
                <title>Editors' Summary</title>
                <sec id="s5a1">
                    <title>Background</title>
                    <p>The provision of private (“for-profit” hospitals and
                        self-employed practitioners, and “not-for-profit” non-government
                        providers, including faith-based organizations) versus public health care
                        services in low and middle income countries raises considerable ideological
                        debate. Ideological arguments aside—which can be very passionate on
                        both sides—there is general agreement that improving the quality of
                        both public and private health care could have a major impact on improved
                        health outcomes, especially as the private sector is so widely used in low
                        and middle income countries. For example, almost three quarters and half of
                        children from the poorest households of South Asia and sub-Saharan Africa,
                        respectively, seek health care from a private provider when they are ill.
                        Private providers are also increasingly responsible for outpatient care for
                        non-communicable diseases.</p>
                    <p>As a result of the mixed health care system in many low and middle income
                        countries, adequate oversight and stewardship of the mixed system from the
                        national government is essential yet often missing.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s5a2">
                    <title>Why Was This Study Done?</title>
                    <p>An understanding of how quality and performance in the private sector
                        compares with that in the public sector would help governments to prioritize
                        where they need to concentrate their efforts. So, for example, if the
                        private sector is generally providing poorer quality care than the public
                        sector, then there is an imperative to improve the quality and outcomes; on
                        the other hand, if the quality of care offered by the private sector is
                        good, the policy priority is to influence the market to further improve
                        access to such health care for low income groups.</p>
                    <p>In order to help with this comparison, the researchers wanted to
                        systematically identify and summarize the results of studies that directly
                        compared the quality of care offered by public providers with the one
                        offered by “formal” private providers (recognized by law) and
                        “informal” private providers (providers that are not legally
                        recognized, such as lay health workers and shop keepers). For the purposes
                        of this study the researchers focused their comparison on the private and
                        public provision of outpatient care in low and middle income countries.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s5a3">
                    <title>What Did the Researchers Do and Find?</title>
                    <p>In their literature review, the researchers searched for relevant studies
                        reported in English, French, or German and published between January 1970
                        and April 2009. Only studies that compared private and public outpatient
                        medical services in the same country, at the same time, using the same
                        methods, and which met particular quality criteria, were included in the
                        analysis. The researchers also had strict criteria for including qualitative
                        studies, and they retrieved the full text of articles, contacted study
                        authors where appropriate, and verified with a second researcher most
                        (80%) of the extracted study data. In order to evaluate and compare
                        the studies, the researchers converted study values to a linear 100%
                        scale, calculated differences between providers within studies, and
                        summarized the median values of the differences across studies.</p>
                    <p>The researchers identified a total of 8,812 relevant titles and abstracts and
                        found 80 studies that included direct quantitative comparisons of public and
                        private formal providers. Ten studies included qualitative data. Most
                        studies were conducted after 1990, and mainly in sub-Saharan Africa
                            (<italic>n</italic> = 39) and Asia and the Pacific
                            (<italic>n</italic> = 23). Most studies did not
                        report socio-economic status of public and private service users, and only
                        five studies presented data by different income groups. No study compared
                        the same individual providers working in public and private care settings.
                        Only two studies compared public providers and private informal providers,
                        so the authors excluded these from subsequent analysis.</p>
                    <p>For the formal sector, since the results for “for-profit” and
                        “not-for-profit” providers were similar, the researchers decided
                        to combine the results. Overall, the researchers found that the median
                        values indicated that many services, irrespective of whether public or
                        private, scored low (less than 50%) on infrastructure, clinical
                        competence, and practice. Generally, the private sector performed better in
                        relation to drug supply, responsiveness, and effort, but there was no
                        detectable difference between provider groups for patient satisfaction.
                        Furthermore, a synthesis of qualitative data suggested that the private
                        sector may be more client-centered.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s5a4">
                    <title>What Do These Findings Mean?</title>
                    <p>Based on the findings of this review, there is a clear need to consider the
                        quality of primary health services in both the public and private sector in
                        order to improve health outcomes in low and middle income countries. These
                        findings also indicate that, for some aspects of care, on average the
                        private sector provided better quality services. The overall low quality of
                        care in both the formal private and public sector found in this review is
                        worrying, and calls for the governments of low and middle income countries
                        to find and implement effective strategies to improve the quality in both
                        sectors. This is particularly important given the increasing volume of
                        conditions that require relatively sophisticated, long-term ambulatory
                        medical care, such as non-communicable diseases.</p>
                </sec>
                <sec id="s5a5">
                    <title>Additional Information</title>
                    <p>Please access these Web sites via the online version of this summary at
                            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433" xlink:type="simple">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433</ext-link>.</p>
                    <list list-type="bullet">
                        <list-item>
                            <p>This study is further discussed in a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000432" xlink:type="simple"><italic>PLoS Medicine</italic>
                                Perspective by Jishnu Das</ext-link>
                                </p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                            <p>WHO has more information on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/healthsystems/topics/delivery/en/index.html" xlink:type="simple">health service delivery</ext-link> in low- and middle-income
                                countries</p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                            <p>WHO has more information on <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/topics/chronic_diseases/en/" xlink:type="simple">noncommunicable diseases</ext-link></p>
                        </list-item>
                        <list-item>
                            <p>The World Bank's <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://econ.worldbank.org/external/default/main?menuPK=477704&amp;pagePK=64167702&amp;piPK=64167676&amp;theSitePK=477688" xlink:type="simple">World Development Report for 2004</ext-link> addresses health
                                care for poor people</p>
                        </list-item>
                    </list>
                </sec>
            </abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was funded by the UK Department for International Development for
                    the benefit of the poor in developing countries (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.research4development.info/SearchResearchDatabase.asp?ProjectID=50118" xlink:type="simple">http://www.research4development.info/SearchResearchDatabase.asp?ProjectID=50118</ext-link>).
                    The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision
                    to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts>
                <page-count count="10"/>
            </counts></article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec id="s1">
            <title>Introduction</title>
            <p>The private sector is the main provider of primary health care for the poor in many
                low and middle income countries (LMICs). For example, in South Asia about three
                quarters of children from the poorest income quintile with acute respiratory
                conditions seeking health care go to a private provider <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-World1">[1]</xref>, and about 45% of sick
                children from the poorest income quintile across 26 African countries go to a formal
                or informal private provider rather than a public provider for health care <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Marek1">[2]</xref>. Private
                providers are also increasingly important for providing ambulatory care as
                non-communicable diseases (NCDs) increase <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Murray1">[3]</xref>.</p>
            <p>Private providers may be “formal”, i.e. recognised by law or by legally
                recognised regulatory authorities, or “informal”, i.e. not recognised
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Bloom1">[4]</xref>. Formal
                private providers include “for-profit” hospitals and self-employed
                practitioners, and “not-for-profit” non-governmental organizations
                (NGOs). NGOs include churches, and are particularly common in Africa, although the
                for-profit/not-for-profit dichotomy is not so clear cut in practice, with some NGOs
                simply representing private practitioners securing tax breaks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson1">[5]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Kanji1">[6]</xref>. Informal allopathic providers
                include “quacks”, lay health workers, drug sellers, and ordinary shop
                keepers <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Waters1">[7]</xref>.</p>
            <p>Advocating that formal for-profit private services are preferable to government
                provision raises considerable ideological debates <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Hanson1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Sauerborn1">[10]</xref>; equally, not-for-profit
                private providers such as those run by churches are seen by some as good and as
                providing value for money <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Leonard1">[11]</xref>. Whatever the debates, there is agreement that
                influencing the quality of both public and private providers could have a major
                impact on health outcomes. Adequate state stewardship and oversight of these mixed
                systems is widely advocated <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lagomarsino1">[9]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Saltman1">[12]</xref>, but the mechanisms to assure quality are not simple and
                are of unclear effectiveness <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Patouillard1">[13]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Peters1">[14]</xref>. Improving stewardship and oversight is complex,
                involving resources, management, legislation, and approaches to influence the market
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Leonard2">[15]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Mills1">[16]</xref>. Thus, an
                understanding of how quality and performance in the formal private sector compares
                with that of the public sector would help governments to focus strategies to improve
                delivery. Putting this simply, if the private sector is generally providing poorer
                quality care than the public sector, then there is an imperative to improve the
                quality and outcomes; on the other hand, if the quality of private-sector care is
                good, the priority for policy is to influence the market somehow to further improve
                access for low income groups.</p>
            <p>“Quality” has many dimensions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Donabedian1">[17]</xref>, including structural
                quality, aspects of delivery, and the technical or professional content of care, all
                of which are likely to influence service use. Each dimension will have complex
                effects on patient satisfaction, patient use of the service, and outcomes for their
                health. In addition, each is interrelated: population health outcomes will depend on
                service use, technical quality, and drug availability, for example. A recent
                substantive analysis that examined the use of medicines in primary care reported
                poor quality prescribing for both sectors, with little change over time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-World2">[18]</xref>. The authors
                also reported the relatively poor quality of data and the need for research
                assessing the difference between the public and private sector. Thus, our objective
                was to systematically identify and summarise the results of studies that directly
                compare the quality of private providers and public services in relation to
                ambulatory health care in LMICs.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
            <title>Methods</title>
            <sec id="s2a">
                <title>Criteria for Inclusion</title>
                <p>We included field-based studies that directly compared service quality in
                    ambulatory care from private versus public medical health services. The purpose
                    was to include studies using the same methods to measure the differences, and in
                    the same countries, to avoid confounding factors related to overall differences
                    in service quality between countries. We included studies conducted in LMICs
                    that assessed ambulatory care, defined as the “delivery of personal health
                    care services on an outpatient basis” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Berman1">[19]</xref>. We only included studies
                    that compared private and public services in the same country, at the same time,
                    using the same methods, and which met particular quality criteria (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s003">Table S1</xref>).
                    “Private” refers to “all organizations and individuals working
                    outside the direct control of the state” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Bennett1">[20]</xref>, and we included only
                    those working within the allopathic medical systems. “Private for-profit
                    providers” included individuals or groups of practitioners in privately
                    owned clinics, hospitals, and pharmacies that operate on a for-profit basis,
                    while “private not-for-profit providers” included practitioners in
                    facilities that operate on a non-profit basis, such as various (missionary or
                    non-missionary) NGOs and private voluntary organizations. Informal providers
                    included those without formal health professional qualifications, such as street
                    vendors and shop keepers. We included studies reported in English, French, or
                    German and published from January 1970 to April 2009. We screened all
                    titles/abstracts found by the search methods described below for potential
                    inclusion, and then carefully applied the detailed inclusion criteria (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s003">Table S1</xref>)
                    to the full text of those identified in the screening search. Studies using
                    qualitative methods were identified and were included if they (a) used
                    internationally accepted data collection methods (e.g., in-depth interviews,
                    focus group discussion, or observation), (b) indicated the methods used in
                    analysis (e.g., thematic analysis, content analysis, or grounded theory), and
                    (c) presented data by theme or in the form of verbatim quotes.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2b">
                <title>Search Methods</title>
                <p>The search strategy for Medline can be found in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s004">Table S2</xref>,
                    and a list of the databases searched in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s005">Table S3</xref>. In addition, we searched all
                    records of the World Health Organization's (WHO's) library database,
                    WHOLIS (on 27 April 2009), all Service Availability Mapping reports published on
                    the WHO Web site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/healthinfo/systems/samdocs/en/index.html" xlink:type="simple">http://www.who.int/healthinfo/systems/samdocs/en/index.html</ext-link>) (on
                    5 December 2010) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-World3">[21]</xref>, all Service Provision Assessment Survey reports
                    published on the Measure DHS Web site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.measuredhs.com/aboutsurveys/search/search_survey_main.cfm?SrvyTp=type&amp;listtypes=3" xlink:type="simple">http://www.measuredhs.com/aboutsurveys/search/search_survey_main.cfm?SrvyTp=type&amp;listtypes=3</ext-link>)
                    (on 3 December 2010) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Measure1">[22]</xref>, and all research studies published on the Core group
                    Web site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.coregroup.org/" xlink:type="simple">http://www.coregroup.org/</ext-link>) (on 6 December 2010), and we examined
                    reference lists of relevant reviews <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Madden1">[23]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Zurovac1">[25]</xref> and of the included
                    studies.</p>
                <p>The search strategies included indexed and free-text terms: health sector, health
                    care, delivery of health care, primary health care, medical care, health clinic,
                    outpatient service, ambulatory care, practitioner, health provider, health
                    provision, hospital, pharmacy, drug vendor, drug seller, drug store, public
                    sector, public, private sector, private, quality of health care, Africa, Asia,
                    South America, developing countries, less developed countries, third world
                    countries, underdeveloped country, low income country, low income nation, middle
                    income country, middle income nation, low and middle income countries.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s2c">
                <title>Data Collection and Analysis</title>
                <p>We applied the inclusion criteria to all titles and abstracts. We retrieved
                    full-text copies of potentially relevant records, and discussed each to resolve
                    uncertainties. We then appraised potential studies against a set of basic
                    minimum methodological criteria to exclude studies where data were unlikely to
                    be reliable (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s003">Table S1</xref>).</p>
                <p>We adapted Donabedian's <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Donabedian1">[17]</xref> classification of quality of care using structural,
                    delivery, and technical categories (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-1000433-t001">Table 1</xref>). We incorporated
                    “responsiveness” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-World5">[26]</xref> to reflect aspects such as waiting time,
                    communication quality, and dignity, as well as an assessment of the
                    “effort” providers make, such as whether they examine the patient,
                    and the length of the consultation time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Leonard3">[27]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Das1">[28]</xref>, and we divided technical
                    quality into measures of competence and clinical practice (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-1000433-t001">Table 1</xref>).</p>
                <table-wrap id="pmed-1000433-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
                        <title>Quality categories, sub-categories, and indicators used.</title>
                    </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pmed-1000433-t001-1" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.t001" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                        <colgroup span="1">
                            <col align="left" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                            <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        </colgroup>
                        <thead>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Quality Category</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sub-Category</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Description and Indicators</td>
                            </tr>
                        </thead>
                        <tbody>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Structural</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Building, equipment, materials</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Availability and condition of health facilities,
                                    and of defined equipment, materials, and supplies</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug availability</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Availability of essential drugs in health
                                    facilities and pharmacies</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Delivery</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Responsiveness</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Waiting time, privacy, confidentiality, staff
                                    friendliness, communication, dignity</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effort</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Length of consultation time, whether a physical
                                    examination is performed, number of explanations given</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient satisfaction</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patients' satisfaction with last
                                    consultation</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Technical</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Competence</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Professional knowledge and skills</td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinical practice</td>
                                <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Presence or absence of critical elements of care,
                                    whether practice is according to standards or guidelines,
                                    proxies for correct prescribing behaviour</td>
                            </tr>
                        </tbody>
                    </table></alternatives></table-wrap>
                <p>S. B. extracted data using a standard form, entered into an Access database, with
                    about 80% verified by a second author to ensure standardisation of
                    coding. We contacted 33 authors for further information, and all but nine
                    authors responded. Standard data describing the study were extracted. If a study
                    reported several comparisons, we selected groups that were most similar within
                    the health system (e.g., public hospitals versus private hospitals, or public
                    health centres versus private clinics). If results were presented separately for
                    different cadres or levels of staff qualification, we chose the comparison group
                    with the staff qualification levels that were most comparable and most
                    frequented by the population. If the latter could not be established, we chose
                    the highest qualified comparison group.</p>
                <p>We then separately computed summary measures of (a) the overall level of quality
                    of care in the private and in the public sector and (b) the difference of
                    quality of care between both sectors stratified by quality categories and
                    components. If there were several data measures for one component in a study, we
                    computed the median for all reported measures to calculate a single measure for
                    component quality for the provider. For example, in the case of a public-sector
                    score (on a linear scale, with 100% being the maximum obtainable) of
                    45% for physical infrastructure, 50% for availability of basic
                    diagnostic equipment, and 60% for availability of basic material, the
                    median for the structural component “building, equipment, and
                    material” would be 50%. The median was also computed for the
                    quality score difference between private and public provider. For example, in
                    case of a difference of +5% in physical infrastructure,
                    +11% in availability of basic diagnostic equipment, and
                    +14% in basic material, the median difference would be
                    +11% for the given comparison in a study. After computing the
                    medians for the overall quality of care and for the difference of care for each
                    single comparison in each study, we computed medians and inter-quartile ranges
                    (IQRs) across all comparisons. The size of the difference and the IQRs of the
                    difference were used to judge whether a difference was evident.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s3">
            <title>Results</title>
            <p>Of 8,812 titles and abstracts identified, 80 studies included direct quantitative
                comparisons of public and private formal providers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pmed-1000433-g001">Figure 1</xref>, adapted from PRISMA 2009 flow diagram
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Moher1">[29]</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s006">Tables S4</xref> and
                    <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s007">S5</xref>
                describe excluded studies). These yielded 133 comparisons, of which we were able to
                convert 101 to a 100% scale (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s008">Table S6</xref>). Most studies were carried out after
                1990; they were mainly conducted in sub-Saharan Africa
                    (<italic>n = </italic>39) and in Asia and the Pacific
                    (<italic>n = </italic>23); and most were intended to
                compare quality, examining all types of primary service and disease category (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-1000433-t002">Table 2</xref>; details in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s011">Table S9</xref>). Most
                studies did not report socio-economic status of public and private service users,
                and only five presented data by different wealth groups <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Barber1">[30]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Das2">[34]</xref>. No study compared the same
                individual providers working in public and private care settings. For two studies
                    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Barber4">[35]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Nahum1">[36]</xref> that reported
                results separately for different cadres, we chose public versus private doctors
                rather than public versus private nurses or midwives as comparison groups, but it
                should be noted that for both groups results pointed in the same direction.</p>
            <fig id="pmed-1000433-g001" position="float">
                <object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.g001</object-id>
                <label>Figure 1</label>
                <caption>
                    <title>Selection of studies.</title>
                    <p>* See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s006">Table S4</xref> for reasons of exclusion; † see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s007">Table
                            S5</xref> for reasons of exclusion.</p>
                </caption>
                <graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
            </fig>
            <table-wrap id="pmed-1000433-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
                    <title>Characteristics of quantitative studies comparing public and formal
                        private providers by region
                        (<italic>n = </italic>80).</title>
                </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pmed-1000433-t002-2" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.t002" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                    <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Characteristic</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">South Asia, East Asia, and Pacific</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Sub-Saharan Africa</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Other<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Total Number of Studies</td>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>Language</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">English</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">23</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">33</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">72</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">French</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>Study year range</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1980–1989</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1990–1999</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">16</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">31</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2000–2009</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>Primary study purpose</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Describe or compare quality of private and public
                                services</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">58</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Assess drug availability and affordability</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Assess demand for, access to, or utilisation of
                                services, or efficiency of service delivery</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>Service type</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Promotive or preventive</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Curative, rehabilitative, or palliative</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">28</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">All types</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">18</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not specified</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>Disease category</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Both CD and NCD</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">24</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">9</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">CD</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">13</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">NCD</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not specified</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>Population age</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Adult</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">6</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Both adult and child</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">43</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Child</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">4</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Not specified</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">11</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>Population gender</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Both (male and female)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">21</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">34</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">15</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">70</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Female</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>Total number of studies</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>23</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>39</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>18</bold>
                            </td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
                                <bold>80</bold>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="nt101">
                        <label>a</label>
                        <p>Includes Europe and Central Asia
                                (<italic>n = </italic>1), Latin America and the
                            Caribbean (<italic>n = </italic>6), the Middle East
                            and North Africa (<italic>n = </italic>7), and
                            studies reporting on countries in more than one world region
                                (<italic>n = </italic>4).</p>
                    </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
            <p>We found only two studies comparing public providers and private informal providers.
                The first <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Massele1">[37]</xref>
                compared malaria-related knowledge and chloroquine availability in public
                dispensaries and informal drug vendors, and suggested that the public sector was
                slightly better. The second <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Tuan1">[38]</xref> mixed both formal and informal private providers
                together. These two studies were excluded from further analysis.</p>
            <p>Of the 101 formal private versus public sector comparisons that were converted to a
                100% scale, 57 compared government with private for-profit providers, 10 with
                a mix of for-profit and not-for-profit providers, and 34 with private not-for-profit
                providers. Of the last 34 comparisons, most
                    (<italic>n = </italic>29) were conducted in sub-Saharan
                Africa.</p>
            <p>Study-level summary values for each quality component are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-1000433-t003">Table 3</xref>, along with the summary
                of the within-study differences. We also carried out an analysis that separated
                private for-profit and private not-for-profit providers (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s009">Table S7</xref>). As
                the results in the for-profit and not-for-profit providers were remarkably
                consistent, they are presented as combined.</p>
            <table-wrap id="pmed-1000433-t003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption>
                    <title>Overall level of quality and comparative quality difference of public and
                        formal private providers.</title>
                </caption><!--===== Grouping alternate versions of objects =====--><alternatives><graphic id="pmed-1000433-t003-3" mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.t003" xlink:type="simple"/><table>
                    <colgroup span="1">
                        <col align="left" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                        <col align="center" span="1"/>
                    </colgroup>
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Category</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Component</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Number of Comparisons Converted to 100%
                                Scale</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Public Quality Score (%)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Private Quality Score (%)</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Difference Private-Public<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref> (%)</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IQR</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IQR</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Median</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">IQR</td>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Structural</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Building, equipment, and materials</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">26</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">41.9</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">25.0, 76.5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22.0, 86.6</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">2.8</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.9, 20.6</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Drug availability</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">14</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">38.8, 58.5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">63.0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.4, 94.8</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">17.9</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">12.5, 29.1</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Delivery</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Responsiveness</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">85.0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.9, 86.3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">89.1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.7, 94.5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">7.0,12.4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Effort</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">84.9</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">46.5, 87.0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">92.9</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">54.5, 93.5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">8.0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.5, 8.0</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Patient satisfaction</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">10</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">56.9, 78.8</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">75.0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">68.0, 79.1</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0.5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−2.0, 4.4</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Technical</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Competence</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">19</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">52.8</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">36.3, 54.2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">45.2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">35.0, 53.3</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−3.0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">−7.6, 0.8</td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1"/>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Clinical practice</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">22</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">44.5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">27.5, 60.9</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">47.0</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">39.1, 66.5</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">5.2</td>
                            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">1.3, 14.0</td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot>
                    <fn id="nt102">
                        <label>a</label>
                        <p>Within each comparison, the difference between the public score and the
                            private score was calculated. The data in this column are the median of
                            these values across all studies. For this reason, they will not
                            correspond to an arithmetic difference of the absolute median scores in
                            the previous columns.</p>
                    </fn>
                </table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
            <p>In addition, ten studies included qualitative data that met our eligibility criteria,
                with a similar geographic spread to the quantitative data.</p>
            <sec id="s3a">
                <title>Structure</title>
                <p>For buildings, equipment, materials, and supplies, no difference was detected.
                    For the 26 comparisons, the IQR of the difference included 0. Respondents in two
                    qualitative studies reporting on this category described private facilities as
                    better <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>.</p>
                <p>For drug availability, private-sector care was substantially better than
                    public-sector care, from 14 comparisons. Nine studies used a standard method and
                    referred to the WHO essential drug list <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-World6">[41]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-World7">[42]</xref>. None of the quantitative
                    studies compared the quality of drugs available in the public versus private
                    sector. Qualitative studies reported that the private sector was more trusted
                    for drug quality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Russell1">[43]</xref> and that the drugs were more readily available <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Deressa1">[44]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lewis1">[45]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3b">
                <title>Service Delivery</title>
                <p>For responsiveness, private-sector care was better (see <xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-1000433-t001">Table 1</xref> for definition), from seven
                    comparisons. Studies used patient interviews, observations, or simulated visits.
                    In six of the seven comparisons measuring waiting time, the time was shorter in
                    the private sector. Qualitative data in five studies indicated that the private
                    sector provided more personalised, respectful <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Hoa1">[46]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Turan1">[47]</xref>, listening <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Russell1">[43]</xref>, and
                    client-centred service, as well as service that was more convenient <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lim1">[48]</xref> and quicker
                    and easier to access <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Turan1">[47]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Paphassarang1">[49]</xref>.</p>
                <p>For effort, private-sector care was better, from three comparisons. A further
                    four studies reported on average consultation times, which were longer in the
                    private sector in all studies, although statistical significance was only
                    computed and confirmed in two of them <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Kanji1">[6]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Pongsupap1">[50]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Mbanefoh1">[52]</xref>.
                    Qualitative data were consistent with this finding. Studies consistently
                    reported criticisms of the public sector (with providers showing favouritism for
                    some patients and less respect for poorer clients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Russell1">[43]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Deressa1">[44]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Hoa1">[46]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lim1">[48]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Paphassarang1">[49]</xref>) and praise for the
                    private sector <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Russell1">[43]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lim1">[48]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Paphassarang1">[49]</xref>.</p>
                <p>For patient satisfaction, no difference between private and public sector was
                    detected, from ten comparisons. None of the studies measuring
                    “satisfaction” reported the use of a validated questionnaire. Only
                    one took into account possible differences in expectations of public and private
                    services <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Mahaprata1">[53]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3c">
                <title>Technical Quality</title>
                <p>For competence, scores for private- versus public-sector care were similar, and
                    generally poor, from 19 comparisons; competence was measured by case scenarios
                    or vignettes, provider interviews, or a formal test. In qualitative studies the
                    private sector was reported as quicker and easier to access, although the
                    competence of some providers was questioned <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lim1">[48]</xref>. The public sector was often
                    perceived as technically competent but inconvenient and provider centred, with
                    complex systems that took time and effort to negotiate <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Deressa1">[44]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Turan1">[47]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Paphassarang1">[49]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Schneider1">[54]</xref>.</p>
                <p>For clinical practice, private-sector care was marginally better, from 22
                    comparisons. Of those not convertible to a linear 100% scale, 14 studies
                    used the same standard methods to assess prescribing behaviour, summarised in
                        <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s010">Table
                        S8</xref>, with no obvious differences. In qualitative studies, respondents
                    perceived public providers as qualified and well trained <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Russell1">[43]</xref>, although some were
                    thought to overprescribe to raise their income <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lim1">[48]</xref>. The private sector was also
                    criticised for overprescribing and collusion between doctors and pharmacists
                        <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Hoa1">[46]</xref>, for
                    suspected “fake” or unlabelled drugs, for “fake”
                    doctors, and for nurses practicing illegally in private pharmacies in need of
                    regulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Hoa1">[46]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lim1">[48]</xref>.</p>
                <p>We carried out a sensitivity analysis including only studies and comparisons
                        (<italic>n = </italic>67) classified as high quality
                    because of their size (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s003">Table S1</xref> provides the criteria); the results
                    obtained were very similar to <xref ref-type="table" rid="pmed-1000433-t003">Table 3</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3d">
                <title>For-Profit and Not-for-Profit Providers</title>
                <p>As mentioned above, most of the not-for-profit studies were carried out in
                    sub-Saharan Africa (29 of 34 comparisons). <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pmed.1000433.s009">Table S7</xref>
                    contains an analysis stratified by private for-profit and private
                    not-for-profit. The direction of the difference is the same as for the
                    aggregated value for all components. Notably, clinical practice was much better
                    in the for-profit sector, and the difference was less marked for the
                    not-for-profit sector, but the number of comparisons in the for-profit sector is
                    limited.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s3e">
                <title>Factors Contributing to a Quality Difference</title>
                <p>Some of the qualitative studies (<italic>n = </italic>8)
                    sought to explain the quality difference between the two sectors. Factors
                    perceived to be related to low public-sector quality included resource
                    constraints, low salaries, high workload, and poor incentives and conditions of
                    service <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Deressa1">[44]</xref>, the lack of a public family/general practice system
                    that enables patients to return to the doctor(s) of their choice and develop
                    relationships of trust over longer periods of time <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Russell1">[43]</xref>, public-sector drugs being
                    sold privately <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">[40]</xref>, staff favouring particular patients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Turan1">[47]</xref>, and clients
                    lacking sufficient information about the appropriate use of drugs, resistance to
                    antibiotics, costs, and their rights to challenge poor service <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">[39]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Hoa1">[46]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Paphassarang1">[49]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Schneider1">[54]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s4">
            <title>Discussion</title>
            <sec id="s4a">
                <title>Summary</title>
                <p>The results of our analyses indicate that, in both private and public sectors,
                    median values for structure, competence, and clinical practice fall around or
                    below scores of 50/100. Whilst these values depend on the instruments used and
                    the stringency of the primary research studies in applying these standards, the
                    trends provide some insight into absolute performance, with obvious problems
                    with technical aspects of care in both sectors.</p>
                <p>In comparative performance, the formal private sector was better for drug
                    availability, responsiveness, and effort. Overall, the median differences were
                    modest, so stereotyped opinions that one sector is clearly better than another
                    are not supported by this review.</p>
                <p>Qualitative data portrayed formal private services that, in contrast to the
                    public sector, were more client centred. This is consistent with the differences
                    in care delivery shown by the quantitative data.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4b">
                <title>Interpretation</title>
                <p>In a formal private setting, drugs may be more available because funds are not
                    restricted in the same way as in the public sector, and private providers are
                    motivated to encourage patients to return, so responsiveness and effort are
                    greater.</p>
                <p>These results, combined with the fact that the private sector provides a
                    substantial amount of health services, raise two further issues—the
                    importance of paying attention to both sectors if overall quality is to be
                    raised, and the need for governments to play a more active role in assuring
                    quality of care.</p>
                <p>Many efforts to improve the quality of ambulatory care are restricted to the
                    public sector on the grounds that public funds should be reserved for the public
                    sector because that is where the poor turn for their health care. But
                    concentrating on the public sector misses a large proportion, the majority in
                    some cases, of the providers used by the poor. Raising the quality of care
                    delivered by private, as well as public, providers would, in fact, be a pro-poor
                    intervention as it would improve the effectiveness of the money the poor spend
                    on health care. A second argument advanced against spending public money on
                    private providers is that because they provide a lower quality of care it is
                    more effective to reserve funds for the public sector. The results of this
                    review indicate that the overall quality of care from the two sets of providers
                    is similar; if anything, the private sector is more responsive and drug
                    availability is greater.</p>
                <p>The overall low quality of care is likely to become even more so as the double
                    burden of communicable disease (CD) and NCD becomes more prominent. Most health
                    care providers, public or private, practicing today have been trained by
                    institutions and work in health systems primarily oriented to CDs. Consequently,
                    providers have only limited knowledge of NCDs, which demand a different set of
                    clinical skills and a different approach to treatment. On most dimensions,
                    effective treatment for NCDs requires approaches quite different to those that
                    are available through the current health systems, and, contrary to views held by
                    many, NCDs and associated risk factors are not the preserve of the rich; they
                    are equally, if not more, prevalent among the poor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Strong1">[55]</xref>. Thus, it has to be
                    considered that certain types of diseases, such as some NCDs, but also more
                    complex CDs, such as AIDS, might require particularly high levels of structural
                    quality, drug availability, and provider competence, while for other diseases,
                    such as childhood diarrhoea, that are easy to diagnose and treat, it is most
                    important to motivate providers to exert effort and practice what they already
                    know <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Das3">[56]</xref>.</p>
                <p>Raising the quality of care in a health system is a long-term effort and requires
                    attention to various aspects, including the incentive structure and training,
                    both areas in which government has an important role, but to which it frequently
                    pays little attention. Systematic and comprehensive traditional narrative
                    reviews suggest a variety of strategies that can help increase quality. For
                    example, supervision and audit with feedback, especially if combined with
                    training, have been found to be effective <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Rowe1">[57]</xref>. However, an overall
                    government bias against the private sector frequently means that too little
                    attention is paid, and too few resources devoted, to overall supervision of the
                    private sector. But setting standards, partly through ensuring standards of
                    training, partly through licensing and accreditation of professionals (including
                    emphasis on continuing education), and partly through consumer protection laws,
                    is an important role of government <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Mills1">[16]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Bhat1">[58]</xref>. Researchers such as Leonard
                    and colleagues <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Leonard2">[15]</xref> have provided useful theoretical frameworks for
                    influencing the private sector based on the “principal-agent
                    theory”. Others have proposed different ways of classifying the variety of
                    strategies that have so far been used to improve the quality of private care,
                    for example, classifying strategies according to the influence they have either
                    on supply or demand or on the overall market environment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Mills1">[16]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Brugha1">[59]</xref>. However, empirical
                    evidence on the effectiveness of various approaches is somewhat limited, as the
                    review by Peters et al. shows for reproductive health care <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Peters1">[14]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4c">
                <title>Strengths and Weaknesses of This Review</title>
                <p>The search was comprehensive, the inclusion criteria were applied carefully, and
                    quality criteria were applied to ensure comparisons were valid and were direct
                    comparisons using the same methods. Given that studies used a very varied set of
                    tools to measure quality of care, results on the absolute level of quality of
                    care have to be interpreted with caution. However, results on the difference in
                    quality of care can be interpreted with more confidence, because, as mentioned
                    above, we took care to include only those studies that directly compared quality
                    of care in the same country at the same time, using the same methods. A further
                    strength is that we were able to categorise the various quality components to
                    allow comparisons between studies. A disadvantage is that small studies could
                    contribute as much to the estimates as large studies, but the sensitivity
                    analysis—excluding the smaller studies—did not alter the direction
                    of the differences between the sectors.</p>
                <p>Although this review fully assessed eligible comparative studies on quality,
                    additional work is needed to compare costs and aspects of equity. Similar to the
                    dispute on quality, there are controversial views on whether private or public
                    care is more costly or more accessible to the poor.</p>
                <p>The review also highlights the lack of comparative evidence between the public
                    sector and the private informal sector, although the latter is widely used <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Marek1">[2]</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pmed.1000433-Das4">[60]</xref>.</p>
            </sec>
            <sec id="s4d">
                <title>Implications for Policy and Research</title>
                <p>With the current evidence base, there is a clear need to consider quality of
                    primary health services in both the public and private sector in order to
                    improve health outcomes. There is a tendency for the private sector to provide
                    better quality services, but further research on the overall quality and testing
                    feasibility and effectiveness of mechanisms to improve quality will be critical
                    for future health gains in LMICs.</p>
                <p>Research needs to standardise outcomes and measures of socio-economic position
                    across studies to improve comparability and to assist in between-country
                    dialogue on effective quality assurance policies. Research on the effectiveness
                    of market-led strategies to influence the private sector is important. Studies
                    of dual practice, examining the same providers' behaviour in the two
                    settings, could be useful specific studies in identifying factors in terms of
                    the setting. Lastly, establishing minimum standards of care, and research to
                    help identify effective approaches to achieve them, is central to achieving the
                    health gains that are possible with current preventive and treatment medical
                    technologies.</p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s6">
            <title>Supporting Information</title>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s001" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s001" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Alternative Language Abstract S1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Translation of the Abstract into French by Sima Berendes.</p>
                    <p>(0.02 MB DOCX)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s002" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s002" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Alternative Language Abstract S2</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Translation of the Abstract into German by Sima Berendes.</p>
                    <p>(0.03 MB DOCX)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s003" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s003" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Table S1</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Inclusion criteria for study reliability.</p>
                    <p>(0.07 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s004" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s004" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Table S2</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Search strategy for Medline.</p>
                    <p>(0.07 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s005" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s005" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Table S3</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Databases searched.</p>
                    <p>(0.05 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s006" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s006" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Table S4</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Reasons for exclusion during screening of titles/abstracts or full
                        papers.</p>
                    <p>(0.05 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s007" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s007" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Table S5</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Excluded studies after reliability criteria application.</p>
                    <p>(0.09 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s008" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s008" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Table S6</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Number of studies and comparisons per category.</p>
                    <p>(0.06 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s009" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s009" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Table S7</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Results of comparisons between public and private providers for sub-Saharan
                        Africa only and stratified by private provider type.</p>
                    <p>(0.06 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s010" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s010" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Table S8</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Comparison of selected prescribing behaviours for patient visits to
                        public-sector and formal for-profit private-sector care providers in
                        LMICs.</p>
                    <p>(0.08 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
            <supplementary-material id="pmed.1000433.s011" mimetype="application/msword" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000433.s011" xlink:type="simple">
                <label>Table S9</label>
                <caption>
                    <p>Characteristics of included quantitative studies summarised by world
                        region.</p>
                    <p>(0.22 MB DOC)</p>
                </caption>
            </supplementary-material>
        </sec>
    </body>
    <back>
        <ack>
            <p>We thank Vittoria Lutje (Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine) for information
                retrieval and Sarah Donegan (Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine) for statistical
                advice. This research was funded by the United Kingdom Department for International
                Development for the benefit of the poor in developing countries.</p>
        </ack>
        <ref-list>
            <title>References</title>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-World1">
                <label>1</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">World Bank</collab>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <source>World development report: Making services work for poor people</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Washington (District of Columbia)</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>World Bank and Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Marek1">
                <label>2</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Marek</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>O'Farrell</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zable</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <source>Trends and opportunities in public-private partnerships to improve
                        health service delivery in Africa. Africa Region Human Development Working
                        Paper Series</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Washington (District of Columbia)</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>World Bank</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Murray1">
                <label>3</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Murray</surname>
                            <given-names>CJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lopez</surname>
                            <given-names>AD</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>Alternative projections of mortality and disability by cause
                        1990–2020: Global Burden of Disease Study.</article-title>
                    <source>Lancet</source>
                    <volume>349</volume>
                    <fpage>1498</fpage>
                    <lpage>1504</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Bloom1">
                <label>4</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bloom</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Standing</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lloyd</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Markets, information asymmetry and health care: towards new
                        social contracts.</article-title>
                    <source>Soc Sci Med</source>
                    <volume>66</volume>
                    <fpage>2076</fpage>
                    <lpage>2087</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Gilson1">
                <label>5</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gilson</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sen</surname>
                            <given-names>PD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mohammed</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mujinja</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1994</year>
                    <article-title>The potential of health sector non-governmental organizations:
                        policy options.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>9</volume>
                    <fpage>14</fpage>
                    <lpage>24</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Kanji1">
                <label>6</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kanji</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kilima</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lorenz</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Garner</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1995</year>
                    <article-title>Quality of primary outpatient services in Dar-es-Salaam: a
                        comparison of government and voluntary providers.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>10</volume>
                    <fpage>186</fpage>
                    <lpage>190</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Waters1">
                <label>7</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Waters</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hatt</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Peters</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Working with the private sector for child health.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                    <fpage>127</fpage>
                    <lpage>137</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Hanson1">
                <label>8</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hanson</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gilson</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Goodman</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mills</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Smith</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Is private health care the answer to the health problems of the
                        world's poor?</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS Med</source>
                    <volume>5</volume>
                    <fpage>e233</fpage>
                    <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.0050233" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.0050233</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Lagomarsino1">
                <label>9</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lagomarsino</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>de Ferranti</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pablos-Mendez</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nachuk</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nishtar</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Public stewardship of mixed health systems.</article-title>
                    <source>Lancet</source>
                    <volume>374</volume>
                    <fpage>1577</fpage>
                    <lpage>1578</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Sauerborn1">
                <label>10</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sauerborn</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2001</year>
                    <article-title>Low quality of care in low income countries: is the private
                        sector the answer?</article-title>
                    <source>Int J Qual Health Care</source>
                    <volume>13</volume>
                    <fpage>281</fpage>
                    <lpage>282</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Leonard1">
                <label>11</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Leonard</surname>
                            <given-names>KL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>When both states and markets fail: asymmetric information and the
                        role of NGOs in African health care.</article-title>
                    <source>Int Rev Law Econom</source>
                    <volume>22</volume>
                    <fpage>61</fpage>
                    <lpage>80</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Saltman1">
                <label>12</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Saltman</surname>
                            <given-names>RB</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ferroussier-Davis</surname>
                            <given-names>O</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>The concept of stewardship in health policy.</article-title>
                    <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>
                    <volume>78</volume>
                    <fpage>732</fpage>
                    <lpage>739</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Patouillard1">
                <label>13</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Patouillard</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Goodman</surname>
                            <given-names>CA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hanson</surname>
                            <given-names>KG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mills</surname>
                            <given-names>AJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Can working with the private for-profit sector improve
                        utilization of quality health services by the poor? A systematic review of
                        the literature.</article-title>
                    <source>Int J Equity Health</source>
                    <volume>6</volume>
                    <fpage>17</fpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Peters1">
                <label>14</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Peters</surname>
                            <given-names>DH</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mirchandani</surname>
                            <given-names>GG</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hansen</surname>
                            <given-names>PM</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Strategies for engaging the private sector in sexual and
                        reproductive health: how effective are they?</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>19</volume>
                    <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
                    <fpage>i5</fpage>
                    <lpage>i21</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Leonard2">
                <label>15</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Leonard</surname>
                            <given-names>DK</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <source>Africa's changing markets for health and veterinary services: the
                        new institutional issues</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>University of California Press/University of California
                        International and Area Studies Digital Collection</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Mills1">
                <label>16</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mills</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brugha</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hanson</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>McPake</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>What can be done about the private health sector in low-income
                        countries?</article-title>
                    <source>World Hosp Health Serv</source>
                    <volume>38</volume>
                    <fpage>24</fpage>
                    <lpage>30, 41–24</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Donabedian1">
                <label>17</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Donabedian</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1978</year>
                    <article-title>The quality of medical care.</article-title>
                    <source>Science</source>
                    <volume>200</volume>
                    <fpage>856</fpage>
                    <lpage>864</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-World2">
                <label>18</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization</collab>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <source>Medicines use in primary care in developing and transitional countries:
                        Fact Book summarizing results from studies reported between 1990 and
                        2006</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Berman1">
                <label>19</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Berman</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>Organization of ambulatory care provision: a critical determinant
                        of health system performance in developing countries.</article-title>
                    <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>
                    <volume>78</volume>
                    <fpage>791</fpage>
                    <lpage>802</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Bennett1">
                <label>20</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bennett</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1992</year>
                    <article-title>Promoting the private sector: a review of developing country
                        trends.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>7</volume>
                    <fpage>97</fpage>
                    <lpage>110</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-World3">
                <label>21</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization</collab>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <source>Health statistics and health information systems: service availability
                        mapping (SAM)</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Measure1">
                <label>22</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Measure</surname>
                            <given-names>DHS</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">ICF Macro</collab>
                    <year>2010</year>
                    <source>Service provision assessment (SPA) surveys</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Calverton (Maryland)</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>Measure DHS and ICF Macro</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Madden1">
                <label>23</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Madden</surname>
                            <given-names>JM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Quick</surname>
                            <given-names>JD</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ross-Degnan</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Kafle</surname>
                            <given-names>KK</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1997</year>
                    <article-title>Undercover careseekers: simulated clients in the study of health
                        provider behavior in developing countries.</article-title>
                    <source>Soc Sci Med</source>
                    <volume>45</volume>
                    <fpage>1465</fpage>
                    <lpage>1482</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-World4">
                <label>24</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization</collab>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <source>The world medicines situation</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Zurovac1">
                <label>25</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zurovac</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rowe</surname>
                            <given-names>AK</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Quality of treatment for febrile illness among children at
                        outpatient facilities in sub-Saharan Africa.</article-title>
                    <source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source>
                    <volume>100</volume>
                    <fpage>283</fpage>
                    <lpage>296</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-World5">
                <label>26</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization</collab>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <source>The world health report 2000—health systems: improving
                        performance</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Leonard3">
                <label>27</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Leonard</surname>
                            <given-names>DK</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Lessons from the new institutional economics for the structural
                        reform of human health services in Africa.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Leonard</surname>
                            <given-names>DK</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Africa's changing markets for health and veterinary services: the
                        new institutional issues</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>University of California Press/University of California
                        International and Area Studies Digital Collection</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Das1">
                <label>28</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Das</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gertler</surname>
                            <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Variations in practice quality in five low-income countries: a
                        conceptual overview.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>
                    <volume>26</volume>
                    <fpage>w296</fpage>
                    <lpage>w309</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Moher1">
                <label>29</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Moher</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Liberati</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tetzlaff</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Altman</surname>
                            <given-names>DG</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2009</year>
                    <article-title>Preferred reporting items for systematic reviews and
                        meta-analyses: the PRISMA statement.</article-title>
                    <source>PLoS Med</source>
                    <volume>6</volume>
                    <fpage>e1000097</fpage>
                    <comment>doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pmed.1000097" xlink:type="simple">10.1371/journal.pmed.1000097</ext-link></comment>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Barber1">
                <label>30</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Barber</surname>
                            <given-names>SL</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Public and private prenatal care providers in urban Mexico: how
                        does their quality compare?</article-title>
                    <source>Int J Qual Health Care</source>
                    <volume>18</volume>
                    <fpage>306</fpage>
                    <lpage>313</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Barber2">
                <label>31</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Barber</surname>
                            <given-names>SL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bertozzi</surname>
                            <given-names>SM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gertler</surname>
                            <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Variations in prenatal care quality for the rural poor in
                        Mexico.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>
                    <volume>26</volume>
                    <fpage>w310</fpage>
                    <lpage>w323</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Barber3">
                <label>32</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Barber</surname>
                            <given-names>SL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gertler</surname>
                            <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Harimurti</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Differences in access to high-quality outpatient care in
                        Indonesia.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>
                    <volume>26</volume>
                    <fpage>w352</fpage>
                    <lpage>w366</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Boller1">
                <label>33</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Boller</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wyss</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mtasiwa</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tanner</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Quality and comparison of antenatal care in public and private
                        providers in the United Republic of Tanzania.</article-title>
                    <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>
                    <volume>81</volume>
                    <fpage>116</fpage>
                    <lpage>122</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Das2">
                <label>34</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Das</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hammer</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Location, location, location: residence, wealth, and the quality
                        of medical care in Delhi, India.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>
                    <volume>26</volume>
                    <fpage>w338</fpage>
                    <lpage>w351</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Barber4">
                <label>35</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Barber</surname>
                            <given-names>SL</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gertler</surname>
                            <given-names>PJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Harimurti</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Differences in access to high-quality outpatient care in
                        Indonesia.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>
                    <volume>26</volume>
                    <fpage>w352</fpage>
                    <lpage>w366</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Nahum1">
                <label>36</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nahum</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Akogbeto</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2000</year>
                    <article-title>[Malaria and pregnancy: attitude of health care personnel
                        during prenatal care in Cotonou, Benin].</article-title>
                    <source>Med Trop (Mars)</source>
                    <volume>60</volume>
                    <fpage>251</fpage>
                    <lpage>255</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Massele1">
                <label>37</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Massele</surname>
                            <given-names>AY</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Sayi</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nsimba</surname>
                            <given-names>SE</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ofori-Adjei</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Laing</surname>
                            <given-names>RO</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1993</year>
                    <article-title>Knowledge and management of malaria in Dar es Salaam,
                        Tanzania.</article-title>
                    <source>East Afr Med J</source>
                    <volume>70</volume>
                    <fpage>639</fpage>
                    <lpage>642</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Tuan1">
                <label>38</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Tuan</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dung</surname>
                            <given-names>VT</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Neu</surname>
                            <given-names>I</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Dibley</surname>
                            <given-names>MJ</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Comparative quality of private and public health services in
                        rural Vietnam.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>20</volume>
                    <fpage>319</fpage>
                    <lpage>327</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Gilson2">
                <label>39</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Gilson</surname>
                            <given-names>L</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Alilio</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Heggenhougen</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1994</year>
                    <article-title>Community satisfaction with primary health care services: an
                        evaluation undertaken in the Morogoro region of Tanzania.</article-title>
                    <source>Soc Sci Med</source>
                    <volume>39</volume>
                    <fpage>767</fpage>
                    <lpage>780</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Lindelow1">
                <label>40</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lindelow</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Serneels</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>The performance of health workers in Ethiopia: results from
                        qualitative research.</article-title>
                    <source>Soc Sci Med</source>
                    <volume>62</volume>
                    <fpage>2225</fpage>
                    <lpage>2235</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-World6">
                <label>41</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization, Health Action International</collab>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <source>Medicine prices—a new approach to measurement</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-World7">
                <label>42</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <collab xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization</collab>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <source>WHO operational package for monitoring and assessing country
                        pharmaceutical situations</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Russell1">
                <label>43</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Russell</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Treatment-seeking behaviour in urban Sri Lanka: trusting the
                        state, trusting private providers.</article-title>
                    <source>Soc Sci Med</source>
                    <volume>61</volume>
                    <fpage>1396</fpage>
                    <lpage>1407</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Deressa1">
                <label>44</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Deressa</surname>
                            <given-names>W</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ali</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hailemariam</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>Malaria-related health-seeking behaviour and challenges for care
                        providers in rural Ethiopia: implications for control.</article-title>
                    <source>J Biosoc Sci</source>
                    <volume>40</volume>
                    <fpage>115</fpage>
                    <lpage>135</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Lewis1">
                <label>45</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lewis</surname>
                            <given-names>M</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Eskeland</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Traa-Valerezo</surname>
                            <given-names>X</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Primary health care in practice: is it effective?</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy</source>
                    <volume>70</volume>
                    <fpage>303</fpage>
                    <lpage>325</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Hoa1">
                <label>46</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hoa</surname>
                            <given-names>NQ</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ohman</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lundborg</surname>
                            <given-names>CS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Chuc</surname>
                            <given-names>NT</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2007</year>
                    <article-title>Drug use and health-seeking behavior for childhood illness in
                        Vietnam—a qualitative study.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy</source>
                    <volume>82</volume>
                    <fpage>320</fpage>
                    <lpage>329</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Turan1">
                <label>47</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Turan</surname>
                            <given-names>JM</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bulut</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nalbant</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ortayli</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Akalin</surname>
                            <given-names>AA</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>The quality of hospital-based antenatal care in
                        Istanbul.</article-title>
                    <source>Stud Fam Plann</source>
                    <volume>37</volume>
                    <fpage>49</fpage>
                    <lpage>60</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Lim1">
                <label>48</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lim</surname>
                            <given-names>MK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yang</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zhang</surname>
                            <given-names>T</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Feng</surname>
                            <given-names>W</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zhou</surname>
                            <given-names>Z</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Public perceptions of private health care in socialist
                        China.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Aff (Millwood)</source>
                    <volume>23</volume>
                    <fpage>222</fpage>
                    <lpage>234</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Paphassarang1">
                <label>49</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Paphassarang</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Philavong</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Boupha</surname>
                            <given-names>B</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Blas</surname>
                            <given-names>E</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Equity, privatization and cost recovery in urban health care: the
                        case of Lao PDR.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                    <issue>Suppl</issue>
                    <fpage>72</fpage>
                    <lpage>84</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Pongsupap1">
                <label>50</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Pongsupap</surname>
                            <given-names>Y</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Van Lerberghe</surname>
                            <given-names>W</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2006</year>
                    <article-title>Choosing between public and private or between hospital and
                        primary care: responsiveness, patient-centredness and prescribing patterns
                        in outpatient consultations in Bangkok.</article-title>
                    <source>Trop Med Int Health</source>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                    <fpage>81</fpage>
                    <lpage>89</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Siddiqi1">
                <label>51</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Siddiqi</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hamid</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rafique</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Chaudhry</surname>
                            <given-names>SA</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Ali</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <etal/>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Prescription practices of public and private health care
                        providers in Attock District of Pakistan.</article-title>
                    <source>Int J Health Plann Manage</source>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                    <fpage>23</fpage>
                    <lpage>40</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Mbanefoh1">
                <label>52</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mbanefoh</surname>
                            <given-names>GF</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Soyibo</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Anyanwu</surname>
                            <given-names>JC</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2004</year>
                    <article-title>Markets for health care in Nigeria.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Nwabu</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Wang'ombe</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Okello</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Munishi</surname>
                            <given-names>G</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Improving health policy in Africa</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Nairobi</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>University of Nairobi Press</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>431</fpage>
                    <lpage>441</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Mahaprata1">
                <label>53</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mahaprata</surname>
                            <given-names>P</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2003</year>
                    <article-title>Quality health care in private and public health care
                        institutions.</article-title>
                    <person-group person-group-type="editor">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Abdo</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Yazbeck</surname>
                            <given-names>AS</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Peters</surname>
                            <given-names>DH</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <source>Health policy research in South Asia: building capacity for
                        reform</source>
                    <publisher-loc>Washington (District of Columbia)</publisher-loc>
                    <publisher-name>World Bank</publisher-name>
                    <fpage>333</fpage>
                    <lpage>367</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Schneider1">
                <label>54</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Schneider</surname>
                            <given-names>H</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Palmer</surname>
                            <given-names>N</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2002</year>
                    <article-title>Getting to the truth? Researching user views of primary health
                        care.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>17</volume>
                    <fpage>32</fpage>
                    <lpage>41</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Strong1">
                <label>55</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Strong</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Mathers</surname>
                            <given-names>C</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Leeder</surname>
                            <given-names>S</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Beaglehole</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Preventing chronic diseases: how many lives can we
                        save?</article-title>
                    <source>Lancet</source>
                    <volume>366</volume>
                    <fpage>1578</fpage>
                    <lpage>1582</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Das3">
                <label>56</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Das</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hammer</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Leonard</surname>
                            <given-names>K</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2008</year>
                    <article-title>The quality of medical advice in low-income
                        countries.</article-title>
                    <source>J Econ Perspect</source>
                    <volume>22</volume>
                    <fpage>93</fpage>
                    <lpage>114</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Rowe1">
                <label>57</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Rowe</surname>
                            <given-names>AK</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>de Savigny</surname>
                            <given-names>D</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Lanata</surname>
                            <given-names>CF</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Victora</surname>
                            <given-names>CG</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>How can we achieve and maintain high-quality performance of
                        health workers in low-resource settings?</article-title>
                    <source>Lancet</source>
                    <volume>366</volume>
                    <fpage>1026</fpage>
                    <lpage>1035</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Bhat1">
                <label>58</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Bhat</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1996</year>
                    <article-title>Regulating the private health care sector: the case of the Indian
                        Consumer Protection Act.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>11</volume>
                    <fpage>265</fpage>
                    <lpage>279</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Brugha1">
                <label>59</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Brugha</surname>
                            <given-names>R</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Zwi</surname>
                            <given-names>A</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>1998</year>
                    <article-title>Improving the quality of private sector delivery of public health
                        services: challenges and strategies.</article-title>
                    <source>Health Policy Plan</source>
                    <volume>13</volume>
                    <fpage>107</fpage>
                    <lpage>120</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
            <ref id="pmed.1000433-Das4">
                <label>60</label>
                <element-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple">
                    <person-group person-group-type="author">
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Das</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                        <name name-style="western">
                            <surname>Hammer</surname>
                            <given-names>J</given-names>
                        </name>
                    </person-group>
                    <year>2005</year>
                    <article-title>Which doctor? Combining vignettes and item response to measure
                        clinical competence.</article-title>
                    <source>J Dev Econom</source>
                    <volume>78</volume>
                    <fpage>348</fpage>
                    <lpage>383</lpage>
                </element-citation>
            </ref>
        </ref-list>
        <glossary>
            <title>Abbreviations</title>
            <def-list>
                <def-item>
                    <term>CD</term>
                    <def>
                        <p>communicable disease</p>
                    </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                    <term>IQR</term>
                    <def>
                        <p>inter-quartile range</p>
                    </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                    <term>LMICs</term>
                    <def>
                        <p>low and middle income countries</p>
                    </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                    <term>NCD</term>
                    <def>
                        <p>non-communicable disease</p>
                    </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                    <term>NGO</term>
                    <def>
                        <p>non-governmental organization</p>
                    </def>
                </def-item>
                <def-item>
                    <term>WHO</term>
                    <def>
                        <p>World Health Organization</p>
                    </def>
                </def-item>
            </def-list>
        </glossary>
        
    </back>
</article>