<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1d3/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1d3" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title>
</journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0188041</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-17-31641</article-id>
<article-categories>
<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
<subject>Research Article</subject>
</subj-group>
<subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular structures and organelles</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell membranes</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Lipids</subject><subj-group><subject>Cholesterol</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Lipids</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular structures and organelles</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell membranes</subject><subj-group><subject>Membrane characteristics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular structures and organelles</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physics</subject><subj-group><subject>Electromagnetic radiation</subject><subj-group><subject>Luminescence</subject><subj-group><subject>Fluorescence</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Membrane trafficking</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Physical sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Physics</subject><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Membrane order in the plasma membrane and endocytic recycling compartment</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Membrane order in the plasma membrane and endocytic recycling compartment</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Iaea</surname>
<given-names>David B.</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Funding acquisition</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Validation</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Visualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – review &amp; editing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="fn" rid="currentaff001"><sup>¤</sup></xref>
</contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Maxfield</surname>
<given-names>Frederick R.</given-names>
</name>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Resources</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – original draft</role>
<role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing – review &amp; editing</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff001"><label>1</label> <addr-line>Department of Biochemistry, Weill Cornell Medical College, New York, NY, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff002"><label>2</label> <addr-line>Weill Cornell Medical College, Rockefeller University, and Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center Tri-Institutional Chemical Biology Program, New York, NY, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple">
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Caplan</surname>
<given-names>Steve</given-names>
</name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/>
</contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>University of Nebraska Medical Center, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001">
<p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p>
</fn>
<fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001">
<label>¤</label>
<p>Current address: Genentech, South San Francisco, CA, United States of America</p>
</fn>
<corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">frmaxfie@med.cornell.edu</email></corresp>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="epub">
<day>10</day>
<month>11</month>
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="collection">
<year>2017</year>
</pub-date>
<volume>12</volume>
<issue>11</issue>
<elocation-id>e0188041</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received">
<day>28</day>
<month>8</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
<date date-type="accepted">
<day>31</day>
<month>10</month>
<year>2017</year>
</date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Iaea, Maxfield</copyright-holder>
<license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">
<license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p>
</license>
</permissions>
<self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0188041"/>
<abstract>
<p>The cholesterol content of membranes plays an important role in organizing membranes for signal transduction and protein trafficking as well as in modulating the biophysical properties of membranes. While the properties of model or isolated membranes have been extensively studied, there has been little evaluation of internal membranes in living cells. Here, we use a Nile Red based probe, NR12S, and ratiometric live cell imaging, to analyze the membrane order of the plasma membrane and endocytic recycling compartment. We find that after a brief incubation to allow endocytosis, NR12S is distributed between the plasma membrane and the endocytic recycling compartment. The NR12S reports that the endocytic recycling compartment is more highly ordered than the plasma membrane. We also find that the plasma membrane and the endocytic recycling compartment are differentially affected by altering cellular cholesterol levels. The membrane order of the plasma membrane, but not the endocytic recycling compartment, is altered significantly when cellular cholesterol content is increased or decreased by 20%. These results demonstrate that changes in cellular cholesterol differentially alter membrane order within different organelles.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group>
<award-group id="award001">
<funding-source>
<institution>NIDDK</institution>
</funding-source>
<award-id>F31-DK104631</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Iaea</surname>
<given-names>David B.</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<award-group id="award002">
<funding-source>
<institution>NIDDK</institution>
</funding-source>
<award-id>R37-DK27083</award-id>
<principal-award-recipient>
<name name-style="western">
<surname>Maxfield</surname>
<given-names>Frederick R.</given-names>
</name>
</principal-award-recipient>
</award-group>
<funding-statement>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grants F31-DK104631 (DBI) and R37-DK27083 (FRM). The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement>
</funding-group>
<counts>
<fig-count count="3"/>
<table-count count="0"/>
<page-count count="8"/>
</counts>
<custom-meta-group>
<custom-meta id="data-availability">
<meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name>
<meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value>
</custom-meta>
</custom-meta-group>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<sec id="sec001" sec-type="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>The structure and function of cellular membranes is largely dictated by their lipid composition, including the amount of cholesterol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref001">1</xref>]. Cholesterol is heterogeneously distributed among cellular organelles but is highly enriched in the plasma membrane (PM) and endocytic recycling compartment (ERC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref002">2</xref>]. In membranes, cholesterol interacts with the acyl chains and headgroups of surrounding lipids resulting in an increase in local membrane rigidity or order, and cholesterol depletion results in a decrease in local membrane order [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref003">3</xref>]. Cellular membranes are composed of hundreds of different lipids that vary in head group, acyl chain length and saturation level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref004">4</xref>]. Additionally, lipids are non-randomly distributed in membranes and vary between the leaflets of the bilayer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref005">5</xref>].</p>
<p>In recent years, there has been a growing interest in examining the membrane order of biological membranes in living cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref006">6</xref>]. Environmentally-sensitive probes, such as Laurdan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref007">7</xref>], have been used to report local fluidity. However, due to the rapid redistribution of Laurdan among membranes, its application to studies of endosomal membranes has been limited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref008">8</xref>].</p>
<p>Recently the Nile Red based probe, NR12S, has been developed and used to report the membrane order of the PM in living cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref009">9</xref>]. NR12S has a Nile Red-like moiety that is anchored in membranes by a long alkyl chain with a zwitterionic headgroup and does not flip across the bilayer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref009">9</xref>]. NR12S allows for accurate measurements of membrane order [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref009">9</xref>], probably due to effects of water permeation on the spectroscopic properties of the fluorophore. In contrast to the PM, little is known about the biophysical properties of most intracellular membranes, including the ERC, which is part of the recycling itinerary for membrane proteins such as the transferrin receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref010">10</xref>]. We have shown that fluorescent lipid analogs that, like NR12S, do not flip in the bilayer rapidly can be delivered to the ERC within a few minutes by nonselective endocytosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref011">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref013">13</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0188041.g001">Fig 1A</xref>). In this study, we utilized the NR12S probe and ratiometric live cell imaging to monitor the membrane order of the PM and ERC, and we found that the ERC is more highly ordered than the PM. The membrane order of the PM appears to be altered to a greater extent than the ERC by changes in the cellular cholesterol content. These results indicate that cellular organelles differentially regulate their membrane order in response to alterations in cellular cholesterol levels.</p>
<fig id="pone.0188041.g001" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0188041.g001</object-id>
<label>Fig 1</label>
<caption>
<title>NR12S distributes between the PM and ERC.</title>
<p>(A) Receptor-mediated endocytic pathway in non-polarized mammalian cells. Transferrin and its receptor are shown as an example. EE, early endosome; SE, sorting endosome; ERC, endocytic recycling compartment; LE, late endosome. (B) Representative maximum projection images of NR12S labeling in U2OS-SRA cells. The ERC is labeled with Alexa405-Tf. Scale bar is 10 μm.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0188041.g001" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
</sec>
<sec id="sec002" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and methods</title>
<sec id="sec003" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials</title>
<p>Alexa labeling kits were purchased from ThermoFisher. Human Transferrin (Tf) was purchased from Sigma. All tissue culture supplies were purchased from Invitrogen. All other chemicals were from Sigma. The medium used are as follows: Medium 2 (150mM NaCl, 5mM KCl, 1mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 20mM HEPES, pH 7.4); M2glucose (Medium 2 containing 2mg/mL glucose).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec004">
<title>Cell culture</title>
<p>U2OS-SRA is a modified human osteosarcoma cell line that expresses the scavenger receptor A (SRA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref014">14</xref>]. U2OS-SRA cells were grown at 37°C in a 5% CO2 humidified incubator and in McCoys 5A medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum, 1mg/mL geneticin as a selection for SRA, 100 units/mL penicillin, 100ug/mL streptomycin. Cells for confocal microscopy were plated on 35-mm plastic dishes, the bottoms of which were replaced with poly-D-lysine-coated coverslips. Cells were plated at 50–60% confluence for all experiments.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec005">
<title>Cholesterol modulation</title>
<p>U2OS-SRA cells were grown for 24 hours in cholesterol depletion medium (McCoys 5A medium similar to the growth medium but with 5% lipoprotein-deficient serum in place of fetal bovine serum, supplemented with 10 μM mevastatin). To overload cholesterol, U2OS-SRA cells were grown for 24 hours in metabolic overloading medium (McCoys 5A medium growth medium supplemented with 50 μg/mL acetylated-LDL and 30 μg Sandoz 58035).</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec006">
<title>Free cholesterol measurement by GC/MS</title>
<p>Cellular lipids were extracted twice with hexane/2-propanol (3:2). During the first extraction, β-sitosterol was added as an internal standard for quantification. Dried lipids were resuspended in hexane and separated on a Varian Factor Four capillary column, using a Varian 400 GC/MS/MS system (14). The protein concentration after solubilization with 0.5 M NaOH was determined by the BCA protein assay.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec007">
<title>Fluorescence labeling</title>
<p>Human transferrin (Sigma) was iron-loaded and purified by Sephacryl S-300 (Pharmacia LKB) gel-filtration chromatography and conjugated to Alexa405 according to the manufacturer's instruction. To label cells with transferrin, cells were incubated with 20 μg/mL Alexa405–transferrin for 15 min at 37°C in M2glucose medium. NR12S was freshly prepared in M2glucose medium and then added to the cells at a final concentration of 0.3 μM. Cells were incubated for 7 min at 37°C in the dark. Following labeling, cells were washed and imaged in M2glcuose medium.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec008">
<title>Fluorescence microscopy</title>
<p>Cells were imaged on a Zeiss LSM 880, AxioObserver microscope equipped with a Plan-Apochromat 63× Oil 1.4 NA differential interference contrast (DIC) M27 objective in a humidified chamber at 37°C. Z-stacks were obtained using a step size of 0.31 μm. NR12S was excited using 514 nm laser and images corresponding to the green (520–580 nm) and red (585–650 nm) were recorded simultaneously using emission filters.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec009">
<title>NR12S image analysis</title>
<p>NR12S intensity in the plasma membrane and endocytic recycling compartment were measured in individual planes. Image planes were selected such that the plasma membrane or endocytic recycling compartment was the primary source of NR12S fluorescence. For the plasma membrane, peripheral regions of the cell were analyzed to exclude the endocytic recycling compartment fluorescence that was visible in the plasma membrane sections. All data were analyzed with MetaMorph image analysis software (Molecular Devices, Downingtown, PA).</p>
</sec>
</sec>
<sec id="sec010" sec-type="conclusions">
<title>Results and discussion</title>
<sec id="sec011">
<title>NR12S labels the PM and ERC</title>
<p>The fluorescence emission of NR12S is sensitive to the membrane environment. In more ordered membranes, NR12S fluorescence emission is blue shifted, while in disordered membranes the fluorescence emission spectra is red shifted (9). These alterations in the emission properties of NR12S allow for ratiometric green/red imaging to determine relative membrane order in cells. In this study, we modulated cholesterol levels using metabolic methods by growing human osteosarcoma cells (U2OS) stably expressing the scavenger receptor A (U20S-SRA cells) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref014">14</xref>] in either lipoprotein deficient serum with the HMG-CoA reductase inhibitor mevastatin, or in medium supplemented with acetylated low density lipoprotein, which binds to SRA, and an acyl-CoA:cholesterol acyltransferase inhibitor, Sandoz 58–035 (see details in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec002">Materials and Methods</xref>). A previous study used cyclodextrin treatment to reduce cholesterol levels, but did not report the extent of cholesterol reduction (9).</p>
<p>To determine the cellular distribution of NR12S, we labeled the outer leaflet of the PM of living U2OS-SRA cells with 0.3 μM NR12S as described by Kucherak et al.[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref009">9</xref>]. After brief incubations, NR12S, like other fluorescent lipid analogs that do not flip spontaneously in the bilayer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref011">11</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref013">13</xref>], is delivered to the ERC by endocytic processes, where it co-localizes with endocytosed transferrin (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0188041.g001">Fig 1</xref>). As the PM and ERC are highly enriched in cholesterol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref002">2</xref>], we sought to analyze how the membrane order of these compartments changes following modulation of cellular cholesterol levels.</p>
</sec>
<sec id="sec012">
<title>Monitoring membrane order in living cells</title>
<p>To modulate cellular cholesterol levels, we cultured U2OS-SRA cells under cholesterol depletion and cholesterol overloading conditions. Overnight cholesterol depletion resulted in a ~20% decrease in cellular cholesterol levels, while overloading increased cholesterol by ~20% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0188041.g002">Fig 2</xref>). Using NR12S, we monitored changes in the membrane order of the PM and ERC following cholesterol modulation. Under all conditions, NR12S was distributed between the PM and ERC in U2OS-SRA cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0188041.g003">Fig 3A</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone.0188041.g002" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0188041.g002</object-id>
<label>Fig 2</label>
<caption>
<title>Metabolic modulation of cellular cholesterol levels.</title>
<p>GC/MS measurement of free cholesterol levels in control, cholesterol depleted and overloaded U2OS-SRA cells. Cellular lipids were extracted and analyzed by GC/MS. Data represent averages (± SE) of three independent experiments normalized to control value. ** p &lt; 0.01.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0188041.g002" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<fig id="pone.0188041.g003" position="float">
<object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0188041.g003</object-id>
<label>Fig 3</label>
<caption>
<title/>
<p>(A) Representative maximum projection images of NR12S labeling in control, cholesterol depleted, and cholesterol overloaded U2OS cells. Scale bar is 10 μm. (B) Representative planes used in the analysis of NR12S fluorescence intensity in the PM, ERC and Cell contact regions. Areas of cell contact points used in analysis are boxed. Scale bar is 10 μm. (C) Analysis of NR12S green/red ratio of the ERC and plasma membrane. NR12S green/red ratio was normalized to control PM. Data represent averages (± SE) of four independent experiments of at least 15 cells per experiment; NS, non-significant; *** p &lt; 0.001 compared to control PM.</p>
</caption>
<graphic mimetype="image" position="float" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0188041.g003" xlink:type="simple"/>
</fig>
<p>To analyze the green/red ratio of NR12S fluorescence in the PM and ERC, we collected a confocal stack of cells labeled with NR12S using a single excitation wavelength, and the emission for the green (ordered) and red (disordered) was collected simultaneously using emission filters (see details in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec002">Materials and Methods</xref>). The green/red ratio of NR12S for the PM and ERC as well as cell-cell contact points was determined using single planes where the fluorescence from the ERC, the PM, and PM at contact regions could be isolated from one another (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0188041.g003">Fig 3B</xref>). Because we are measuring fluorescence ratio values, variations in intensity due to the amount of dye do not affect the measurement. Comparing the NR12S green/red ratio of the ERC to the PM in control cells shows that the ERC has a green/red ratio about 40% higher than the PM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0188041.g003">Fig 3C</xref>). This indicates that the ERC membrane is more ordered than the PM.</p>
<p>Analysis of the cholesterol depleted or overloaded U2OS-SRA cells shows that there was an alteration to the membrane order of the PM (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0188041.g003">Fig 3C</xref>). In the PM, NR12S green and red signal showed that following cholesterol depletion, NR12S PM emission was red shifted with a ~20% decrease in the NR12S green/red ratio, compared to control U2OS-SRA cells. This shift is consistent with a decrease in cellular cholesterol content and a reduction in membrane order [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref009">9</xref>]. Additionally, cholesterol overloading resulted in an increase in membrane order and a blue shift of NR12S. Consistent with these observations, measurements of cell-cell contact points from cholesterol depleted or overloaded cells demonstrated a similar shift in membrane order as the bulk plasma membrane measurement. We note that under our culture conditions (50–60% confluency), every cell we used for measurements was touching at least one other cells. We did not observe any dependence of the green/red ratio in the contact regions on the extent of cell-cell contact.</p>
<p>In the ERC, there was a small decrease in the green/red ratio when cholesterol was depleted (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0188041.g003">Fig 3C</xref>), but this difference did not reach statistical significance based on four experiments. The green/red ratio in the ERC was virtually unchanged upon cholesterol overloading. These data indicate that effects of alterations in cholesterol have a smaller effect on membrane order in the ERC than in the PM.</p>
<p>Cellular organelles are composed of complex mixtures of lipids that modulate their biophysical properties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref001">1</xref>]. Unfortunately, the membrane composition of the ERC has not been well documented owing to difficulties of organelle purification. The abundance of cholesterol in the ERC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref002">2</xref>] would be consistent with the membranes being highly ordered. Previous work has shown that GPI-anchored proteins are retained longer in the ERC compared to either the transferrin receptor or fluorescent lipid analogs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref011">11</xref>], indicating that the ERC is highly ordered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref015">15</xref>].</p>
<p>The retention of GPI-anchored proteins in the ERC was abolished when cellular cholesterol levels were reduced by ~ 50%. In the current study, when cholesterol levels are altered by ~20%, we observe that the membrane order of the PM, but not the ERC, is altered by modulation of cellular cholesterol levels. This indicates that the membrane properties of the PM are more influenced by changes in cholesterol than those of the ERC. Interestingly, it was shown recently that the effect of cholesterol on ordered lipid domain formation is dependent upon the phospholipid composition of the membranes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref016">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0188041.ref017">17</xref>]. The retention of cholesterol and increased membrane order of the ERC implies that lipids may be differentially distributed between the PM and ERC. Enrichment of specific lipids, including cholesterol, in these organelles likely defines their unique biophysical properties.</p>
</sec>
</sec>
</body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grants F31-DK104631 (DBI) and R37-DK27083 (FRM). We thank Andrey S. Klymenchko (CNRS, Strasbourg) for providing the NR12S probe and technical guidance. We would also like to thank Natalya Gertsik and Frederik Wendelboe Lund for critical reading of this manuscript.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeagle</surname> <given-names>PL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cholesterol and the cell membrane</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>822</volume>(<issue>3–4</issue>):<fpage>267</fpage>–<lpage>87</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">3904832</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>SX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Karylowski</surname> <given-names>OJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wustner</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGraw</surname> <given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maxfield</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Vesicular and non-vesicular sterol transport in living cells. The endocytic recycling compartment is a major sterol storage organelle</article-title>. <source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>277</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>609</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M108861200" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M108861200</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11682487</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>London</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Insolubility of lipids in triton X-100: physical origin and relationship to sphingolipid/cholesterol membrane domains (rafts)</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>1508</volume>(<issue>1–2</issue>):<fpage>182</fpage>–<lpage>95</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">11090825</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iaea</surname> <given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maxfield</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cholesterol trafficking and distribution</article-title>. <source>Essays in biochemistry</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>43</fpage>–<lpage>55</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1042/bse0570043" xlink:type="simple">10.1042/bse0570043</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">25658343</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondal</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mesmin</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maxfield</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sterols are mainly in the cytoplasmic leaflet of the plasma membrane and the endocytic recycling compartment in CHO cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>581</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1091/mbc.E08-07-0785" xlink:type="simple">10.1091/mbc.E08-07-0785</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">19019985</object-id>; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC2626560.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klymchenko</surname> <given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kreder</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>Fluorescent probes for lipid rafts: from model membranes to living cells</article-title>. <source>Chem Biol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>97</fpage>–<lpage>113</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chembiol.2013.11.009" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.chembiol.2013.11.009</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">24361047</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bagatolli</surname> <given-names>LA</given-names></name>. <article-title>To see or not to see: lateral organization of biological membranes and fluorescence microscopy</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>1758</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1541</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bbamem.2006.05.019" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.bbamem.2006.05.019</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">16854370</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Millard</surname> <given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wuskell</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loew</surname> <given-names>LM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cholesterol-enriched lipid domains can be visualized by di-4-ANEPPDHQ with linear and nonlinear optics</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>89</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>L04</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1529/biophysj.105.064816" xlink:type="simple">10.1529/biophysj.105.064816</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">15879475</object-id>; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC1366585.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kucherak</surname> <given-names>OA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oncul</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Darwich</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yushchenko</surname> <given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arntz</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Didier</surname> <given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Switchable nile red-based probe for cholesterol and lipid order at the outer leaflet of biomembranes</article-title>. <source>J Am Chem Soc</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>132</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>4907</fpage>–<lpage>16</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1021/ja100351w" xlink:type="simple">10.1021/ja100351w</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">20225874</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hao</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maxfield</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Effects of cholesterol depletion and increased lipid unsaturation on the properties of endocytic membranes</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>279</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>14171</fpage>–<lpage>8</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M309793200" xlink:type="simple">10.1074/jbc.M309793200</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">14734557</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayor</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sabharanjak</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maxfield</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cholesterol-dependent retention of GPI-anchored proteins in endosomes</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>4626</fpage>–<lpage>38</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1093/emboj/17.16.4626" xlink:type="simple">10.1093/emboj/17.16.4626</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">9707422</object-id>; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC1170792.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mukherjee</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soe</surname> <given-names>TT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maxfield</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Endocytic sorting of lipid analogues differing solely in the chemistry of their hydrophobic tails</article-title>. <source>The Journal of cell biology</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>144</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1271</fpage>–<lpage>84</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">10087269</object-id>; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC2150570.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mayor</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Presley</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maxfield</surname> <given-names>FR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sorting of membrane components from endosomes and subsequent recycling to the cell surface occurs by a bulk flow process</article-title>. <source>The Journal of cell biology</source>. <year>1993</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1257</fpage>–<lpage>69</lpage>. <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">8509447</object-id>; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC2119709.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pipalia</surname> <given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Subramanian</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mao</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ralph</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutt</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname> <given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Histone deacetylase inhibitors correct the cholesterol storage defect in most NPC1 mutant cells</article-title>. <source>Journal of lipid research</source>. <year>2017</year>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1194/jlr.M072140" xlink:type="simple">10.1194/jlr.M072140</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">28193631</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Refaei</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leventis</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silvius</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessment of the roles of ordered lipid microdomains in post-endocytic trafficking of glycosyl-phosphatidylinositol-anchored proteins in mammalian fibroblasts</article-title>. <source>Traffic</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1012</fpage>–<lpage>24</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1600-0854.2011.01206.x" xlink:type="simple">10.1111/j.1600-0854.2011.01206.x</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">21696526</object-id>.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>London</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>New Insights into How Cholesterol and Unsaturation Control Lipid Domain Formation</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>465</fpage>–<lpage>6</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2016.06.037" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.bpj.2016.06.037</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27508431</object-id>; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC4982935.</mixed-citation></ref>
<ref id="pone.0188041.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Engberg</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hautala</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yasuda</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dehio</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murata</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slotte</surname> <given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>The Affinity of Cholesterol for Different Phospholipids Affects Lateral Segregation in Bilayers</article-title>. <source>Biophys J</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>546</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bpj.2016.06.036" xlink:type="simple">10.1016/j.bpj.2016.06.036</ext-link></comment> <object-id pub-id-type="pmid">27508438</object-id>; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC4982936.</mixed-citation></ref>
</ref-list>
</back>
</article>