<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-28593</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107916</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular types</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Stem cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Hematopoietic progenitor cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Prep1 (pKnox1) Regulates Mouse Embryonic HSC Cycling and Self-Renewal Affecting the Stat1-Sca1 IFN-Dependent Pathway</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Prep1 Regulates Fetal HSC Cycling and Self-Renewal</alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Modica</surname><given-names>Livia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iotti</surname><given-names>Giorgio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>D’Avola</surname><given-names>Annalisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blasi</surname><given-names>Francesco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Istituto FIRC di Oncologia Molecolare (IFOM), Milan, Italy</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bunting</surname><given-names>Kevin D.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Emory University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">francesco.blasi@ifom.eu</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: LM FB. Performed the experiments: LM AD. Analyzed the data: LM GI FB. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: LM FB.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>9</issue>
<elocation-id>e107916</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Modica et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>A hypomorphic <italic>Prep1</italic> mutation results in embryonic lethality at late gestation with a pleiotropic embryonic phenotype that includes defects in all hematopoietic lineages. Reduced functionality of the hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) compartment might be responsible for the hematopoietic phenotype observed at mid-gestation. In this paper we demonstrate that Prep1 regulates the number of HSCs in fetal livers (FLs), their clonogenic potential and their ability to <italic>de novo</italic> generate the hematopoietic system in ablated hosts. Furthermore, we show that Prep1 controls the self-renewal ability of the FL HSC compartment as demonstrated by serial transplantation experiments. The premature exhaustion of Prep1 mutant HSCs correlates with the reduced quiescent stem cell pool thus suggesting that Prep1 regulates the self-renewal ability by controlling the quiescence/proliferation balance. Finally, we show that in FL HSCs Prep1 absence induces the interferon signaling pathway leading to premature cycling and exhaustion of fetal HSCs.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the AIRC (Associazione Italiana Ricerche sul Cancro) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.airc.it" xlink:type="simple">http://www.airc.it</ext-link>), grants 8929 and 12829. The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Hematopoiesis is the production of blood cells in the embryo and throughout adult life. Hematopoietic stem cells (HSCs) produce and replace mature blood cells through self-renewal and differentiation. During embryonic development hematopoiesis occurs step-wise in different embryonic sites: in the yolk sac around E7, in the aorta-gonad mesonephros (AGM) at E10.5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Medvinsky1">[1]</xref> and from E11 in the fetal liver (FL). At mid-late gestation in FL, HSCs undergo a massive expansion generating the stem cell pool that will contribute to mature blood cells during entire life. Around birth HSCs move to the bone marrow (BM) where they reside mainly in a quiescent state during adult life <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ema1">[2]</xref>. Intrinsic factors, such as transcription factors and chromatin modifiers, and extrinsic microenvironmental factors encircling the HSCs modulate their activity during both embryonic and adult life <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Orkin1">[3]</xref>. The BM niche and the factors controlling adult HSCs have been extensively studied <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Calvi1">[4]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Yoshihara1">[9]</xref>, but developmental mediators of HSCs biology remain largely unknown. Identifying the mechanisms regulating HSCs during development is crucial since often cells undergoing malignant transformation reacquire properties distinctive of stem cells during developmental stages <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Jiang1">[10]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Clevers1">[14]</xref>. Thus the molecular details of fetal HSCs may be critical for further elucidation of HSCs malignancy and possible new targets for cancer therapy. Finally, factors regulating expansion and proliferation of FL HSCs might help developing protocols for <italic>ex vivo</italic> expansion of HSCs for clinical applications.</p>
<p>Prep1 is a TALE family homeodomain transcription factor and plays an essential role in embryonic development <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Longobardi1">[15]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-FernandezDiaz1">[19]</xref>. <italic>Prep1<sup>−/−</sup></italic> embryos die before gastrulation around E6.25 due to p53-dependent apoptosis of epiblast cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-FernandezDiaz1">[19]</xref>. A hypomorphic <italic>Prep1</italic> (<italic>Prep1<sup>i</sup></italic>) mutation that causes the expression of 3 to 10% of Prep1 protein induces later embryonic lethality around E17.5 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ferretti2">[20]</xref>. However, one quarter of these hypomorphs escape embryonic death and are important for identifying adult biological functions of <italic>Prep1</italic>. Prep1 acts as a tumor suppressor controlling genome stability and is an essential regulator of hematopoietic differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Longobardi2">[21]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Iotti2">[23]</xref>. Prep1 controls both myeloid and lymphoid differentiation as <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL cells generate less CFU-GEMM colonies and differentiate less B cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-DiRosa1">[24]</xref>. The thymus of adult <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> mice is underdeveloped and the T cell lineage is compromised <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Penkov1">[25]</xref>. All these features of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL and BM can be reproduced by transplanting FL cells into ablated hosts. <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL cells compete inefficiently with wild-type (wt) cells in competitive repopulation assays suggesting a defect in the HSC compartment <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-DiRosa1">[24]</xref>. However, how Prep1 affects HSCs biology and which HSCs properties are regulated remain unanswered.</p>
<p>We now demonstrate that Prep1 regulates the number of HSCs in FLs as well as their functionality to <italic>de novo</italic> generate the hematopoietic system in ablated hosts. Prep1 controls self-renewal of the FL HSC compartment and governs the balance between quiescent and proliferating fetal HSCs. The absence of Prep1 derepresses the interferon (IFN) signaling pathway, Stat1 is activated and FL HSCs cycle more frequently. We also identify Prep1 target genes likely mediating these effects.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="methods">
<title>Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Mice</title>
<p>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup> have been described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Iotti2">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Khn1">[26]</xref>. Congenic CD45.1 mice (B6.SJL-Ptprc Pepc/BoyCrl; Ly5.1) were purchased from Charles River. All animal experiments were performed in accordance with Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of IFOM and approved by the Italian Ministry of Health (project #110/11). Animals were kept on a 12/12-h light/dark cycle (lights on at 07∶00 h) with free access to food and water. All animal handlings (transplantation, sacrifice etc.,) were in accordance with the guidelines established by EU (directive 2010/63/EU). Topical anesthesia (ELMA cream) applied to the site 30 minutes prior to intravenous injection of cells. Mice were sacrificed by carbon dioxide euthanasia.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>Cells</title>
<p>Cell suspensions were obtained from E14.5 FLs as already described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Morrison1">[27]</xref>. BM cells were harvested by flushing femurs and tibias in PBS with 2% heat inactivated fetal bovine serum (staining buffer). Peripheral blood (PB) was obtained by tail bleeding. EML1 cells were the kind gift of Dr. Schickwann Tsai and were cultured as described <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Tsai1">[28]</xref>. pLKO.1 vectors encoding shRNA targeting murine Prep1 or nontargeting control were obtained from Sigma (St Louis, MO). Lentiviral infection was obtained by 2 cycles of spinoculation (1800 rpm, 45 minutes per cycle).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Flow cytometry</title>
<p>Stainings of surface markers were performed in staining buffer with the following conjugated monoclonal antibodies purchased from BD (BD Pharmingen) or eBioscience: Gr1 (RB6-8C5), B220 (RA3-6B2), Ter119 (TER-119), CD3e (145-2C11), Mac1 (M1/70), Sca1 (D7 or E13–161.7), cKit (2B8), AA4.1 (AA4.1), CD41 (MWReg30), CD48 (HM48-I), CD150 (mShad150), Il7R (SB/199), CD45.2 (104), CD45.1 (A20). The lineage cocktail (Lin) was composed of Gr1, B220, CD3e and Ter119. Mac1 was included only in the Lin used for BM cells. Stainings of intracellular markers were performed as follows: after surface marker staining, cells were fixed and permeabilised by Cytofix/Cytoperm kit (BD) and stained for pSTAT1 (#9271, Cell signaling) or Ki67 (#51-36524, BD) for 45 min. Then, fluorochrome-conjugated secondary antibodies were added. For cell cycle staining Hoechst33342 (1 µg/mL, Sigma) was added to stain DNA. Apoptosis staining was performed using AnnxinV Binding Buffer (BD), FITC-AnnexinV (Sigma) according to the manufacture’s protocol. Stained cells were analyzed by FACSCalibur (BD Biosciences) or FACSCantoII (BD Biosciences). Cell sorting was performed by FACSAria (BD Biosciences). CellQuest, Diva and FlowJo (Tree Star) software were used for data acquisition and analyses.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2d">
<title>Long Term Culture-Initiating Cell (LTC-IC) assay</title>
<p>A feeder layer of freshly isolated wt BM cells was established plating 3×10<sup>5</sup> cells/well (96 well plate). Cells were cultured in MyeloCult (Stem Cell Technologies) supplemented with 10<sup>−6</sup> M Hydrocortisone (Sigma). Proliferation was blocked by X-Ray irradiation (15 gray) at 70–80% confluency. HSCs purified from FLs were plated on the established feeder layer as specified in the text. Cultures were kept for 5 weeks in MyeloCult and then transferred into 35 mm plates in methylcellulose (MethoCult, Stem Cell Technologies). Colonies were scored after 12 days.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2e">
<title>Transplantation assays</title>
<p>8 to 12 weeks old CD45.1 mice were lethally irradiated with a 6.5 gray dose of X-rays (experimentally determined as minimal lethal dose). Four hours after irradiation, unfractionated or purified FL cells (CD45.2) in competition with BM cells were injected into the tail vain of CD45.1 mice. The injected cell doses are indicated in the text for each transplantation. For secondary and tertiary transplantations, 2×10<sup>6</sup> unfractionated BM cells were collected from recipients and injected into the tail vain of new hosts. Repopulation activity was evaluated by repopulating units (RU) as follows: RU = (%chimerism)×(n. competitors cells/10<sup>5</sup>)/(100–%chimerism) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ema2">[29]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2f">
<title>Real-Time quantitative PCR</title>
<p>HSCs were sorted from Prep1<sup>+/+</sup> and Prep1<sup>i/i</sup> FLs and kept on ice. Cell lysis, RNA extraction, reverse transcription and pre-amplification were performed by Taqman kit #4387299 (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Taqman Assays-on-demand were purchased from Life Technologies.</p>
<p>Each PCR reaction was run in triplicate and GAPDH was used as housekeeping gene. Real-time PCRs were carried out on the ABI/Prism 7900 HT Sequence Detector System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA).</p>
</sec><sec id="s2g">
<title>Statistical analysis</title>
<p>Values are expressed as mean and error bars represent SEM. The significance of differences was determined by two-tailed Student’s t test. Pvalue (p) ≤0.05 were considered significant (*p≤0.05; **p≤0.01; ***p≤0.001).</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Prep1 regulates the number of functional HSCs in E14.5 FLs</title>
<p>To investigate how Prep1 regulates the stem and progenitor compartments during development, we used E14.5 <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL cells. Initially we determined the immunophenotype of stem and progenitors populations in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FLs in comparison to wt controls. The Lin<sup>−</sup>Sca1<sup>+</sup>cKit<sup>+</sup> (L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>) population, mainly enriched in progenitors and to a lesser extent in stem cells, showed a 2-fold increase in Prep1 deficient embryos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g001">Figure 1A</xref>). Further dissection of the L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> population with the CD150, CD48 and CD41 markers revealed a 50% reduction in the frequency of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> cells that express stem markers (CD150<sup>+</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup>) compared to the wt counterpart (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). From now on and throughout the paper we will refer to the L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup> cells as HSC as they represent an almost pure HSC population <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Kim1">[30]</xref>. The absolute number of the <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs was similar to the wt because of the relative expansion of the L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g001">Figure 1B</xref>). Importantly Prep1 is expressed in the HSC compartment (see below).</p>
<fig id="pone-0107916-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Prep1 affects stem and progenitors compartments in E14.5 FLs.</title>
<p>(A–D) Representative FACS analyses of <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FLs are shown on the left. Graphs describing percentage and absolute numbers are reported on the right. Numbers in the FACS plots indicate the percentage of cells in parental gates. (A) Lin<sup>−</sup>Sca1<sup>+</sup>cKit<sup>+</sup> population is shown. FACS plots are referred to Lineage<sup>−</sup> gate (n = 8 for each genotype; % L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> p = 0.01; # L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> p = 0.01). (B) HSC population is identified as L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup> CD41<sup>−</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>. FACS plots are referred to L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> gate (n = 8 for each genotype; % HSCs p = 0.0000056; # HSCs p = not significant). (C) CLPs are identified as Lin<sup>−</sup>Il7R<sup>+</sup>Sca1<sup>int</sup>ckit<sup>int</sup>. FACS plots are referred to Lin<sup>−</sup>Il7R<sup>+</sup> gate. (n = 4 for each genotype; % CLPs p = 0.00014; # CLPs p = 0.00023). (D) FACS plots regarding myeloid progenitors refer to Lin<sup>−</sup>Sca1<sup>−</sup>ckit<sup>hi</sup> gate. GMPs are FcγR<sup>+</sup>CD34<sup>+</sup> (n = 4 for each genotype; % GMPs p = 0.05; # GMPs p = 0.07); CMPs are FcγR<sup>int</sup>CD34<sup>+/l</sup>°<sup>w</sup> (n = 4 for each genotype; % CMPs p = 0.005; # CMPs p = 0.007); MEPs are FcγR<sup>−</sup>CD34<sup>−</sup> (n = 4 for each genotype; % MEPs p = not significant; # MEPs p = not significant).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We also analyzed lymphoid and myeloid committed progenitor populations. <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> common lymphoid progenitors (CLPs) showed a statistically significant 3.3 fold increase compared to wt controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). Conversely, common myeloid progenitors (CMPs) and granulocyte/macrophage progenitors (GMPs) were reduced in frequency and absolute number when Prep1 was underexpressed (58% and 38% reduction, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g001">Figure 1D</xref>). These data indicate a role for Prep1 in regulating the first steps of the hematopoietic differentiation during fetal development, from stem cells to lineage-primed progenitors, and that Prep1 exerts a peculiar differentiation stage-specific function.</p>
<p>To functionally characterize the impact of Prep1 on HSCs we investigated their ability to form colonies <italic>in vitro</italic> in LTC-IC assay. We tested the HSC population (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g001">Fig. 1B</xref>) and the L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>AA4.1<sup>+</sup> cells (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107916.s001">Figure S1</xref>). The latter is another cell population enriched for HSCs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Hsu1">[31]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Petrenko1">[32]</xref>. Comparing the numbers of scored colonies at all plated cell doses, a strong decrease in the clonogenic potential of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> stem/progenitor cells was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g002">figures 2A and 2B</xref>). This agrees with our previous finding that myeloid, erythroid and immature CFU colonies were reduced in the absence of Prep1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-DiRosa1">[24]</xref>. Hypomorphic <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> generated smaller colonies in comparison to wt cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g002">Figure 2C</xref>). Thus, Prep1 acts on the functionality of stem/progenitor cells.</p>
<fig id="pone-0107916-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>Impaired clonogenic activity of Prep1 deficient stem cell populations.</title>
<p>(A) LTC-IC assay was performed plating 100, 300 or 500 L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>A<sup>+</sup> cells purified from <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FLs. Mean value of scored colonies after 12 days in methylcellulose at each cell dose are shown (n = 9 at each cell dose for each genotype; 500 L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>A<sup>+</sup> p = 0.003, 300 and 100 L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>A<sup>+</sup> p = not significant). (B) LTC-IC was performed with 50, 100, 200 L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup> CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup> from both genotypes and colonies scored after 12 days in methylcellulose. (n = 4 at each cell dose for each genotype; 200 cells p = 0.001, 100 cells p = 0.01, 50 cells p = not significant). (C) Representative images of LTC-IC colonies obtained from <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>A<sup>+</sup> cells (<italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> colony: 4x original magnification; <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> colony: 10x original magnification; scale bars = 100 µm).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>To investigate whether the reduced frequency and clonogenic potential of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs depends on the lower number of HSCs, we analyzed the frequency of functional stem cells by an <italic>in vivo</italic> transplantation experiments with purified HSCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g003">Figure 3A</xref>). Wt HSCs repopulated all the recipients already at the lowest cell dosage (50 cells) whereas <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs fully repopulated recipients only at the highest dosages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g003">Figure 3A</xref>; mice showing more than 2% donor-derived cells in the PB were considered as positively repopulated). The mean chimerism shown by transplanted mice at each cell dosage is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g003">Figure 3B</xref>.</p>
<fig id="pone-0107916-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Prep1 controls the number and the functionality of HSCs in E14.5 FLs.</title>
<p>(A) 50, 100 or 200 HSCs sorted from <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FLs were transplanted into lethally irradiated mice in competition with 2×10<sup>5</sup> CD45.1 BM cells. Mice showing more than 2% CD45.2<sup>+</sup> cells in the PB were considered as positively repopulated. HSCs are identified as CD45.2<sup>+</sup> L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup>cells. The graph represents the percentage of positively repopulated mice 16 weeks after transplantation (n = 4 for each genotype) (B) The graph indicates the mean chimerism shown by transplanted mice at each cell dosage in the PB 16 weeks after transplantation. (C) 2000 LSK cells purified form <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> or <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FLs were transplanted in competition with 1×10<sup>6</sup> BM cells into lethally irradiated CD45.1 recipients. (D) PB analyses to detect donor-derived (CD45.2<sup>+</sup>) cells performed at 7, 12,16 and 20 weeks after transplantation. In the graph, black bars represent the mean of CD45.2<sup>+</sup> cells in the PB of <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> or <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> reconstituted mice (n = 4 for each genotype; p&lt;0.001). (E–F) RUs (on the left) were calculated on FACS data (on the right) obtained from BMs of repopulated mice 20 weeks after transplantation. (E) Mean of RUs in Prep1<sup>+/+</sup> or Prep1<sup>i/i</sup>-transplanted mice; p = 0.05. (F) Mean of HSCs RUs in <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> or <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic>-transplanted mice; p = 0.01. HSCs are identified as CD45.2<sup>+</sup> L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup>cells.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>This set of experiments demonstrates that Prep1 controls the number of HSCs in FL and points to a role for this transcription factor in regulating also their functionality.</p>
</sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Prep1 affects HSCs self-renewal by controlling their proliferation state</title>
<p>To analyze the role of Prep1 in regulating the functionality of fetal HSCs, we assessed the ability of Prep1 deficient cells to <italic>de novo</italic> generate the stem/progenitor compartments <italic>in vivo</italic>. We transplanted CD45.2 <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> or wt FL L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> cells in competition with wt CD45.1 BM cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g003">Figure 3C</xref>) and followed the kinetic of repopulation in the PB of the hosts exploiting the CD45.2 phenotype of the donor cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> cells generated less mature hematopoietic cells in PB compared to wt controls at all time points (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g003">Figure 3D</xref>). This agrees with the decrease of both mature myeloid and lymphoid cells in the PB of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> recipients <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-DiRosa1">[24]</xref>. Twenty weeks after transplantation, we analyzed the repopulation efficiency of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> v wt HSCs by counting the number of repopulating units (see Methods). This revealed a dramatic (86%) decrease in the ability of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs to repopulate the entire hematopoietic system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g003">Figure 3E</xref>). We also measured the ability of FL <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs to give rise to new stem cells, investigating the donor-derived HSCs compartment in the host. Again, the number of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic>-derived RUs dropped compared to wt controls (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g003">Figure 3F</xref>). The progenitor compartments were also negatively affected by the absence of Prep1 in repopulated mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107916.s005">Table S1</xref>). The time of 20 weeks after transplantation, chosen to assess PB reconstitution, does not conflict with malignant transformation occurring in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> mice at least 7–8 months after transplantation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Longobardi2">[21]</xref>.</p>
<p>Functional impairment or decreased HSCs number in Prep1-deficient FLs might be due to increased apoptosis. However, the experiment shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g004">figure 4A</xref> rules out this hypothesis since wt and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs displayed comparable apoptosis level as measured by Annexin V binding. Nonetheless, when we moved to the analysis of the proliferative state of HSCs, we noticed a slight increase in the percentage of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs in G1 and S-G2-M phases compared to wt and, importantly, a statistically significant 50% reduction in the Prep1 deficient G0 quiescent pool (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). The depletion of the G0 pool in the stem cell compartment in the absence of Prep1 indicates that the functional defects observed in hypomorphic FLs might depend on a deregulated balance between quiescent and proliferative states which may lead to the exhaustion of the stem cell pool. To verify this hypothesis, we tested the self-renewal ability of fetal HSCs through serial transplantations into ablated hosts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g005">Figure 5A–5D</xref>). BM cells from <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> transplanted mice were less efficient than wt in repopulating PB in secondary recipients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g005">Figure 5B</xref>). 25% of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> transplanted mice (2/8) showed no reconstitution at all after long-term repopulation. Eight weeks after secondary transplantation, reconstitution by donor cells was analyzed with respect to the myeloid, B-lymphoid and T-lymphoid lineages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g005">Figure 5C</xref>). <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> donor cells were much less efficient than wt littermates in generating all the lineages, with a 30% decrease of myeloid CD45.2<sup>+</sup>Gr1<sup>+</sup>Mac1<sup>+</sup> and 75% reduction of both CD45.2<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>+</sup> and CD45.2<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup> lymphoid cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g005">Figure 5C</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0107916-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Prep1 influences HSC quiescent pool rather than HSCs apoptosis.</title>
<p>(A) Representative FACS contour plots to identify apoptotic <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs are shown on the left. The represented plots refer to L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup> gate and numbers in the FACS plots indicate the percentage of cells in parental gates. On the right, the graph represents the mean of apoptotic HSCs (Annexin<sup>+</sup> DAPI<sup>−</sup>) (n = 3; p = not significant). (B) Representative FACS contour plots to identify the cell cycle distribution of <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs are shown on the left. The represented plots refer to L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup> gate and numbers in the FACS plots indicate the percentage of cells in parental gates. On the right, the graph represents the mean of G0 (Ki67<sup>−</sup>Hoechst<sup>l</sup>°<sup>w</sup>), G1 (Ki67<sup>+</sup>Hoechst<sup>l</sup>°<sup>w</sup>) and S/G2/M (Ki67<sup>+</sup>Hoechst<sup>hi</sup>) HSCs (n = 3; p = not significant) (n = 3; G0 p = 0.02; G1 and S/G2/M p = not significant).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig><fig id="pone-0107916-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption>
<title>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup> HSCs undergo exhaustion faster than wt in serial transplantation assay.</title>
<p>(A) 2×10<sup>6</sup> unfractionated BM cells from primary recipients were injected into secondary hosts. Primary recipients had received 1×10<sup>6</sup> unfractionated CD45.2<sup>+</sup> FL cells together with 1×10<sup>6</sup> unfractionated CD45.1<sup>+</sup> wt BM cells (chimerism shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107916.s004">FigureS4</xref>). (B) PB analyses of secondary recipients were performed 8 and 20 weeks after transplantation to detect CD45.2<sup>+</sup> cells. Each recipient is depicted with a separate symbol, blue and red colors indicating <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> reconstituted mice, respectively. Black bars represent the mean values in <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> or <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> reconstituted mice (n = 8 for each genotype at both time points; p-value&lt;0.001 at both time points). (C) 20 weeks after transplantation, PB of secondary hosts was analysed for donor-derived myeloid cells (CD45.2<sup>+</sup>Gr1<sup>+</sup>Mac1<sup>+</sup>; p = 0.000017), B lymphoid cells (CD45.2<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>+</sup>; p = 0.000007) and T lymphoid cells (CD45.2<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup>; p = 0.000017). Black bars represent mean values (n = 8 for each genotype). (D) Tertiary transplantations were performed injecting 2×10<sup>6</sup> BM cells from secondary recipients into tertiary hosts. (E) PB of tertiary hosts was analyzed 20 weeks after transplantation to detect CD45.2<sup>+</sup> cells. Black bars represent the mean values (n = 10 for <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and n = 8 for <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic>; p-value = 0.007). On the right, representative FACS histograms obtained for CD45.2<sup>+</sup> cells of control and mutant tertiary recipients. (F) The ratio between the number of positively repopulated mice (CD45.2<sup>+</sup> cells &gt;2%) and transplanted mice is represented for primary, secondary and tertiary transplantations for both genotypes (primary transplantation n = 10 for each genotype; secondary transplantation n = 8 for each genotype; tertiary transplantation n = 10 for <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and n = 8 for <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic>).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>When we transferred BM cells from secondary to tertiary recipients (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g005">Figure 5D</xref>), <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> derived cells lost their repopulation capacity as only a minor fraction of the tertiary transplanted hosts (2/8) showed a low repopulation activity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g005">Figure 5E–F</xref>). In summary, <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs initially repopulate primary recipients as wt controls. However, in secondary and tertiary recipients the <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> stem cell pool decreases tending to premature exhaustion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g005">Figure 5F</xref>).</p>
<p>To directly support the above conclusion, we re-transplanted primary recipient’s BM cells after readjusting the CD45.2/CD45.1 ratio in donor cells by FACS sorting (six mice for wt and 2 for hypomorphic). The result was unequivocal with a mean 42 v 5% donor-derived cells in wt and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> secondarily transplanted mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107916.s002">Figure S2A</xref>). Similarly, in PB donor-derived myeloid, B-lymphoid and T lymphoid cells were dramatically reduced in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> compared to wt reconstituted mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107916.s002">Figure S2B–D</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Prep1 modulates the interferon signaling pathway in FL HSCs</title>
<p>The reduced quiescent stem cell pool and the premature exhaustion of HSCs in the <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL suggest that Prep1 regulates self-renewal by controlling the quiescence/proliferation balance. To gain insight into the signaling cascades and the molecular mechanisms regulated by Prep1 in FL HSCs, we investigated the increased expression of the surface marker Sca-1 in L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g001">Figure 1C</xref>). Sca-1 is known to regulate the repopulation activity and self-renewal of HSCs in both FL and BM <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Hartner1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Essers1">[34]</xref>. We measured in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL HSCs a 2-fold increase in Sca-1 antigen compared to wt control littermates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g006">Figure 6A</xref>) and a comparable increase in its transcript level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g006">Figure 6B</xref>). Since Sca-1 is an IFN-inducible gene <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Sinclair1">[35]</xref> and is upregulated by IFNs in FL HSCs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Hartner1">[33]</xref>, we investigated whether other components of this signaling pathway are perturbed in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs measuring the mRNA level of a panel of genes implicated in the IFN response (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g006">Figure 6C</xref>). We observed an increase in the expression of Stat1, Stat2 and Irf7 in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs compared to wt littermates. Moreover we also noticed a statistically significant reduction in the expression of Adar1 in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> cells.</p>
<fig id="pone-0107916-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption>
<title>Prep1 modulates the IFN signaling pathway of FL HSCs.</title>
<p>(A) The expression of Sca-1 on the cell surface of <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> L<sup>−</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup> is quantified by mean fluorescent intensity (MFI). The representative FACS histogram on the left refers to L<sup>−</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup> gate (n = 8 for each genotype; p = 0.003). (B) qRT-PCR was performed on sorted <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup> cells to detect Sca1 transcripts. Values are normalized on GAPDH expression (n = 4 for each genotypes; p = 0.02). (C) The histograms show the expression of the indicated genes in sorted <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup> cells as detected by qRT-PCR. (n = 4 for each genotypes; Stat1 p = 0.02; Adar1 p = 0.02; Irf7 p = 0.003; Prep1 p = 0.00002). (D) The representative FACS histogram on the left refers to the L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup> gate. The negative control (grey histogram) tracing represents a sample stained for all the surface markers plus the fluorochrome-conjugated secondary antibody used to detect pStat1, but without the pStat1 antibody. (n = 3 for each genotype; p = 0.01). The phosphorylation of Stat1 (pStat1) was analyzed by MFI and quantitated on the right.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g006" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Furthermore a ChIP sequencing analysis performed on mouse embryos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Penkov2">[36]</xref> (and embryonic stem cells) revealed that Irf1, Irf2 and Irf8 are direct Prep1 targets (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g007">Figure 7</xref>). The peaks, having a highly significant intensity, are located about from Kb to few bp (<italic>Irf8</italic>) before the transcription start site of the genes. These data together with the increased expression of signaling mediators like Stat1, Stat2 and of <italic>Irf7</italic> and the decrease of the suppressor of the IFN response (Adar1) indicate that Prep1 regulates the IFN pathway. To corroborate the involvement of STATs, we investigated the activation of Stat1 comparing its phosphorylation state in wt and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs by flow cytometry and observed a statistically significant 1.6 fold-increase in pStat1 in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g006">Figure 6D</xref>).</p>
<fig id="pone-0107916-g007" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption>
<title>Prep1 ChIP-seq tracing of the mouse embryo Irf1, Irf2 and Irf8 genes.</title>
<p>ChIPseq tracing from the m9 mouse genome. In the <italic>Irf1</italic> gene a Prep1 peak is present about 10 Kbp upstream of the promoter: the peak is centered around the TGAGTGACAG Prep1 consensus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Penkov2">[36]</xref>. In the <italic>Irf2</italic> gene, the peak is present 50 Kbp upstream of the promoter and is centered around a similar TGAATGACAA Prep1 consensus <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Penkov2">[36]</xref>. In the <italic>Irf8</italic> gene, the peak is right at the promoter, 100 bp distance, centered around a less frequent hexameric consensus, TGGCAG <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Penkov2">[36]</xref>. Chromatin immunoprecipitation was performed on E11.5 mouse embryos <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Penkov2">[36]</xref> and was confirmed in ES cells.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g007" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Moreover, since the ablation of Pbx1 in adult HSCs influences the TGFbeta pathway <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ficara1">[37]</xref>, we investigated whether Prep1 acts in a similar way in FLs. To this aim, we knocked down (KD) Prep1 by shRNA in the EML1 progenitors cell line and assessed their responsiveness to TGFbeta. We found no significant alteration in SMAD levels at both RNA and protein level (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g008">Figure 8B–C</xref>). However, the phosphorylation of Smad2 and Smad3 was reduced in Prep1<sup>KD</sup> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g008">Figure 8C</xref>). This suggests that Prep1 may partly act modulating TGFbeta.</p>
<fig id="pone-0107916-g008" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption>
<title>Prep1 does not affect Smads expression but modulates their phosphorylation in the EML1 progenitor cell line.</title>
<p>(A) Prep1 knock-down (KD) was assessed by Immuno-blotting analysis. Actin was used as loading control. (B–C) Prep1 KD or control EML1 cells were incubated 4 h with (+) or without (−) TGFβ (10 ng/ml). (B) Histograms show fold induction of the indicated transcripts in Prep1 KD or control EML1 cells as measured by qRT-PCR. The data represent 2 independent experiments. (C) Smads and their phosphorylated forms (as indicated) were detected by Western blot analyses. Vinculin was used as loading control. The data were reproduced in 2 independent experiments.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.g008" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>We next investigated the status of the IFN pathway in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs in the adult wt environment after transplantation. Neither the activation of Stat1 (pStat1) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107916.s003">Figure S3A</xref>) nor the overexpression of Sca-1 was reproduced in the BM niche of transplanted mice (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107916.s003">Figure S3B</xref>). Moreover, since Sca-1 overexpression is a distinguishing marker of proliferative v. quiescent HSCs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Essers1">[34]</xref>, we investigated the cell cycle status of these cells. In the adult environment, <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> and wt HSCs did not show any statistically significant difference in the quiescent G0 stem cell pool (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107916.s003">Figure S3C</xref>). This indicates that the effect of Prep1 on the Stat1/Sca1 proliferative pathway is specific to fetal cells and may be dispensable during adult hematopoiesis.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>We have shown that Prep1 controls the number and function of HSC during mouse embryo development. Prep1 regulates HSC self-renewal since <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> cells are deficient in generating the stem cell compartment upon transplantation into ablated hosts (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g003">Figure 3</xref>) and undergo faster exhaustion upon serial transplantation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g005">Figure 5</xref>).</p>
<p>These results are coherent with the role in hematopoiesis of other TALE family members: Pbx1 and Meis1. Pbx1 regulates transcription mostly as a dimer with Prep1 or Meis1. In a mixed cells population Meis1-Pbx1 complex mainly associated with intragenic regions of developmental genes, whereas Prep1-Pbx1 bound promoters of genes involved in basic cell functions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Penkov2">[36]</xref>. Pbx1 and Meis1 play an important role in the hematopoietic compartment as both FL <italic>Pbx1<sup>−/−</sup></italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-DiMartino1">[38]</xref> and <italic>Meis1<sup>−/−</sup></italic> HSCs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Azcoitia1">[39]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Hisa1">[40]</xref> are inefficient in establishing multi-lineage hematopoiesis when tested in transplantation experiments. Moreover, Pbx1 regulates BM HSC self-renewal by maintaining the quiescent stem cell pool <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ficara1">[37]</xref>. Adult <italic>Pbx1<sup>−/−</sup></italic> HSCs show a reduced G0 fraction and undergo exhaustion faster than wt. Pbx1 also has a lineage-specific role preventing myeloid differentiation and maintaining lymphoid potential <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ficara2">[41]</xref>. As Prep1 is the most common partner of Pbx1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Penkov2">[36]</xref>, the phenotype of <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSC may be similar to <italic>Pbx1<sup>−/−</sup></italic>. However, CMPs and CLPs frequency in the <italic>Pbx1<sup>−/−</sup></italic> background is different from <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic>, where the frequency of lymphoid progenitors is drastically increased. Moreover, whereas Meis1 and Pbx1 act in concert to transcriptionally modulate TGFbeta response <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ficara1">[37]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ariki1">[42]</xref>, Prep1 is mainly implicated in the regulation of the IFN-response pathway and may affect the TGFbeta pathway in the adult. The phenotypes may also depend on additional non-transcriptional effects of Prep1 as both Meis1 and Pbx1 are decreased in P<italic>rep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ferretti2">[20]</xref>.</p>
<p>In this paper we also show that Prep1 regulates the cell cycle state of the FL HSCs, maintaining cells in the G0 phase (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Embryonic FL HSCs are mainly proliferating cells in comparison with the quiescent adult BM HSCs. At E14.5, FL HSCs cycle every 48 hours <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Nygren1">[43]</xref>, while adult HSCs divide every 7 weeks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Dingli1">[44]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Wilson1">[45]</xref>. As a consequence, G0 phase FL HSCs cannot aptly be considered the fetal counterpart of the adult HSCs which represent a “dormant” pool. Rather, the prolonged permanence in G0 is a requirement to assure that the modality of cell division corresponds to biological necessities. Furthermore, in terms of cell cycle the transit through G0 and the prolonged cell cycle are peculiarities of HSCs versus progenitors cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Nygren1">[43]</xref>. In this view, Prep1 might act as an intrinsic factor necessary at mid-gestation to regulate the cell cycle of HSCs and to preserve their self-renewal ability.</p>
<p>In homeostatic conditions quiescent BM HSCs enter the cell cycle dividing preferentially by asymmetric cell division with the aim to produce at the same time mature cells and to maintain a stem cell pool <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Shenghui1">[46]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ting1">[48]</xref>, FL HSCs mainly divide by symmetric self-renewing divisions in order to expand the HSC pool <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Morrison3">[49]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Mikkola1">[50]</xref>. We show that, in E14.5 FLs, Prep1 deficiency causes a reduction in the number of HSCs and an increase in multipotent progenitors identified as L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> cells. The inverse correlation between stem and progenitor cells <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> embryos might be caused by a change in the balance between symmetric and asymmetric cell divisions skewed towards the asymmetric mode, leading to a reduced stem cell pool and the increased progenitor compartment.</p>
<p>In addition, the increased cycling shown by <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> fetal HSCs positively correlates with the role of Prep1 as tumor suppressor. Indeed <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL cells cause lymphomas when transplanted in hosts after a long latency <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Longobardi2">[21]</xref> and the deregulated cell cycle might contribute to make these cells prone to malignant transformation.</p>
<p>Furthermore, <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL HSCs display an activated IFN-induced response as demonstrated by the activation of STAT1, increased IFN-induced transcripts and decreased Adar1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0107916-g006">Figure 6</xref>). This feature positively correlates with the reduced number of HSCs in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FLs. IFN signaling has been shown to regulate HSCs properties in both adult and fetal tissues. Indeed, treatment of adult HSCs with IFNα induces their proliferation with the concomitant decrease of the G0 pool causing HSCs exhaustion, an effect mediated by activation of STAT1 and upregulation of Sca-1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Essers1">[34]</xref>. In addition, Adar1 deaminase suppresses IFN signaling and is strongly down-regulated in FL HSCs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Hartner1">[33]</xref>. Similarly to <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs, <italic>Adar1<sup>−/−</sup></italic> FL HSCs upregulate IFN inducible genes (Sca-1, Stats and Irfs) and show a diminished number of HSCs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Hartner1">[33]</xref>.</p>
<p>Although not yet directly tested, it is tempting to speculatre that the Prep1-absence-dependent activation of IFN response is connected to DNA damage accumulation. The induction of DNA damage in human and mouse cells triggers Atm-mediated DNA damage response that, in turn, through the activation of NFKB leads to the expression of IFN and IFN-induced genes such as <italic>Irf1</italic> and <italic>Irf7</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-BrzostekRacine1">[51]</xref>. Interestingly, Prep1 acts as a tumor suppressor in maintaining genome stability in cells <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Iotti1">[22]</xref>. FL HSCs are exposed to proliferative stress with accumulation of mutations and genome instability <italic>per se,</italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FL cells show DNA damage accumulation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Iotti1">[22]</xref>. We speculate that the activation of the IFN response in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs could possibly be induced by intrinsic DNA damage due to Prep1 deficiency. The direct binding of Prep1 to three interferon-response genes (<italic>Irf1</italic>, <italic>Irf2</italic>, <italic>Irf8</italic>), the increased expression of Irf7 and repression of Irf8 support the idea that Prep1 regulates the IFN pathway. These factors orchestrate the pathway and affect stem and progenitors cell proliferation and differentiation <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ning1">[52]</xref>.</p>
<p>The present work also shows that the Stats/Sca1 proliferative axis is is no longer activated in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> HSCs isolated from adult transplanted BM niche (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0107916.s003">Figure S3</xref>). This is not a unique case in hematopoietic development as <italic>Mll<sup>−/−</sup></italic> mice lose quiescent G0 HSCs and show repopulation defects. Importantly, the Mll-dependent self-renewal defect is much stronger in the FL than in the adult BM niche <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-McMahon1">[53]</xref>. The dual behavior of hypomorphic cells suggests that an embryonic niche-specific signal is required for the <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> fetal phenotype and possibly suggests different proliferative cues in FLs and adult quiescent BM niche. An additional regulator of HSC activity missing in <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> cells might be the TGFbeta-dependent activation of Smad2/Smad3, in agreement with the <italic>Pbx1<sup>−/−</sup></italic> phenotype <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0107916-Ficara1">[37]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Conclusions</title>
<p>In this work, we demonstrate that the homeodomain transcription factor Prep1 controls the number and the biological activities of fetal HSCs. In particular, we show that Prep1 regulates the self-renewal ability and the cell cycle distribution of HSCs during fetal hematopoiesis by regulating the activation of Stat1, Sca-1 via the IFN-dependent proliferative pathway.</p>
</sec><sec id="s6">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0107916.s001" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>The HSC-enriched population L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>AA4.1<sup>+</sup> is affected by the absence of Prep1.</bold> (A) Representative FACS dot plots to identify L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>AA4.1<sup>+</sup> cells in <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FLs. The plots show AA4.1<sup>+</sup> cells in the L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup> population and the numbers indicate their percentage in the parental gate. (B) Graphs describe the percentage (left) and absolute numbers (left) of the L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>AA4.1<sup>+</sup> population (n = 8 for <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and n = 12 for <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FLs in both graphs; % L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>AA4.1<sup>+</sup> p = not significant; # L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>AA4.1<sup>+</sup> p = 0.02).</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0107916.s002" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold><italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic></bold><bold> cells in a readjusted ratio with competitors show defective repopulation upon secondary transplantation.</bold> 1×10<sup>6</sup> <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> or <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> CD45.2<sup>+</sup> cells sorted from primary recipients were mixed with 3×10<sup>5</sup> sorted CD45.1<sup>+</sup> competitor cells and transplanted into lethally irradiated secondary recipients. (A) To detect donor-derived (CD45.2<sup>+</sup>) cells, PB analyses of secondary recipients were performed 16 weeks after transplantation. White diamonds and grey triangles indicate <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> reconstituted mice, respectively. Black bars represent the mean of CD45.2<sup>+</sup> cells in <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> or <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> reconstituted mice (n = 6 for <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and n = 2 for <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic>. p = 0.02). (B-C-D) 16 weeks after transplantation, PB of secondary hosts was analysed (B) for the presence of donor-derived myeloid cells (CD45.2<sup>+</sup>Gr1<sup>+</sup>Mac1<sup>+</sup>; p-value = 0.008), (C) donor-derived B lymphoid cells (CD45.2<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>+</sup>; p-value = 0.04) and (D) donor-derived T lymphoid cells (CD45.2<sup>+</sup>CD3<sup>+</sup>; p-value = 0.02). Black bars represent mean values (n = 6 for <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and n = 2 for <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic>).</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0107916.s003" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>The IFN-induced signaling pathway is not induced in the absence of Prep1 in the adult BM niche.</bold> (A–C) pStat1, Sca1 and cell cycle distribution were analyzed in <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> and <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic>-derived HSCs in the BM of primary transplanted mice that received 1×10<sup>6</sup> unfractionated FL cells together with 1×10<sup>6</sup> unfractionated wt BM cells. Representative FACS plots are reported on the left and their quantifications on the right. (A) pStat1 intensity was evaluated by MFI. FACS plots are referred to CD45.2<sup>+</sup>L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup> gate (n = 3 for each genotypes; p = not significant; representative of 3 independent experiments). (B) Sca-1 intensity was evaluated by MFI. FACS plots are referred to CD45.2<sup>+</sup>L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup>CD48<sup>−</sup>CD41<sup>−</sup> gate (n = 4 for each genotypes; p = not significant; representative of 3 independent experiments). (C) Cell cycle distribution in G0, G1 and S/G2/M phases was evaluated for donor-derived HSCs by Ki67/Hoechst 33342 staining. FACS plots are referred to CD45.2<sup>+</sup>L<sup>−</sup>S<sup>+</sup>K<sup>+</sup>CD150<sup>+</sup> gate (n = 5 for each genotypes; G0, G1 and S/G2/M p = not significant).</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0107916.s004" mimetype="image/tiff" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S4</label><caption>
<p><bold>Chimerism in primary recipients of the serial transplantation experiment.</bold> Primary recipients received 1*10<sup>6</sup> unfractionated CD45.2 FL cells from <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> or <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> embryos together with 1*10<sup>6</sup> unfractionated CD45.1 BM cells. Percentages of donor-derived cells (on the left) were calculated on FACS data (on the right) obtained from BMs of transplanted mice 20 weeks after transplantation.</p>
<p>(TIF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0107916.s005" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0107916.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Progenitor compartments are affected in transplanted hosts in the absence of Prep1.</bold> 2000 LSK cells purified form <italic>Prep1<sup>+/+</sup></italic> or <italic>Prep1<sup>i/i</sup></italic> FLs were transplanted in competition with 1×10<sup>6</sup> BM cells into lethally irradiated CD45.1 recipients. LSK, CLP and CMP RUs (±SEM) are calculated in the BM of transplanted primary recipients (see Methods). (RU = repopulating units; LSK = Lin<sup>−</sup>Sca-1<sup>+</sup>cKit<sup>+</sup> cells; CLP = common lymphoid progenitors; CMP = common myeloid progenitors).</p>
<p>(DOCX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>We are grateful to the IFOM mouse and flow cytometry facilities.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Medvinsky1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Medvinsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dzierzak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Definitive hematopoiesis is autonomously initiated by the AGM region</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>86(6)</volume>: <fpage>897</fpage>–<lpage>906</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Ema1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ema</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakauchi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Expansion of hematopoietic stem cells in the developing liver of a mouse embryo</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> <volume>95(7)</volume>: <fpage>2284</fpage>–<lpage>2288</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Orkin1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Orkin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zon</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Hematopoiesis: an evolving paradigm for stem cell biology</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>132(4)</volume>: <fpage>631</fpage>–<lpage>644</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Calvi1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Calvi</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weibrecht</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Osteoblastic cells regulate the haematopoietic stem cell niche</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>425(6960)</volume>: <fpage>841</fpage>–<lpage>846</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Sugiyama1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sugiyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kohara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagasawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Maintenance of the hematopoietic stem cell pool by CXCL12-CXCR4 chemokine signaling in bone marrow stromal cell niches</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> <volume>25(6)</volume>: <fpage>977</fpage>–<lpage>988</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Zhang1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Identification of the haematopoietic stem cell niche and control of the niche size</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>425(6960)</volume>: <fpage>836</fpage>–<lpage>841</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Arai1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirao</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ohmura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Tie2/angiopoietin-1 signaling regulates hematopoietic stem cell quiescence in the bone marrow niche</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>118(2)</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>–<lpage>161</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Kiel1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kiel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iwashita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Terhorst</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>SLAM family receptors distinguish hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells and reveal endothelial niches for stem cells</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>121(7)</volume>: <fpage>1109</fpage>–<lpage>1121</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Yoshihara1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yoshihara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hosokawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagiwara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takubo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Thrombopoietin/MPL signaling regulates hematopoietic stem cell quiescence and interaction with the osteoblastic niche</article-title>. <source>Cell Stem Cell</source> <volume>1(6)</volume>: <fpage>685</fpage>–<lpage>697</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Jiang1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>C-C</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Hedgehog signaling in development and cancer</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source> <volume>15(6)</volume>: <fpage>801</fpage>–<lpage>812</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Gereige1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gereige</surname><given-names>L-M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkola</surname><given-names>HKA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>DNA methylation is a guardian of stem cell self-renewal and multipotency</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source> <volume>41(11)</volume>: <fpage>1164</fpage>–<lpage>1166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Leong1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leong</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W-Q</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>The Notch pathway in prostate development and cancer</article-title>. <source>Differentiation</source> <volume>76(6)</volume>: <fpage>699</fpage>–<lpage>716</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Reya1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Wnt signalling in stem cells and cancer</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>434(7035)</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>–<lpage>850</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Clevers1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clevers</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Wnt/beta-catenin signaling in development and disease</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>127(3)</volume>: <fpage>469</fpage>–<lpage>480</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Longobardi1"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longobardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penkov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mateos</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Florian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Biochemistry of the TALE transcription factors Prep, Meis and Pbx in vertebrates. Devel</article-title>. <source>Dynamics</source> <volume>243(1)</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>–<lpage>75</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Moens1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Moens</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selleri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Hox cofactors in vertebrate development</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>291(2)</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>–<lpage>206</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Ferretti1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pöpperl</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maconochie</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krumlauf</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Segmental expression of Hoxb2 in r4 requires two separate sites that integrate cooperative interactions between Prep1, Pbx and Hox proteins</article-title>. <source>Dev Camb Engl</source> <volume>127(1)</volume>: <fpage>155</fpage>–<lpage>166</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Deflorian1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Deflorian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tiso</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blasi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Prep1.1 has essential genetic functions in hindbrain development and cranial neural crest cell differentiation</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>131(3)</volume>: <fpage>613</fpage>–<lpage>627</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-FernandezDiaz1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Diaz</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurent</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Girasoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longobardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The absence of Prep1 causes p53-dependent apoptosis of mouse pluripotent epiblast cells</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>137(20)</volume>: <fpage>3393</fpage>–<lpage>3403</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Ferretti2"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villaescusa</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Rosa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Diaz</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longobardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Hypomorphic mutation of the TALE gene Prep1 (pKnox1) causes a major reduction of Pbx and Meis proteins and a pleiotropic embryonic phenotype</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>26(15)</volume>: <fpage>5650</fpage>–<lpage>5662</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Longobardi2"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longobardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iotti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Rosa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mejetta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Prep1 (pKnox1)-deficiency leads to spontaneous tumor development in mice and accelerates EmuMyc lymphomagenesis: a tumor suppressor role for Prep1</article-title>. <source>Mol Oncol</source> <volume>4(2)</volume>: <fpage>126</fpage>–<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Iotti1"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iotti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longobardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Masella</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dardaei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Santis</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Homeodomain transcription factor and tumor suppressor Prep1 is required to maintain genomic stability</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source> <volume>108(29)</volume>: <fpage>314</fpage>–<lpage>322</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Iotti2"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Iotti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mejetta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Modica</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penkov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ponzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Reduction of Prep1 levels affects differentiation of normal and malignant B cells and accelerates Myc driven lymphomagenesis</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source> <volume>7(10)</volume>: <fpage>e48353</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-DiRosa1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Di Rosa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Villaescusa</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longobardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iotti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The homeodomain transcription factor Prep1 (pKnox1) is required for hematopoietic stem and progenitor cell activity</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>311(2)</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>–<lpage>334</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Penkov1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Penkov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Rosa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez Diaz</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Basso</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferretti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Involvement of Prep1 in the alphabeta T-cell receptor T-lymphocytic potential of hematopoietic precursors</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source> <volume>25(24)</volume>: <fpage>10768</fpage>–<lpage>10781</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Khn1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kühn</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwenk</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aguet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rajewsky</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Inducible gene targeting in mice</article-title>. <source>Science</source> <volume>269(5229)</volume>: <fpage>1427</fpage>–<lpage>1429</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Morrison1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hemmati</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wandycz</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weissman</surname><given-names>IL</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The purification and characterization of fetal liver hematopoietic stem cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci</article-title>. <volume>92(22)</volume>: <fpage>10302</fpage>–<lpage>10306</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Tsai1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bartelmez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sitnicka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Lymphohematopoietic progenitors immortalized by a retroviral vector harboring a dominant-negative retinoic acid receptor can recapitulate lymphoid, myeloid, and erythroid development</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>2831</fpage>–<lpage>2841</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Ema2"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ema</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matsubara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Adult mouse hematopoietic stem cells: purification and single-cell assays</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source> <volume>1(6)</volume>: <fpage>2979</fpage>–<lpage>2987</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Kim1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Enhanced purification of fetal liver hematopoietic stem cells using SLAM family receptors</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> <volume>108</volume>: <fpage>737</fpage>–<lpage>744</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Hsu1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ema</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Hematopoietic stem cells express Tie-2 receptor in the murine fetal liver</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> <volume>96</volume>: <fpage>3757</fpage>–<lpage>3762</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Petrenko1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petrenko</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beavis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klaine</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kittappa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Godin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The molecular characterization of the fetal stem cell marker AA4</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>691</fpage>–<lpage>700</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Hartner1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hartner</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Walkley</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orkin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>ADAR1 is essential for the maintenance of hematopoiesis and suppression of interferon signaling</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>109</fpage>–<lpage>115</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Essers1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Essers</surname><given-names>MAG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Offner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco-Bose</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waibler</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kalinke</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>IFNalpha activates dormant haematopoietic stem cells in vivo</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>458(7240)</volume>: <fpage>904</fpage>–<lpage>908</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Sinclair1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Daly</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dzierzak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>The Ly-6E.1 (Sca-1) gene requires a 3′ chromatin-dependent region for high-level gamma-interferon-induced hematopoietic cell expression</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> <volume>87(7)</volume>: <fpage>2750</fpage>–<lpage>2761</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Penkov2"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Penkov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mateos San Martín</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fernandez-Díaz</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rosselló</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torroja</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Analysis of the DNA-binding profile and function of TALE homeoproteins reveals their specialization and specific interactions with Hox genes/proteins</article-title>. <source>Cell Reports</source> <volume>3(4)</volume>: <fpage>1321</fpage>–<lpage>1333</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Ficara1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ficara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cleary</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Pbx1 regulates self-renewal of long-term hematopoietic stem cells by maintaining their quiescence Cell Stem Cell</article-title>. <volume>2(5)</volume>: <fpage>484</fpage>–<lpage>496</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-DiMartino1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>DiMartino</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Selleri</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Traver</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Firpo</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rhee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The Hox cofactor and proto-oncogene Pbx1 is required for maintenance of definitive hematopoiesis in the fetal liver</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> <volume>98(3)</volume>: <fpage>618</fpage>–<lpage>626</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Azcoitia1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Azcoitia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aracil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martínez-A</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The homeodomain protein Meis1 is essential for definitive hematopoiesis and vascular patterning in the mouse embryo</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source> <volume>280(2)</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>–<lpage>320</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Hisa1"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hisa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rachel</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Hematopoietic, angiogenic and eye defects in Meis1 mutant animals</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source> <volume>23(2)</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>–<lpage>459</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Ficara2"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ficara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crisafulli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Pbx1 restrains myeloid maturation while preserving lymphoid potential in hematopoietic progenitors</article-title>. <source>J Cell Sci</source> <volume>126</volume>: <fpage>3181</fpage>–<lpage>91</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Ariki1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ariki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mabuchi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suzuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakatake</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Homeodomain transcription factor meis1 is a critical regulator of adult bone marrow hematopoiesis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source> <volume>9(2)</volume>: <fpage>e87646</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Nygren1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nygren</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bryder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>SEW</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Prolonged cell cycle transit is a defining and developmentally conserved hemopoietic stem cell property</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> <volume>177(1)</volume>: <fpage>201</fpage>–<lpage>208</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Dingli1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dingli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pacheco</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Modeling the architecture and dynamics of hematopoiesis</article-title>. <source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev Syst Biol Med</source> <volume>2(2)</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>–<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Wilson1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laurenti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oser</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van der Wath</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanco-Bose</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Hematopoietic stem cells reversibly switch from dormancy to self-renewal during homeostasis and repair</article-title>. <source>Cell</source> <volume>135(6)</volume>: <fpage>1118</fpage>–<lpage>1129</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Shenghui1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shenghui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of Stem Cell Self-Renewal</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source> <volume>25(1)</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>–<lpage>406</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Morrison2"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimble</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Asymmetric and symmetric stem-cell divisions in development and cancer</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>441(7097)</volume>: <fpage>1068</fpage>–<lpage>1074</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Ting1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deneault</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cellot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chagraoui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Asymmetric segregation and self-renewal of hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells with endocytic Ap2a2</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> <volume>119(11)</volume>: <fpage>2510</fpage>–<lpage>2522</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Morrison3"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kimble</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Asymmetric and symmetric stem-cell divisions in development and cancer</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> <volume>441(7097)</volume>: <fpage>1068</fpage>–<lpage>1074</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Mikkola1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mikkola</surname><given-names>HKA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Orkin</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>The journey of developing hematopoietic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Development</source> <volume>133(19)</volume>: <fpage>3733</fpage>–<lpage>3744</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-BrzostekRacine1"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brzostek-Racine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Scoy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The DNA damage response induces IFN</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> <volume>187(10)</volume>: <fpage>5336</fpage>–<lpage>5345</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-Ning1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ning</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pagano</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>IRF7: activation, regulation, modification and function</article-title>. <source>Genes Immun</source> <volume>12(6)</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>–<lpage>414</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0107916-McMahon1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hiew</surname><given-names>SY-L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hadjur</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veiga-Fernandes</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Menzel</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Mll has a critical role in fetal and adult hematopoietic stem cell self-renewal</article-title>. <source>Cell Stem Cell</source> <volume>1(3)</volume>: <fpage>338</fpage>–<lpage>345</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>