<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS ONE</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group>
<journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group>
<issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-21927</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106067</article-id>
<article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and life sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Pests</subject><subj-group><subject>Insect pests</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene flow</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Ecology and environmental sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Species colonization</subject><subj-group><subject>Invasive species</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories>
<title-group>
<article-title>Low Genetic Diversity in <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> Aphid Populations at the Worldwide Scale</article-title>
<alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Clonal Diversity of <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic></alt-title>
</title-group>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nibouche</surname><given-names>Samuel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fartek</surname><given-names>Benjamin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mississipi</surname><given-names>Stelly</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delatte</surname><given-names>Hélène</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynaud</surname><given-names>Bernard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
<contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Costet</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Cirad, UMR PVBMT, Saint-Pierre, La Réunion, France</addr-line></aff>
<aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Université de la Réunion, UMR PVBMT, Saint-Pierre, La Réunion, France</addr-line></aff>
<contrib-group>
<contrib contrib-type="editor" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gerardo</surname><given-names>Nicole M.</given-names></name>
<role>Editor</role>
<xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib>
</contrib-group>
<aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Emory University, United States of America</addr-line></aff>
<author-notes>
<corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email xlink:type="simple">samuel.nibouche@cirad.fr</email></corresp>
<fn fn-type="conflict"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn>
<fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: BF SN LC HD BR. Performed the experiments: BF SM. Analyzed the data: SN BF LC HD. Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: BF SM SN HD LC BR.</p></fn>
</author-notes>
<pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date>
<volume>9</volume>
<issue>8</issue>
<elocation-id>e106067</elocation-id>
<history>
<date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date>
</history>
<permissions>
<copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
<copyright-holder>Nibouche et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:type="simple"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xlink:type="simple">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions>
<abstract>
<p>Numerous studies have examined the genetic diversity and genetic structure of invading species, with contrasting results concerning the relative roles of genetic diversity and phenotypic plasticity in the success of introduced populations. Increasing evidence shows that asexual lineages of aphids are able to occupy a wide geographical and ecological range of habitats despite low genetic diversity. The anholocyclic aphid <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> is a pest of sugarcane and sorghum which originated in the old world, was introduced into the Americas, and is now distributed worldwide. Our purpose was to assess the genetic diversity and structuring of populations of this species according to host and locality. We used 10 microsatellite markers to genotype 1333 individuals (57 samples, 42 localities, 15 countries) collected mainly on sugarcane or sorghum. Five multilocus lineages (MLL) were defined, grouping multilocus genotypes (MLG) differing by only a few mutations or scoring errors. Analysis of a 658 bp sequence of mitochondrial COI gene on 96 individuals revealed five haplotypes, with a mean divergence of only 0.19 %. The distribution of MLL appeared to be strongly influenced by geography but not by host plant. Each of the five MLL grouped individuals from (A) Africa, (B) Australia, (C) South America, the Caribbean and the Indian Ocean including East Africa, (D) USA, and (E) China. The MLL A and C, with a wide geographic distribution, matched the definition of superclone. Among aphids, <italic>M. sacchari</italic> has one of the lowest known rates of genetic diversity for such a wide geographical distribution.</p>
</abstract>
<funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by CIRAD, by the Conseil Régional de La Réunion and by the European Union: European regional development fund (ERDF). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability" xlink:type="simple"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta>
</front>
<body><sec id="s1">
<title>Introduction</title>
<p>Range expansion of exotic species can result from either evolutionary adaptation or generalism and plasticity often associated with a change in niche <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Lee1">[1]</xref>. Genetic diversity is required for evolutionary adaptation, but a reduction in genetic diversity in invasive populations compared to populations in their native range is expected and often observed <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Amsellem1">[2]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Grapputo1">[5]</xref>. Organisms with clonal reproduction may exhibit reduced genetic diversity within populations, as better-adapted clonal genotypes expand and dominate available resources <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Vrijenhoek1">[6]</xref>. In aphids, the concept of “superclones” emerged <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Vorburger1">[7]</xref> when a few asexual genotypes of the same species were able to colonize a wide geographical or ecological range of habitats <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Chen1">[8]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Piffaretti1">[11]</xref>. The capacity of these populations to adapt to different conditions could be the result of a preadaptation capacity for phenotypic plasticity rather than local selection acting on genetic diversity <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Facon1">[12]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Ward1">[13]</xref>. What is more, this capacity may be enhanced by their high rate of reproduction and population expansion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Loxdale1">[14]</xref>. For these reasons, clonal aphids are good models to assess the ability of asexual lineages to show rapid and widespread adaptive changes to ecological conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Loxdale2">[15]</xref>.</p>
<p>The old world genus <italic>Melanaphis</italic> van der Groot 1917 comprises around 20 species mainly associated with Poaceae, most of which originate from East Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Blackman1">[16]</xref>. The sugarcane aphid <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> (Zehtner, 1897) (Homoptera, Aphididae), which is considered to be mainly anholocyclic, is present in America, Australia, Asia and Africa. <italic>M. sacchari</italic> is known to be invasive in continental US <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Mead1">[17]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-White1">[18]</xref> and in Central and South America <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Blackman1">[16]</xref>. The host range of this species is restricted to Poaceae <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Amsellem1">[2]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Singh1">[19]</xref>. Blackman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Blackman2">[20]</xref> hypothesised that <italic>Melanaphis</italic> individuals originating from sorghum or sugarcane were distinct taxa, referred to as <italic>M. sorghi</italic> and <italic>M. sacchari</italic> respectively, even though their host plant preference was not absolute. In their catalogue, Remaudière and Remaudière <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Remaudire1">[21]</xref> considered <italic>M. sorghi</italic> to be a synonym for <italic>M. sacchari</italic>, but both forms were still listed as separate taxa by Blackman and Eastop <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Blackman3">[22]</xref>, and it is still not clear whether <italic>M. sacchari</italic> constitutes a single species or a complex of sibling taxa.</p>
<p>In any case, <italic>M. sacchari</italic> is a major pest of sorghum and sugarcane. On sugarcane, it is considered to be the most common and most efficient vector of the <italic>Sugarcane yellow leaf virus</italic> (ScYLV), which causes yellow leaf disease <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Rott1">[23]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Schenck1">[24]</xref>, a disease of worldwide economic importance <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Gonalves1">[25]</xref>–<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Rassaby1">[27]</xref>. The aphid is also a major pest of sorghum, causing direct damage (sap feeding) and indirect damage (sooty mould) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Singh1">[19]</xref>. Varietal resistance against <italic>M. sacchari</italic> is one of the main control tactics suggested both for sugarcane <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Akbar1">[28]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Fartek1">[29]</xref> and sorghum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Singh1">[19]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Wang1">[30]</xref>. Most plant resistance to aphids is specific to a single aphid species or to a few biotypes within a species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Dogimont1">[31]</xref> and it has been demonstrated that variability exists among clonal lineages of aphids in their response to resistant cultivars <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Caillaud1">[32]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Lombaert1">[33]</xref>. Therefore, characterisation of the genetic diversity of aphids is critical for breeding durable and efficient resistance, which has to account for the worldwide diversity of these pests and the potential emergence of new invasive biotypes.</p>
<p>Based on a worldwide sample of aphids covering its area of distribution (home range as well as invasive range) and using microsatellite markers and sequencing of a fragment of the mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase I gene (COI), the purpose of this study was to evaluate 1) the mode of reproduction of <italic>M. sacchari</italic>; 2) molecular evidence for the existence of sibling species; and 3) its genetic diversity and structuring according to host and locality.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="materials|methods">
<title>Materials and Methods</title>
<sec id="s2a">
<title>Insect samples</title>
<p>Here, an ‘individual’ refers to one individual aphid and a ‘sample’ refers a several individuals collected from the same host plant species in a given locality and date. The complete set of individuals (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0106067.s003">Table S1</xref>) comprised 57 samples from 42 localities in a total of 15 countries or provinces, and from five host plants: sugarcane, pearl millet, and three wild or cultivated sorghum species (<italic>Sorghum bicolor</italic>, <italic>S. halepense, S. verticilliflorum</italic>). The three sorghum species were considered as a single host plant, hereafter named ‘sorghum’.</p>
<p>Aphids were collected from wild or cultivated plants and placed in 70% ethanol in Eppendorf tubes, kept frozen at −80°C until they were processed. Only a few aphids were collected on each plant sampled to avoid collecting several individuals from the same colony.</p>
<p>Sampling was carried out from 2002 to 2009 by our team in Reunion Island and by colleagues in the other parts of the world (see acknowledgements). Geographic coordinates of sampling localities are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0106067.s003">Table S1</xref>. No specific permissions were required for sampling aphids in these locations. The field studies did not involve endangered or protected species.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b">
<title>DNA extraction, genotyping and sequencing</title>
<sec id="s2b1">
<title>DNA extraction</title>
<p>DNA was extracted using the “salting-out” protocol of Sunnucks and Hales <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Sunnucks1">[34]</xref>. Briefly, it consists in extracting DNA from whole aphids by crushing them in a TNES/Proteinase K buffer and precipitating DNA in ethanol. This method is simple and fast, and provided sufficient DNA for phylogeny and microsatellite PCR analyses.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2b2">
<title>Genotyping</title>
<p>According to their polymorphism, ten microsatellite loci (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0106067-t001">Tab. 1</xref>) were selected among the 14 previously developed by our team for <italic>M. sacchari</italic> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Molecular1">[35]</xref>. PCR reactions were performed with labelled primers and multiplexed into two mixes (Type-it, standard procedure, Qiagen), and the following thermocycling protocol was used: denaturation at 95°C for 15 min, 25 denaturation cycles for 30 s at 94°C, a 1-min 30 s annealing step at 54°C, and a 30-s elongation step at 72°C. We used an ABI prism 3110 for genotyping after addition of an internal size standard for each sample (GeneScan LIZ 500, Applied Biosystems). Alleles were identified at each locus by comparison with the size standard using GeneMapper version 2.5 software (Applied Biosystems).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0106067-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption>
<title>Observed microsatellite Multi Locus Genotypes (MLG): allele size (bp) at each locus, distribution by host plant and in each of the five Multi Locus Lineages (MLL) defined with GENCLONE. Within MLL allelic variations are in bold.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0106067-t001-1" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.t001" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLG</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-G08</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-G403</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-B03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-C08</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-G01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-E01</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-G12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-E03</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-D02</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CIR-Ms-G02</td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>210</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>316</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms30</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>204</bold>/206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>318</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms31</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/<bold>230</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>254</bold>/<bold>314</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms41</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>226</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>252</bold>/<bold>314</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms42</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>226</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>254</bold>/<bold>314</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms301</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>248</bold>/<bold>312</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms302</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>248</bold>/<bold>314</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms303</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>298</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms304</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>310</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms305</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>312</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms306</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>314</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms307</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>316</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms308</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214//216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>318</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms309</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253//253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189//203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>343</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms310</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>250</bold>/<bold>345</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms311</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>252</bold>/<bold>312</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms312</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>252</bold>/<bold>314</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms313</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>254</bold>/<bold>312</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms314</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>254/314</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms315</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">189/203</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206/<bold>206</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176/176</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/<bold>228</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>256/314</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL B</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188/<bold>193</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226/<bold>232</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>199</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188/<bold>193</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226/<bold>252</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>199</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms121</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188/<bold>191</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226/<bold>232</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>199</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms122</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188/<bold>191</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226/<bold>232</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>201</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/<bold>199</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/<bold>210</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/<bold>234</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>199</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/<bold>199</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/<bold>210</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204/212</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/<bold>232</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>199</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/<bold>199</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/<bold>212</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/<bold>232</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>199</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/<bold>199</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/<bold>210</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/<bold>232</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>199</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms12</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>195/</bold>197</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/<bold>210</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/<bold>232</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>205</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms15</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/<bold>199</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/<bold>210</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/<bold>232</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>201</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms16</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>195/</bold>197</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/<bold>210</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/<bold>232</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>203</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms21</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>195/</bold>197</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/<bold>210</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/216</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/193</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228/<bold>234</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">199/<bold>203</bold></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms9</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/<bold>216</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/188</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226/234</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201/201</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms10</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233/233</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">251/259</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">213/213</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/199</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185/206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">247/247</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212/<bold>218</bold></td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186/188</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">226/234</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201/201</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms32</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/197</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198/206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/245</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208/212</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>216/</bold>224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/222</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216/216</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ms33</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229/229</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">253/253</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">215/215</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197/197</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198/206</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245/245</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208/212</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>224</bold>/224</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220/222</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216/216</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2b3">
<title>Sequencing</title>
<p>A total of 91 aphids were chosen among the worldwide sample to represent different combinations of region and host plant. COI fragments were amplified using the LCO1490 and HCO2198 primers designed by Folmer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Folmer1">[36]</xref>. PCR was carried out using the protocol of Kim and Lee <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Kim1">[37]</xref>. PCR products were purified and sequenced by a subcontractor (Cogenics), and a consensus sequence of 658 pb was chosen for later analyses.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s2c">
<title>Data analysis</title>
<sec id="s2c1">
<title>Clonal diversity analysis</title>
<p>Micro-Checker software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-VanOosterhout1">[38]</xref> was run on the whole population. No evidence was found for the presence of null alleles. Any single combination of alleles was retrieved from genotyping data and arranged as unique multilocus genotypes (MLGs). Given the clonal reproduction of <italic>M. sacchari</italic>, we assumed that the different occurrences of the same MLG in a sample were the result of local clonal reproduction. We therefore retained a single representative of each MLG in each of the 57 samples for genetic and diversity analysis.</p>
<p>Using GENCLONE software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-ArnaudHaond1">[39]</xref>, we computed a matrix of pairwise genetic distance between MLGs computed as the number of allelic differences between MLGs <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-ArnaudHaond2">[40]</xref>. Examination of the distribution of these distances enabled us to define a threshold below which MLGs were considered to belong to the same multilocus lineage (MLL), i.e. genotypes which differed slightly due to mutation or scoring errors according to Arnaud-Haond et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-ArnaudHaond2">[40]</xref>. The same matrix of pairwise distances was also used to construct a minimum spanning network using HAPSTAR software <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Teacher1">[41]</xref>. On the set of identical loci within each MLL, we computed p<sub>sex</sub>, the probability that the repeated MLGs originated from distinct sexual reproductive events. A p<sub>sex</sub> value lower than 0.01 supported the hypothesis that MLGs originated from the same MLL <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-ArnaudHaond2">[40]</xref>. To describe clonal diversity, we computed the clonal richness index as R  =  (G-1)/(N-1), where G is the number of genotypes detected (either MLGs for R<sub>MLG</sub> or MLL for R<sub>MLL</sub>), and N is the number of samples <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Dorken1">[42]</xref>.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c2">
<title>Phylogenetic analysis</title>
<p>Sequence alignments of the COI gene were performed using Geneious software version 5.6.6 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Biomatters1">[43]</xref>. Five sequences from <italic>M. sacchari</italic> individuals collected in India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Rebijith1">[44]</xref> were retrieved from GenBank and added to our data. Four sequences from three species of the <italic>Melanaphis</italic> genus were also retrieved from GenBank and used as outgroups: <italic>M. donacis</italic> (referenced HQ443314), <italic>M. bambusae</italic> (referenced EU701747 and EU701746) and <italic>M. japonica</italic> (referenced GU457792). Maximum Likelihood inference performed with MEGA6 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Tamura1">[45]</xref> was used to choose the most reliable evolutionary model of base substitution to infer the evolutionary history. Based on the AICc criterion, the best model proved to be the General Time Reversible model with gamma distribution of evolutionary rates among sites (GTR+G) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Nei1">[46]</xref>. The GTR+G model was then used with MEGA6 to reconstruct the subsequent phylogenetic tree through the Maximum Likelihood method, with 10,000 bootstrap replicates for branch support.</p>
</sec><sec id="s2c3">
<title>Population genetic analysis</title>
<p>We used GENEPOP <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Raymond1">[47]</xref> to compute population genetics parameters for each of the MLLs delimited by GENCLONE. We tested departures from Hardy–Weinberg equilibrium and heterozygote deficit and excess, and calculated population fixation index values (F<sub>is</sub>). Genetic differentiation between MLLs was tested with a G test and pairwise F<sub>ST</sub> were computed.</p>
</sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3">
<title>Results</title>
<sec id="s3a">
<title>Genetic and clonal diversity</title>
<p>We genotyped a total of 1333 aphids using the ten microsatellite markers. When we retained a single representative of each MLG in each of the 57 samples, this yielded a dataset containing 98 individuals.</p>
<p>Global genetic diversity was low, with 36 MLGs found (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0106067-t001">Table 1</xref>). Global clonal richness was also low, with a R<sub>MLG</sub>  = 0.361. The distribution of the pairwise number of different alleles between MLG appeared multimodal, with a first minimum located at a distance of five alleles (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0106067.s001">Figure S1</xref>). Grouping MLGs which differed by one to four alleles defined five groups. Calculation of p<sub>sex</sub> on the set of identical loci within each of these five groups yielded values &lt;0.01, confirming that the MLGs within each group were unlikely to have derived from distinct reproductive events. We therefore considered that the five groups defined five multilocus lineages (MLLs) which grouped slightly distinct MLGs resulting from step mutations or scoring errors (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0106067-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0106067-g001">Figure 1</xref>). Considering the five MLLs, clonal richness was very low, as shown by the R<sub>MLL</sub>  = 0.041.</p>
<fig id="pone-0106067-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption>
<title>Minimum spanning network of <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> microsatellite distances computed as the number of allele differences between MLGs. Each node represents one step in the network, i.e. a distance of one allele.</title>
<p>The numbers in the circles represent MLGs according to <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0106067-t001">Table 1</xref>. Coloured backgrounds represent the Multi Locus Lineages (MLLs). MLGs in the same dashed line box share the same COI haplotype.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.g001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b">
<title>Phylogenetic relationship within samples</title>
<p>Within our 91 <italic>M. sacchari</italic> COI sequences, only three distinct haplotypes were observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0106067-g002">Figure 2</xref>). One haplotype was observed in individuals belonging to MLL-A, MLL-B or MLL-E (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0106067-g001">Figure 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0106067-g002">Figure 2</xref>). The second haplotype was only observed in individuals belonging to MLL-C. The third haplotype was observed in individuals belonging to MLL-D. No association of haplotypes with the host plant was observed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0106067-g002">Figure 2</xref>). These three haplotypes differed from the two available in GenBank from five Indian samples, giving a total of five haplotypes and five nucleotide substitutions among 96 <italic>M. sacchari</italic> individuals. The phylogenetic tree built from a 658 bp fragment of the COI gene clearly separated the four <italic>Melanaphis</italic> species with &gt;80% bootstrap support (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0106067.s002">Figure S2</xref>). But within the <italic>M. sacchari</italic> sequences, the presence of distinct taxa was not supported by bootstrap analysis at the 80% threshold. Intraspecific genetic divergence in <italic>M. sacchari</italic> was low, with a mean pairwise divergence of 0.19% (range 0.000.61%). When the five <italic>M. sacchari</italic> sequences retrieved from GenBank were excluded, the mean divergence was 0.17% (range 0.000.30%). The mean divergence of <italic>M. sacchari</italic> sequences with the closest taxa, <italic>M. japonica</italic>, was 1.06% (range 0.92%1.39%).</p>
<fig id="pone-0106067-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption>
<title>COI haplotype network (top), in which <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> COI sequences originating from the present study are numbered from 1 to 3.</title>
<p><italic>M. sacchari</italic> GenBank COI sequences from India <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Rebijith1">[44]</xref> are numbered 4 (JX051388, JX05189, JX051390) and 5 (HQ112185, JX051402). Mj  =  <italic>Melanaphis japonica</italic> COI sequence from GenBank (GU457792). Distribution as a function of host plant (middle): sorghum (blue) vs. sugarcane (red). Distribution as a function of MLL (bottom): A (green), B (blue), C (yellow), D (violin), E (red).</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.g002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c">
<title>Standard population genetics</title>
<p>Plotting the results of the factorial correspondence analysis with GENETIX confirmed the grouping of the 36 MLGs in five MLLs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0106067-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Factor 1 distinguished MLL-A and MLL-E, and a group formed by the three MLL-B, MLL-C and MLL-D. Factor 2 distinguished MLL-E from other MLLs. Factor 3 distinguished between MLL-B, MLL-C and MLL-D.</p>
<fig id="pone-0106067-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption>
<title>Factorial correspondence analysis of microsatellite data with GENETIX.</title>
<p>Each symbol represents one of the 36 MLGs. Colours and letters refer to Multilocus Lineage (MLL) assignment with GENCLONE.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.g003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>Genetic differentiation between the five MLLs was strong, with a highly significant F<sub>st</sub> ranging from 0.262 to 0.694 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0106067.s004">Table S2</xref>).</p>
<p>The five populations comprised by each distinct MLL differed significantly from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, and showed a clear signature of asexual reproduction with a significant heterozygote excess and negative F<sub>IS</sub> values (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0106067.s005">Table S3</xref>).</p>
</sec><sec id="s3d">
<title>Geographical and host distribution of MLLs</title>
<p>Distribution of the MLLs revealed strong geographical structuring (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0106067-g004">Figure 4</xref>). MLL-A was observed in Africa, MLL-B was restricted to Australia, MLL-C exhibited the widest distribution area (South America, the Caribbean, the Indian Ocean and East Africa), MLL-D was observed in the USA, and MLL-E was only observed in China. Kenya was the only country where two MLLs were observed simultaneously: one sample (Ken1) contained a mix of MLL-A and MLL-B, one sample (Ken5) contained MLL-A alone, and three samples (Ken2, Ken3, Ken4) contained MLL-B alone.</p>
<fig id="pone-0106067-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption>
<title>Relative geographical within-state distribution of Multilocus lineages (MLL).</title>
<p>The size of circle is not proportional to the size of the sample. Aus  =  Australia, Bra  =  Brazil, Col  =  Columbia, Ecu  =  Ecuador, Gua  =  Guadeloupe, Haw  =  Hawaii, Lou  =  Louisiana, Mar  =  Martinique, Mau  =  Mauritius, Run  =  Reunion Island, Ben  =  Benin, Cam  =  Cameroon, Nig  =  Niger, Chi  =  China, Ken  =  Kenya.</p>
</caption><graphic mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.g004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"/></fig>
<p>No host plant structuring was observed: in all the countries where both sorghum and sugarcane samples were collected, each MLL was found on both host plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0106067-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p>
<table-wrap id="pone-0106067-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption>
<title>Distribution of the 98 individuals, a single representative of each MLG in each of the 57 samples, as a function of country/province and host plant.</title>
</caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0106067-t002-2" position="float" mimetype="image" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.t002" xlink:type="simple"/>
<table><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">State</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Host plant</td>
<td colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1">Number of individuals</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of samples</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL-A</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL-B</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL-C</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL-D</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MLL-E</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Benin</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sorghum</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pearl millet</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cameroon</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sorghum</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kenya</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sorghum</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Niger</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sorghum</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Australia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brazil</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Columbia</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecuador</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guadeloupe</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Martinique</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mauritius</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reunion</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sorghum</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hawaii</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Louisiana</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sorghum</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sugarcane</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">China</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sorghum</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
<td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</alternatives></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4">
<title>Discussion</title>
<p>Molecular analysis revealed a very low genetic diversity among 57 samples collected in 15 countries on two main hosts, with 36 MLGs structured in five MLLs. The distribution of MLLs was strongly structured by geography but not by the host plant (sorghum vs. sugarcane).</p>
<p>Sequencing the COI ‘barcoding’ region, a typical locus used for species discrimination and phylogeny, particularly in aphids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-CoeurdAcier1">[48]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Kim2">[49]</xref>, did not enable the detection of cryptic species in our samples. Specifically, we observed no molecular evidence for a clear separation into two species, <italic>M. sacchari</italic> and <italic>M. sorghi</italic>. We found sequence variations peaking at 0.61%, with a mean value of 0.19%, both of which are within the range of intraspecific divergence observed in the Aphididae family by Footit et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Foottit1">[50]</xref> or Lee et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Lee2">[51]</xref>.</p>
<sec id="s4a">
<title>Reproduction</title>
<p>Population genetic parameters were consistent with populations which only reproduce by apomictic parthenogenesis, as previously described by Blackman and Eastop <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Blackman3">[22]</xref>. Each population significantly differed from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium, with a high heterozygote excess. These features are a common consequence of populations which have reproduced clonally for a long time. In a global study of genetic diversity on <italic>Aphis gossypii,</italic> Carletto et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Carletto1">[52]</xref> obtained similar results to ours as they observed low genetic diversity, with the predominance of a few clones at the worldwide scale reproducing only by apomictic parthenogenesis. But later, evidence for sexual reproduction of <italic>A. gossypii</italic> was found in Iran <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Razmjou1">[53]</xref>. High genetic diversity and evidence for sexual reproduction was also observed in <italic>A. gossypii</italic> alate spring migrants in France <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Thomas1">[54]</xref>. Similarly, in the <italic>Brachycaudus helichrysi</italic> (Kaltenbach) sibling species H2, a sexually reproducing population was identified in India, despite almost exclusively clonal reproduction at the worldwide scale <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Piffaretti1">[11]</xref>. This shows that sexual admixture can still exist in a local population even in species which are highly clonal at the worldwide scale. A holocycle has been observed in <italic>M. sacchari</italic> in Asia <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Blackman1">[16]</xref> and this suggests that higher genetic diversity may exist in some parts of its geographic distribution area even if our sampling did not allow us to observe it.</p>
</sec><sec id="s4b">
<title>Geographic genetic structure</title>
<p>Microsatellite analyses showed that population structuring at the worldwide scale was only influenced by geography, delimiting five MLLs corresponding to five geographic zones: Africa, China, Australia, USA, and South America – Indian Ocean (including Kenya) and the Caribbean. Variation within each of the four biggest zones (excluding China where only one sample was analysed) was low, with MLGs within a zone differing by a few step mutations, which we suggest is due to one or few separate introductions. These results suggest that each of the five zones was colonized separately following the introduction of one or a few clones from the region of origin of <italic>M. sacchari</italic>, which the present study did not allow us to identify. At least two of the five MLLs covered a very wide geographic area and matched the pattern of a single asexual genotype with a high capacity for dispersal which would have spread across a large area: MLL-A was observed in West and East Africa, and MLL-C was observed in South America, the Indian Ocean, East Africa, and the Caribbean. Both MLLs match the definition of “superclone” <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Vorburger1">[7]</xref>, characterised by geographically and ecologically widespread distribution, which has already been documented in several aphid species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Harrison1">[9]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Llewellyn1">[10]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Piffaretti1">[11]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Figueroa1">[55]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-ZepedaPaulo1">[56]</xref>.</p>
<p>The low rate of genetic diversity observed in the whole geographic area covered by our study, and the lack of published data about the dates of introduction of <italic>M. sacchari</italic> in the countries sampled, meant we were not able to reconstruct the invasion routes of this species. The only exception was continental USA. <italic>M. sacchari</italic> was first described in Hawaii in the late 19<sup>th</sup> century <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Foottit2">[57]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Zimmerman1">[58]</xref>, and was first recorded in continental USA at the end of the 1970s in Florida <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Hall1">[59]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Hall2">[60]</xref> and in 2001 in Louisiana <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-White1">[18]</xref>. In our study, almost all individuals sampled in Louisiana and Hawaii belonged to the same MLG, Ms9, and shared the same COI haplotype, neither of which were observed in other regions. This strongly suggests that <italic>M. sacchari</italic> was introduced in continental USA from Hawaii. This finding is noteable, as one would expect an introduction into continental USA from either South America or the Caribbean, a shorter invasion route. However, Mondor et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0106067-Mondor1">[61]</xref> emphasized that the relationship between the colonization of the Hawaiian Islands by an aphid species and its presence in continental USA was due to the high rate of commercial exchanges between the two. Here we provide an example of reverse colonization from Hawaii to continental USA. In Kenya, MLL-C was observed in three samples from the coastal region of Kenya but was not found in a sample collected inland. This underlines the fact that, even though <italic>M. sacchari</italic> has been recorded in almost all areas where sugarcane is cultivated, the possibility for the expansion of some genotypes should be taken seriously, mainly its unknown potential impact on the epidemiology of the viral diseases it transmits.</p>
</sec></sec><sec id="s5">
<title>Supporting Information</title>
<supplementary-material id="pone.0106067.s001" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.s001" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Distribution of the pairwise number of different alleles between MLGs.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0106067.s002" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.s002" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Figure S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Molecular Phylogenetic analysis by Maximum Likelihood method with bootstrap support (10,000 replicates) using 658 bp cytochrome c oxidase subunit I sequences from 100 </bold><bold><italic>Melanaphis</italic></bold><bold> spp. individuals.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0106067.s003" mimetype="application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.s003" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S1</label><caption>
<p><bold>Voucher number, sampling information, GenBank accession and SSR genotyping of individual aphids.</bold></p>
<p>(XLSX)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0106067.s004" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.s004" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S2</label><caption>
<p><bold>Genetic differentiation between MLLs: pairwise F<sub>ST</sub> and significance of the G test computed with GENEPOP.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="pone.0106067.s005" mimetype="application/pdf" xlink:href="info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0106067.s005" position="float" xlink:type="simple"><label>Table S3</label><caption>
<p><bold>Population genetics parameters for each MLL.</bold></p>
<p>(PDF)</p>
</caption></supplementary-material></sec></body>
<back>
<ack>
<p>The authors would like to thank all those who helped collect aphid samples worldwide: T. Martin (Benin), T. Brévault (Cameroon), A. Ratnadass (Niger), C. Agosa Kirungu and J.-F. Martiné (Kenya), N. Sallam, P. Samson and R. Goebel (Australia), P. Silvie and M.V. Sampaio (Brazil), J.-H. Daugrois (Caribbean), W. White (Louisiana), S. Ganeshan (Mauritius), D. Gualle and J Mendoza (Ecuador), J.-C. Girard (Columbia), S. Schenk (Hawaii), R. Tibère and Alex Nibouche (Reunion), Jianwen Chen (China). The authors also thank B. Facon for his helpful advice.</p>
</ack>
<ref-list>
<title>References</title>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Lee1"><label>1</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary genetics of invasive species</article-title>. <source>Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>386</fpage>–<lpage>391</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Amsellem1"><label>2</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Amsellem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Noyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Bourgeois</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hossaert-McKey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Comparison of genetic diversity of the invasive weed <italic>Rubus alceifolius</italic> Poir. (Rosaceae) in its native range and in areas of introduction, using amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP) markers</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>–<lpage>455</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Bossdorf1"><label>3</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bossdorf</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Auge</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lafuma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siemann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Phenotypic and genetic differentiation between native and introduced plant populations</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source> <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Dlugosch1"><label>4</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dlugosch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Founding events in species invasions: genetic variation, adaptive evolution, and the role of multiple introductions</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>431</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Grapputo1"><label>5</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grapputo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindstroem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lyytinen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mappes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>The voyage of an invasive species across continents: genetic diversity of North American and European Colorado potato beetle populations</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>4207</fpage>–<lpage>4219</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Vrijenhoek1"><label>6</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Vrijenhoek RC, Parker ED Jr (2009) Geographical parthenogenesis: general purpose genotypes and frozen niche variation. In: Schön I, Martens K, van Dijk P, editors. Lost sex. The evolutionary biology of parthenogenesis: Springer Netherlands. 99–131.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Vorburger1"><label>7</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vorburger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sunnucks</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Environmentally related patterns of reproductive modes in the aphid <italic>Myzus persicae</italic> and the predominance of two ‘superclones’ in Victoria, Australia</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>3493</fpage>–<lpage>3504</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Chen1"><label>8</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanlerberghe-Masutti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barchia</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McLoon</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Evidence of superclones in Australian cotton aphid <italic>Aphis gossypii</italic> Glover (Aphididae: Hemiptera)</article-title>. <source>Pest management science</source> <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>938</fpage>–<lpage>948</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Harrison1"><label>9</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mondor</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evidence for an Invasive Aphid “Superclone”: Extremely low genetic diversity in Oleander Aphid (<italic>Aphis nerii</italic>) populations in the Southern United States</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e17524</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Llewellyn1"><label>10</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Llewellyn</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loxdale</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brookes</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Migration and genetic structure of the grain aphid (<italic>Sitobion avenae</italic>) in Britain related to climate and clonal fluctuation as revealed using microsatellites</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>21</fpage>–<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Piffaretti1"><label>11</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Piffaretti</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clamens</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanlerberghe-Masutti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Call</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Regular or covert sex defines two lineages and worldwide superclones within the leaf curl plum aphid (<italic>Brachycaudus helichrysi</italic>, Kaltenbach)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>3916</fpage>–<lpage>3932</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Facon1"><label>12</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Facon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Genton</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shykoff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jarne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Estoup</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A general eco-evolutionary framework for understanding bioinvasions</article-title>. <source>Trends in Ecology &amp; Evolution</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>130</fpage>–<lpage>135</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Ward1"><label>13</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gaskin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Ecological genetics of plant invasion: what do we know?</article-title> <source>Invasive Plant Science and Management</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>98</fpage>–<lpage>109</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Loxdale1"><label>14</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loxdale</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Was Dan Janzen (1977) right about aphid clones being a ‘super-organism’, ie a single ‘evolutionary individual’? New insights from the use of molecular marker systems</article-title>. <source>Mitteilungen der Deutschen Gesellschaft für Allgemeine und Angewandte Entomologie</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>–<lpage>449</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Loxdale2"><label>15</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Loxdale HD (2009) What's in a clone: the rapid evolution of aphid asexual lineages in relation to geography, host plant adaptation and resistance to pesticides. In: Schön I, Martens K, van Dijk P, editors. Lost sex. The evolutionary biology of parthenogenesis: Springer Netherlands. 535–557.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Blackman1"><label>16</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Blackman RL, Eastop VF (2000) Aphids of the world crops: an identification and information guide 2nd edition. Chichester, UK: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Mead1"><label>17</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mead FW (1978) <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> (Zehntner) – Florida – New continental United States record. Cooperative Plant Pest Report 3.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-White1"><label>18</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reagan</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title><italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> (Homoptera: Aphididae), a sugarcane pest new to Louisiana</article-title>. <source>Florida Entomologist</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>435</fpage>–<lpage>436</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Singh1"><label>19</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>BU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Padmaja</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seetharama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Biology and management of the sugarcane aphid, <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> (Zehntner) (Homoptera: Aphididae), in sorghum: a review</article-title>. <source>Crop Protection</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>739</fpage>–<lpage>755</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Blackman2"><label>20</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Blackman RL, Eastop VF, Brown PA (1990) The biology and taxonomy of the aphids transmitting barley yellow dwarf virus. In: Burnett PA, editor. World Perspectives on Barley Yellow Dwarf International Workshop. Udine (Italy): CIMMYT. 197–214.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Remaudire1"><label>21</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Remaudière G, Remaudière M (1997) Catalogue of the world's Aphididae. Paris, France: INRA.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Blackman3"><label>22</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Blackman RL, Eastop VF (2006) Aphids on the world's herbaceous plants and shrubs. Chichester, UK: John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Rott1"><label>23</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rott</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirkov</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schenck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Recent advances in research on <italic>Sugarcane yellow leaf virus</italic>, the causal agent of sugarcane yellow leaf</article-title>. <source>Sugar Cane International</source> <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>–<lpage>27</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Schenck1"><label>24</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schenck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehrer</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Factors affecting the transmission and spread of <italic>Sugarcane yellow leaf virus</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Disease</source> <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>1085</fpage>–<lpage>1088</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Gonalves1"><label>25</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonçalves</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Landell</surname><given-names>MGA</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Virus diseases of sugarcane. A constant challenge to sugarcane breeding in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Functional Plant Science and Biotechnology</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>–<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Lehrer1"><label>26</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lehrer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Komor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Impact of <italic>Sugarcane yellow leaf virus</italic> on growth and sugar yield of sugarcane</article-title>. <source>Journal of General Plant Pathology</source> <volume>75</volume>: <fpage>288</fpage>–<lpage>296</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Rassaby1"><label>27</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rassaby</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Letourmy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaume</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Irey</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Impact of <italic>Sugarcane yellow leaf virus</italic> on sugarcane yield and juice quality in Réunion Island</article-title>. <source>European Journal of Plant Pathology</source> <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>459</fpage>–<lpage>466</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Akbar1"><label>28</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Akbar</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Showler</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beuzelin</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reagan</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gravois</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Evaluation of aphid resistance among sugarcane cultivars in Louisiana</article-title>. <source>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</source> <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>699</fpage>–<lpage>704</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Fartek1"><label>29</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fartek</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nibouche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Turpin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Costet</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reynaud</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Resistance to <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> in the sugarcane cultivar R 365</article-title>. <source>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</source> <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>270</fpage>–<lpage>278</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Wang1"><label>30</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Efficient and fine mapping of RMES1 conferring resistance to sorghum aphid <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic></article-title>. <source>Molecular Breeding</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>777</fpage>–<lpage>784</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Dogimont1"><label>31</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dogimont</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bendahmane</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chovelon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boissot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Host plant resistance to aphids in cultivated crops: genetic and molecular bases, and interactions with aphid populations</article-title>. <source>Comptes Rendus Biologies</source> <volume>333</volume>: <fpage>566</fpage>–<lpage>573</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Caillaud1"><label>32</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caillaud</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dedryver</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Di Pietro</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Clonal variability in the response of <italic>Sitobion avenae</italic> (Homoptera: Aphididae) to resistant and susceptible wheat</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source> <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>–<lpage>195</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Lombaert1"><label>33</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lombaert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Carletto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Piotte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fauvergue</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecoq</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Response of the melon aphid, <italic>Aphis gossypii</italic>, to host-plant resistance: evidence for high adaptive potential despite low genetic variability</article-title>. <source>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</source> <volume>133</volume>: <fpage>46</fpage>–<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Sunnucks1"><label>34</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sunnucks</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Numerous transposed sequences of mitochondrial cytochrome oxidase I–II in aphids of the genus <italic>Sitobion</italic> (Hemiptera: Aphididae)</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>510</fpage>–<lpage>524</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Molecular1"><label>35</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><collab xlink:type="simple">Molecular Ecology Resources Primer Development Consortium</collab>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Andris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aradottir</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arnau</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Audzijonyte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Permanent Genetic Resources added to Molecular Ecology Resources Database 1 June 2010 – 31 July 2010</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1106</fpage>–<lpage>1108</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Folmer1"><label>36</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Folmer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeh</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lutz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vrijenhoek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>DNA primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit I from diverse metazoan invertebrates</article-title>. <source>Molecular marine biology and biotechnology</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>294</fpage>–<lpage>299</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Kim1"><label>37</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>A molecular phylogeny of the tribe Aphidini (Insecta: Hemiptera: Aphididae) based on the mitochondrial tRNA/COII, 12S/16S and the nuclear EF1α; genes</article-title>. <source>Systematic Entomology</source> <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>711</fpage>–<lpage>721</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-VanOosterhout1"><label>38</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Oosterhout</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wills</surname><given-names>DPM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shipley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Micro-Checker: software for identifying and correcting genotyping errors in microsatellite data</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Notes</source> <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>535</fpage>–<lpage>538</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-ArnaudHaond1"><label>39</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnaud-Haond</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belkhir</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>GENCLONE: a computer program to analyse genotypic data, test for clonality and describe spatial clonal organization</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Notes</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>–<lpage>17</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-ArnaudHaond2"><label>40</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arnaud-Haond</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alberto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Serrão</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Standardizing methods to address clonality in population studies</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>5115</fpage>–<lpage>5139</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Teacher1"><label>41</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teacher</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>HapStar: automated haplotype network layout and visualization</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>–<lpage>153</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Dorken1"><label>42</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorken</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Severely reduced sexual reproduction in northern populations of a clonal plant, <italic>Decodon verticillatus</italic> (Lythraceae)</article-title>. <source>Journal of Ecology</source> <volume>89</volume>: <fpage>339</fpage>–<lpage>350</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Biomatters1"><label>43</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Biomatters (2012) Geneious version 5.6.6.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Rebijith1"><label>44</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rebijith</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Asokan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>NKK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chaitanya</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>DNA barcoding and elucidation of cryptic aphid species (Hemiptera: Aphididae) in India</article-title>. <source>Bulletin of Entomological Research</source> <volume>103</volume>: <fpage>601</fpage>–<lpage>610</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Tamura1"><label>45</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>MEGA6: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis Version 6.0</article-title>. <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>2725</fpage>–<lpage>2729</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Nei1"><label>46</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Nei M, Kumar S (2000). Molecular evolution and phylogenetics. Oxford University Press, New York.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Raymond1"><label>47</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rousset</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>GenePop on the Web</article-title>. <volume>v</volume>: <fpage>3.4</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-CoeurdAcier1"><label>48</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Coeur d'Acier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jousselin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rasplus</surname><given-names>J-Y</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Phylogeny of the Genus <italic>Aphis</italic> Linnaeus, 1758 (Homoptera: Aphididae) inferred from mitochondrial DNA sequences</article-title>. <source>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution</source> <volume>42</volume> <fpage>598</fpage>–<lpage>611</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Kim2"><label>49</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Molecular systematics of the genus <italic>Megoura</italic> (Hemiptera: Aphididae) using mitochondrial and nuclear DNA sequences</article-title>. <source>Molecules and Cells</source> <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>510</fpage>–<lpage>522</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Foottit1"><label>50</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foottit</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maw</surname><given-names>HEL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Von Dohlen</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>PDN</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Species identification of aphids (Insecta: Hemiptera: Aphididae) through DNA barcodes</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source> <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1189</fpage>–<lpage>1201</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Lee2"><label>51</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Barcoding aphids (Hemiptera: Aphididae) of the Korean Peninsula: updating the global data set</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source> <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>32</fpage>–<lpage>37</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Carletto1"><label>52</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carletto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lombaert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chavigny</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brévault</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lapchin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Ecological specialization of the aphid <italic>Aphis gossypii</italic> Glover on cultivated host plants</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>2198</fpage>–<lpage>2212</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Razmjou1"><label>53</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Razmjou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vorburger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moharramipour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mirhoseini</surname><given-names>SZ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fathipour</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Host associated differentiation and evidence for sexual reproduction in Iranian populations of the cotton aphid, <italic>Aphis gossypii</italic></article-title>. <source>Entomologia Experimentalis et Applicata</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>–<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Thomas1"><label>54</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boissot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanlerberghe-Masutti</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>What do spring migrants reveal about sex and host selection in the melon aphid?</article-title> <source>BMC Evolutionary Biology</source> <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Figueroa1"><label>55</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Le Gallic</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prunier-Leterme</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briones</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Genetic structure and clonal diversity of an introduced pest in Chile, the cereal aphid <italic>Sitobion avenae</italic></article-title>. <source>Heredity</source> <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>24</fpage>–<lpage>33</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-ZepedaPaulo1"><label>56</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zepeda-Paulo</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramírez</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuentes-Contreras</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Margaritopoulos</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>The invasion route for an insect pest species: the tobacco aphid in the New World</article-title>. <source>Molecular Ecology</source> <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>4738</fpage>–<lpage>4752</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Foottit2"><label>57</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foottit</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maw</surname><given-names>HEL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pike</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Aphids (Hemiptera: Aphididae and Adelgidae) of Hawai'i: Annotated List and Key to Species of an Adventive Fauna</article-title>. <source>Pacific Science</source> <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>–<lpage>30</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Zimmerman1"><label>58</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="book" xlink:type="simple">Zimmerman EC (1948) Insects of Hawaii. Vol. 5. Homoptera: Sternorrhyncha. Honolulu: University of Hawaii Press. 464 p.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Hall1"><label>59</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>The sugarcane aphid, <italic>Melanaphis sacchari</italic> (Zehntner), in Florida</article-title>. <source>Journal of the American Society Sugar Cane Technologists</source> <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>26</fpage>–<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Hall2"><label>60</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Insects and mites associated with sugarcane in Florida</article-title>. <source>Florida Entomologist</source> <volume>71</volume>: <fpage>138</fpage>–<lpage>150</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
<ref id="pone.0106067-Mondor1"><label>61</label>
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mondor</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tremblay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Messing</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Morphological and ecological traits promoting aphid colonization of the Hawaiian Islands</article-title>. <source>Biological Invasions</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>87</fpage>–<lpage>100</lpage>.</mixed-citation>
</ref>
</ref-list></back>
</article>